<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="/~files/feed-premium.xsl"?>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:admin="http://webns.net/mvcb/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:feedpress="https://feed.press/xmlns" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <feedpress:locale>en</feedpress:locale>
    <atom:link rel="via" href="http://feeds.propublica.org/propublica/main"/>
    <atom:link rel="self" href="http://feeds.propublica.org/propublica/main"/>
    <atom:link rel="hub" href="http://feedpress.superfeedr.com/"/>
    <title>ProPublica: Articles and Investigations</title>
    <link>http://www.propublica.org/</link>
    <description/>
    <dc:language>en</dc:language>
    <dc:creator>ProPublica</dc:creator>
    <dc:rights>Copyright 2017</dc:rights>
    <dc:date>2017-03-12T17:22:22-05:00</dc:date>
    <admin:generatorAgent rdf:resource="http://expressionengine.com/"/>
    <item>
      <title>When It Comes to Wall Street, Preet Bharara Is No Hero</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5497306</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/when-it-comes-to-wall-street-preet-bharara-is-no-hero/#28699</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/jesse_eisinger/">Jesse Eisinger</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>After his election in 1968, President Richard Nixon asked Robert Morgenthau, the US Attorney for the Southern District of New York, to resign. Morgenthau refused to leave voluntarily, saying it degraded the office to treat it as a patronage position.</p>

<p>Nixon&#8217;s move precipitated a political crisis. The president named a replacement. Powerful politicians lined up to support Morgenthau. Morgenthau had taken on mobsters and power brokers. He had repeatedly prosecuted Roy Cohn, the sleazy New York lawyer who had been Senator Joe McCarthy&#8217;s right-hand man. (One of Cohn&#8217;s clients and prot&#233;g&#233;s was a young New York City real estate developer named Donald Trump.) When Cohn complained that Morgenthau had a vendetta against him, Morgenthau replied, &#8220;A man is not immune from prosecution merely because a United States Attorney happens not to like him.&#8221;</p>

<p>Morgenthau carried that confrontational attitude to the world of business. He pioneered the Southern District&#8217;s approach to corporate crime. When his prosecutors took on corporate fraud, they did not reach settlements that called for fines, the current fashion these days. They filed criminal charges against the executives responsible.</p>

<p>Before Morgenthau, the Department of Justice focused on two-bit corporate misdeeds&#8212;Ponzi schemes and boiler room operations. Morgenthau changed that. His prosecutors went after CEOs and their enablers&#8212;the accountants and lawyers who abetted the frauds or looked the other way. &#8220;How do you justify prosecuting a nineteen-year old who sells drugs on a street corner when you say it&#8217;s too complicated to go after the people who move the money?&#8221; he once asked.</p>

<p>Morgenthau&#8217;s years as United States Attorney were followed by political success. He was elected New York County District Attorney in 1974, the first of seven consecutive terms for that office.</p>

<p>There are parallels between Morgenthau, and Preet Bharara, the U.S. attorney for the Southern District who was fired by President Trump this weekend.</p>

<p>Like Morgenthau, the 48-year old Bharara leaves the office of US Attorney for the Southern District celebrated for taking on corrupt and powerful politicians. Bharara prosecuted two of the infamous &#8220;three men in a room&#8221; who ran New York state: Sheldon Silver, the Democratic speaker of the assembly and Dean Skelos, the Republican Senate majority leader.</p>

<p>He won convictions of a startling array of local politicians, carrying on the work of the Moreland Commission, an ethics inquiry created and then dismissed by New York&#8217;s Gov. Andrew Cuomo. (This weekend, Bharara cryptically tweeted that &#8220;I know what the Moreland Commission must have felt like,&#8221; a suggestion that he was fired as he was pursuing cases pointed at Trump or his allies.)</p>

<p>But the record shows that Bharara was much less aggressive when it came to confronting Wall Street&#8217;s misdeeds.</p>

<p>President Obama appointed Bharara in 2009, amid the wreckage of the worst financial crisis since the Great Depression. He inherited ongoing investigations into the collapse, including a probe against Lehman Brothers.</p>

<p>He also inherited something he and his young charges found more alluring: insider-trading cases against hedge fund managers. His office focused obsessively on those. At one point, the Southern District racked up a record of 85-0 in those cases. (Appeals courts would later throw out two prominent convictions, infuriating him and dealing blows to several other cases.)</p>

<p>Hedge funds are safer targets. The firms aren&#8217;t enmeshed in the global financial markets in the way that giant banks are. Insider trading cases are relatively easy to win and don&#8217;t address systemic abuses that helped bring down the financial system.</p>

<p>Even there his record was more mixed than is popularly understood. As Sheelah Kolhatkar demonstrates in her propulsive and riveting <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Black-Edge-Inside-Information-Wanted/dp/0812995805">&#8220;Black Edge,&#8221;</a> when it came to bringing his biggest whale to justice, Steve Cohen of SAC Capital, the Southern District blinked. They did not charge him, only securing a guilty plea from his firm.</p>

<p>Present and former prosecutors say Bharara did not give much emphasis to investigations arising from the financial meltdown, an approach shared by his boss, Attorney General Eric Holder. Justice Department insiders say many of those inquiries withered not because they were unpromising, but because <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/the-rise-of-corporate-impunity">they had little support</a>.</p>

<p>Bharara missed an opportunity by not bringing any significant criminal charges against individuals in the wake of the collapses of Lehman, investment bank Merrill Lynch, the insurer AIG, the mortgage securities and <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/banks-self-dealing-super-charged-financial-crisis">collateralized debt obligation businesses</a>, or the myriad public misrepresentations from bank CEOs about their finances.</p>

<p>Bharara and senior officials in Washington argue that there were no criminal cases to file after the 2008 crisis. But the U.S. attorney&#8217;s office in Manhattan did pursue significant civil cases against the banks for their mortgage activities, cases that had to proove misconduct by the &#8220;preponderance of the evidence.&#8221; And DOJ did win guilty pleas from the banks themselves, an indication that prosecutors might have been able to charge individuals for their part in crimes their institutions had acknowledged. Academics who studied those years, including Columbia&#8217;s Tomasz Piskorski and James Witkin and Chicago&#8217;s Amit Seru <a href="file://localhost/Users/jesseeisinger/Downloads/Misrepresentation_MBS.pdf">found widespread patterns of fraud</a> in the mortgage business.</p>

<p>The exception makes this failure all the more puzzling. As I detailed in 2014, Bharara&#8217;s office <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/04/magazine/only-one-top-banker-jail-financial-crisis.html">brought one case for misconduc</a>t during the financial crisis &#8212; against a mid-level banker. Prosecutors charged Kareem Serageldin of Credit Suisse with overseeing traders who knowingly misrepresented the value of mortgage securities. Serageldin pleaded guilty and went to prison.</p>

<p>Serageldin&#8217;s colleagues in the industry and others familiar with Credit Suisse found it hard to believe that he was the only person involved in that particular fraud.</p>

<p>Bharara&#8217;s reluctance to pursue senior executives was seen in other investigations of big banks. His office wrested a $1.7 billion fine from JPMorgan Chase over its complicity in the Bernie Madoff Ponzi scheme, but it brought no charges against individual bankers.</p>

<p>One odd aspect of his tenure was the Southern District&#8217;s willingness to defer to other jurisdictions when it came to Wall Street cases.</p>

<p>Historically, the SDNY has been the leading enforcers of securities laws, nicknamed the &#8220;sovereign district&#8221; for its propensity to grab corporate fraud cases from elsewhere on the flimsiest of jurisdictional pretexts. Under Bharara, the southern district let other U.S. attorneys claim investigations into residential mortgage-backed securities, the instruments at the heart of the financial crisis. Those other offices were not nearly as versed in complex financial cases as their colleagues in Manhattan. In addition, Bharara&#8217;s office ceded post-financial crisis investigations into foreign exchange and global interest rate manipulation to prosecutors working from the Justice Department&#8217;s headquarters.</p>

<p>Like Morgenthau, Bharara was a prominent figure in the New York landscape, given to well-orchestrated press conferences and memorable sound bites. Like Morgenthau, he did not leave office quietly, even thought the president has a longstanding right to name his own U.S. attorneys. And like Morgenthau, he may try to parlay his martyrdom into elective office.</p>

<p>But if he runs on his record of convictions, as prosecutors often do, voters might want to consider as well the list of possible targets he never pursued.</p>

             <p class="note related-note"><p>Jesse Eisinger writes about the forces that have sapped federal prosecutors of the will and authority to pursue top bankers in his forthcoming book, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Chickenshit-Club-Justice-Department-Criminals/dp/1501121367">&#8220;The Chickenshit Club.&#8221;</a></p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5497306.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Trump Administration</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-12T17:22:22-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>We Want Your Thoughts on Our Podcast</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5486906</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/podcast/item/we-want-your-thoughts-on-our-podcast/#28698</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/joaquin_sapien/">Joaquin Sapien</a>
    
</p>
                                    <style>
.player_box { display: none; }

div.article-inline-image.Right.demobbed {display: none;}
</style>

<p>Two months ago, we launched The Breakthrough, a podcast where investigative journalists tell us how they nailed their biggest stories.</p>

<p>Our first eight episodes took listeners behind the scenes of reporting from across the globe. We interviewed <a href="https://www.propublica.org/podcast/item/the-breakthrough-what-american-journalists-can-learn-reporting-under-putin">a reporter in Russia</a> who told us what it was like to face intimidation from the Kremlin, an author who <a href="https://www.propublica.org/podcast/item/the-breakthrough-meet-the-reporter-went-undercover-in-the-hermit-kingdom">went undercover as a teacher</a> in North Korean schools, and a <a href="https://www.propublica.org/podcast/item/the-breakthrough-how-a-reporter-solved-a-decades-old-murder">veteran Mississippi reporter</a> who tracked down an alleged serial killer.</p>

<p>We&#8217;re taking a break to think about where we should take the podcast from here. And we want your help.</p>

<iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/311730987&amp;color=ff5500&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false"></iframe>

<p>Tell us about what you want to hear more of, less of, and what, if anything, we might do differently.</p>

<p>To give us the feedback, please <a href="https://propublica.forms.fm/propublica-podcast-questionnaire">take this survey</a>.</p>

<p>The information you give will not only help us improve, it will also help us find sponsors so that we can keep the podcast thriving and well-funded.</p>

<p>Thank you.</p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5486906.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-10T13:54:00-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Vital Signs</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5486274</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/introducing-vital-signs/#28692</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/scott_klein/" title="View Scott Klein's other articles">Scott Klein</a>


 and <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/sisi_wei/" title="View Sisi Wei's other articles">Sisi Wei</a></p>
                                    <p>ProPublica has accumulated a wealth of data about how medicine is really practiced in the U.S. We&#8217;ve got millions of data points on things we believe everyone should know about his or her providers, like whether they&#8217;ve been barred from federal health care programs, their prescribing and treatment patterns, and how much money pharmaceutical companies pay them for things like consulting and speaking.</p>


<div class="callout">

    <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/">Vital Signs</a></h2>
<a href="https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/"><img class="border" src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_630/20170310-vital-signs-app-promo-630.jpg" /></a>
<p>Know more about your doctor. <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/">See the project.</a></p>

</div>


<p>Today we&#8217;re launching a project called <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/">Vital Signs</a> that puts the most important information from across all of our health care projects in one easy-to-use place, and can alert you when we get new information or when something happens you should know about right away, for example if your provider is now paid more per patient than 90 percent of peers, which may be a sign of overtreatment or use of more costly services.</p>

<p>Our health care databases, including Dollars for Docs and Prescriber Checkup, have long been among the most popular features of our site, and are a key part of the mission of our data team &#8212; to help people use data to make better choices and live better lives. We&#8217;ve spent years collecting, cleaning and analyzing data about hundreds of thousands of doctors and other health professionals across several different interactive databases. <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/">Vital Signs</a> lets you see what matters most across all of them, and dig deeper to explore even more data.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s split up into five general sections:</p>

<ul>
<li>Standing With Federal Health Programs</li>
<li>Office Visits and Costs</li>
<li>Relationships with Pharmaceutical and Device Companies</li>
<li>Prescribing Patterns and Habits</li>
<li>Surgical Performance</li>
</ul>

<p>Each section is color coded to make it easy to understand, and includes only the most important insights into that provider&#8217;s practice. For most data points we give you a way to compare a given metric with the provider&#8217;s peers, so you can see if he or she is doing things much differently &#8212; which may be worth talking to your provider about.</p>

<p>Not all medical providers have data in each section. Obviously, if a doctor is not a surgeon, or does not perform the surgeries we&#8217;ve got data on, you won&#8217;t see anything under Surgical Performance on that doctor&#8217;s page. Likewise, if a healthcare provider doesn&#8217;t treat Medicare patients &#8212; say a pediatrician &#8212; you may not see any data under the sections that rely on publicly available records provided by the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services.</p>

<p>New to this project is data on health care providers who have been kicked out of government health programs. For the first time, you&#8217;ll be able to see your provider&#8217;s standing.</p>

<p><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/">Vital Signs</a> can also send you email notifications every time we update the data or if we spot something new or something important changes for your provider. It&#8217;s designed for mobile devices, so you can easily pull up this information while at your doctor&#8217;s office or in other care settings.</p>

<p>The data in Vital Signs is also a jumping off point for you to dive in further based on what you&#8217;re interested in. Each section corresponds to a much deeper and more detailed set of data on that provider. You&#8217;ll see links under the &#8220;Dig Deeper&#8221; subheading that will let you see everything we know about that subject for that provider.</p>

<p>The data across all of our health care databases is updated throughout the year &#8212; as often as monthly but more often once or twice per year. You can subscribe to alerts in <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/">Vital Signs</a> and we&#8217;ll email you whenever we update your doctor&#8217;s record. If something critical changes about your provider &#8212; for instance, if he or she has been banned from participating in federal programs like Medicare or Medicaid &#8212; we&#8217;ll email you as soon as the data reflects that.</p>

<p>One last thing: If you use health care data professionally, the data in Vital Signs is available via API. You can use the API to match what we know about providers with other information, as long as you know their NPI numbers. (Read more about the API <a href="https://www.propublica.org/nerds/item/introducing-the-vital-signs-api">on the ProPublica Nerd Blog</a>.) For now, the API is only available to a limited number of applicants, but we&#8217;ll be welcoming more users in the month ahead. You can read the documentation and sign up to join the waitlist on the <a href="https://www.propublica.org/datastore/api/vital-signs-api">Data Store website</a>.</p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5486274.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-10T11:04:13-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vital Signs</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5486275</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://projects.propublica.org/vital-signs/#28690</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/sisi_wei/">Sisi Wei</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>Know more about your doctor.
</p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5486275.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-10T11:03:05-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fact-Checking Elected Officials on the Affordable Care Act Repeal</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5484031</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/fact-checking-elected-officials-on-the-affordable-care-act-repeal/#28689</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/charles_ornstein/">Charles Ornstein</a>
    
</p>
            <p class="note copublish-note"><p>This story was co-published with Kaiser Health News, Stat and Vox.</p></p>                        <p>Dismayed by the results of the 2016 election, Meg Godfrey decided she needed to do more than vote, share social media posts and sign online petitions. So she went to the website of Sen. Roy Blunt, R-Mo., and typed a note in support of the Affordable Care Act.</p>

<p>&#8220;I asked him to use my tax dollars to provide health care to his constituents just like my tax dollars provide health care for him and his family,&#8221; she said she wrote.</p>

<p>A short while later, Godfrey received an <a href="http://www.propublica.org/documents/item/3486418-Sen-Blunt-Letter.html">email reply</a> from Blunt, essentially a form letter explaining why he supported the law&#8217;s repeal. &#8220;When President Obama signed this bill into law, he assured Americans that they would be able to keep their plans and doctors, while promising choice and affordability,&#8221; Blunt wrote. &#8220;Since the law has gone into effect, I have heard from countless Missourians who were unable to keep their insurance plans and/or providers.&#8221;</p>


<div class="callout">

<h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-us-fact-check-members-of-congress-on-the-affordable-care-act">Can you help us fact-check Congress on the ACA?</a></h2>
<p>Have you sent a letter in support, in opposition or asking questions about the ACA to your congressperson? Did you get a response? <a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-us-fact-check-members-of-congress-on-the-affordable-care-act">Share them with us</a>. </p>

</div>


<p>The email then gave a number of statistics to buttress Blunt&#8217;s position that the law is failing.</p>

<p>But something about the letter didn&#8217;t sit right with Godfrey, so she forwarded the email to ProPublica, asking us to fact-check it. Our assessment: The note was misleading and lacked important context.</p>

<p>That led ProPublica to wonder about the accuracy of responses sent to constituents by other members of the House and Senate on the Affordable Care Act and its future. Today, ProPublica is teaming with journalists at <a href="http://khn.org/">Kaiser Health News</a>, <a href="https://www.statnews.com/">Stat</a> and <a href="http://www.vox.com/">Vox</a> to gather those missives from our readers. On Monday, House Republican leaders unveiled their official proposal to repeal and replace the law. As the legislative debate begins in earnest, we plan to look at the representations made by elected officials from both parties and share what we find.</p>

<p>ProPublica asked Timothy Jost, an ACA expert and emeritus professor at Washington and Lee University School of Law, to review Blunt&#8217;s email. &#8220;Some of this information is inaccurate, the rest of it is spin,&#8221; he concluded.</p>

<p>A spokesman for Blunt provided citations for the data in the senator&#8217;s note but did not respond to a follow-up email.</p>

<p>Jost helped us break down Blunt&#8217;s message:</p>

<p><strong>Blunt&#8217;s email</strong>:</p>

<div id="DC-note-341799" class="DC-embed DC-embed-note DC-note-container"></div>
<script src="//assets.documentcloud.org/notes/loader.js"></script>
<script>
  dc.embed.loadNote('//www.documentcloud.org/documents/3486418-Sen-Blunt-Letter/annotations/341799.js');
</script>
<noscript>
  <p>&#8220;By the end of 2013, over 4.7 million Americans had their health care plans canceled.&#8221; <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3486418-Sen-Blunt-Letter/annotations/341799.html">View note</a></p>
</noscript>

<p><strong>Analysis</strong>: The 4.7 million figure came from an <a href="http://finance.yahoo.com/news/policy-notifications-current-status-state-204701399.html">Associated Press article</a> from December 2013, Blunt&#8217;s office said. Subsequent analyses, however, showed that the figure was overstated. Two researchers from the Urban Institute, <a href="http://healthaffairs.org/blog/2014/03/03/how-many-nongroup-policies-were-canceled-estimates-from-december-2013/">writing in the journal Health Affairs</a>, estimated that the number was closer to 2.6 million. Moreover, Jost notes, the Obama administration said states could allow insurers to leave transitional plans in place after Jan. 1, 2014. Missouri was one of the states that <a href="http://www.commonwealthfund.org/publications/blog/2014/jun/adoption-of-the-presidents-extended-fix">did so</a>. &#8220;So if a plan was cancelled in Missouri, it was the decision of the insurer, not a federal requirement,&#8221; Jost wrote.</p>

<p><strong>Blunt&#8217;s email</strong>: &#8220;This year, Missourians who purchase health insurance on the ObamaCare exchanges will see an average of a 25 percent increase on their premium.&#8221;</p>

<p><strong>Analysis</strong>: The average premium for a Missouri plan did indeed increase by 25 percent this year, according to <a href="http://acasignups.net/16/10/25/addendum-2017-average-rate-hike-project">ACAsignups.net</a>, a website that tracks the law and was cited by Blunt&#8217;s office. But that isn&#8217;t the entire story. First, the vast majority of marketplace enrollees in Missouri and nationwide receive hefty subsidies that reduce their cost.</p>

<p>Second, if you step out of the aggregate and look instead at a hypothetical person shopping for an affordable plan, the increase is lower. The Obama administration often compared monthly premiums for a 27-year-old in a benchmark plan (the plan upon which the government calculates subsidies). In Missouri, the premium actually decreased from $235 to $233 between 2014 and 2015. It increased 10 percent in 2016 and another 18 percent, to $305, for this year, according to the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.</p>

<p>But most enrollees aren&#8217;t paying the sticker price. Some 78 percent of Missouri marketplace consumers in 2016 could obtain coverage for $100 or less per month in 2017, after accounting for subsidies from the government, federal data shows.</p>

<p><strong>Blunt&#8217;s email</strong>: &#8220;In addition to increased costs, families in Missouri and across the nation have lost the ability to choose a plan that best suits their health care needs. Missourians in 97 of 114 counties and the city of St. Louis will only have one option on the exchange.&#8221;</p>

<div id="DC-note-341811" class="DC-embed DC-embed-note DC-note-container"></div>
<script src="//assets.documentcloud.org/notes/loader.js"></script>
<script>
  dc.embed.loadNote('//www.documentcloud.org/documents/3486418-Sen-Blunt-Letter/annotations/341811.js');
</script>
<noscript>
  <p>&#8220;In addition to increased costs, families in Missouri and across the nation have lost the ability to choose a plan that best suits their health care needs. Missourians in 97 of 114 counties and the city of St. Louis will only have one option on the exchange.&#8221; <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3486418-Sen-Blunt-Letter/annotations/341811.html">View note</a></p>
</noscript>

<p><strong>Analysis</strong>: Blunt is technically correct, but again the statistic lacks context, according to <a href="http://www.politifact.com/missouri/statements/2017/feb/22/roy-blunt/roy-blunt-leaves-out-context-missouris-health-insu/">Politifact Missouri</a>. &#8220;According to the U.S. Census Bureau, of Missouri&#8217;s roughly 6 million residents, about 63 percent live in the 17 counties and one city that will continue to have at least two provider choices,&#8221; the fact-checker wrote in February.</p>

<p><strong>What&#8217;s missing</strong>: Blunt&#8217;s email did not mention that more than 200,000 Missourians receive coverage through the Affordable Care Act exchanges. It also didn&#8217;t mention that health insurance premiums routinely increased by large amounts before the law took effect and that many Missourians with preexisting conditions effectively had no insurers to pick from, Jost said.</p>

<p>The number of people without insurance has gone down under the ACA, falling from 13 percent in 2013 to 9.8 percent in 2015, the most recent year for which <a href="https://www.census.gov/content/dam/Census/library/publications/2016/demo/p60-257.pdf">data is available, according to the U.S. Census Bureau.</a></p>

<p>Blunt spokesman Brian Hart declined to say how many people have written the senator about the ACA and what percentage of them were for or against the law.</p>


<div class="callout">

<h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/represent/statements/search?q=affordable+care+act">Congressional Statements on the Affordable Care Act</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/represent/statements/search?q=affordable+care+act">See our list</a> of press releases on the Affordable Care Act from members of the House of Representatives and the Senate.</p>

</div>


<p>Godfrey, who wrote to Blunt, is currently employed as a brand communications manager for a lighting manufacturer. She and her husband live in Northern California but are moving to St. Louis later this year. &#8220;I&#8217;m getting a head-start on my political activism in the state,&#8221; she wrote in an email to ProPublica. &#8220;We had planned to retire and get insurance on the exchange. Now we still plan to move but will, most likely, continue to work until we are eligible for Medicare.&#8221;</p>

<p>Godfrey, 62, said Blunt&#8217;s response to her was &#8220;infuriating.&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;I asked about what he was doing to take care of the people who elected him and he spouted misleading statistics,&#8221; she wrote. &#8220;I am surprised he didn&#8217;t bring up death panels [which do not exist]. I hate being treated like an idiot.&#8221;</p>

             <p class="note related-note"><p>Have you corresponded with a member of Congress or senator about the Affordable Care Act? We&#8217;d love to see the response you received. Please fill out <a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-us-fact-check-members-of-congress-on-the-affordable-care-act">our short form</a>.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5484031.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-10T05:00:40-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Your Member of Congress Telling It Straight On The ACA? Help Us Fact-Check Them.</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5483906</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-us-fact-check-members-of-congress-on-the-affordable-care-act/#28691</guid>
      <media:content url="http://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/get_involved_primary/20170309-aca-callout-300x200_1.jpg" medium="image"/>
      <media:description type="plain">President Donald Trump addresses Congress in February (Samuel Corum/Anadolu Agency/Getty Images)</media:description>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/terry_parris/">Terry Parris Jr.</a>
    
</p>
            <img src="/images/ngen/get_involved_primary/20170309-aca-callout-300x200_1.jpg" alt="President Donald Trump addresses Congress in February (Samuel Corum/Anadolu Agency/Getty Images)" />

            <p>We're looking for civically engaged people to help us fact-check what members of Congress are sending to their constituents. And we are particularly looking at how they respond when it comes to the Affordable Care Act and its future. So, ProPublica is teaming with journalists at <a href="http://khn.org/">Kaiser Health News</a>, <a href="https://www.statnews.com/">Stat</a> and <a href="http://www.vox.com/">Vox </a>to gather as many responses as possible.</p>

<p>We've already fact-checked one e-mail to a constituent from Missouri Sen. Roy Blunt. Our assessment: <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/fact-checking-elected-officials-on-the-affordable-care-act-repeal" target="_blank">The note was misleading and lacked important context</a>. We want to do more and that's where you come in.</p>

<p><strong>Have you sent a letter in support, in opposition or asking questions about the ACA to your senator or congressperson? Did you get a response? Share them with us.</strong></p>

<p>Below is a form that allows you to choose the elected representative or senator that you wrote a letter to. From there you can upload a document or copy and paste the text of the letter or email you sent, as well as the elected official's response.</p>

<p>If you have any questions about anything, please email <a href="mailto:acafactcheck@propublica.org">acafactcheck@propublica.org</a>.</p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5483906.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Health Care</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-10T04:59:03-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Senators to White House: How Will Kushner Avoid Overlap Between Business Empire and Government Work?</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5481893</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/senators-how-will-kushner-avoid-overlap-between-business-empire-government/#28693</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/justin_elliott/">Justin Elliott</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>Two senators and a congressman are pressing the White House to disclose exactly how Jared Kushner will comply with conflict of interest laws.</p>

<p>Sen. Elizabeth Warren, D-Mass., Sen. Tom Carper, D-Del., and Rep. Elijah Cummings, D-Md., sent a <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3513188-2017-03-08-Letter-on-Kushner-Recusals.html">letter</a> to the Trump administration Wednesday, prompted by our recent story that detailed how Kushner, a top aide to President Trump, is <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/white-house-power-player-jared-kushner-keeping-parts-of-real-estate-empire">keeping parts of his family real-estate empire</a>.</p>

<p>The White House has declined to detail how Kushner will comply with ethics laws that require government employees to avoid handling issues that could affect their pocketbooks.</p>

<p>Many people entering government comply with the law by simply <a href="https://www.oge.gov/web/oge.nsf/Financial%20Conflicts%20of%20Interest/34F1CF2FAF392D7D85257E96006364EB?opendocument">divesting their assets</a>. Kushner has divested some, but not all, of his business. The White House declined to tell us what holdings Kushner is keeping and what he has given up.</p>

<p>Government employees who hold on to assets must recuse themselves from areas in which they have a conflict. The White House hasn&#8217;t detailed specific areas in which Kushner will recuse himself.</p>

<p>The Democrats&#8217; letter is addressed to <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/01/25/president-donald-j-trump-announces-white-house-compliance-team">Stefan Passantino</a>, a White House lawyer charged with handling ethics issues. The letter asks for a response by March 14.</p>

<p>Asked about the letter, White House spokeswoman Hope Hicks declined to tell ProPublica whether the administration plans to respond.</p>

<p>Hicks said in a statement:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Mr. Kushner is fully complying with the ethics rules, removing himself from active participation in his prior businesses, divesting of substantial assets and recusing himself where appropriate in light of interests that he is not divesting.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>The Democrats&#8217; letter asks the White House to provide details on Kushner&#8217;s financial holdings, how Kushner will recuse himself from issues that could affect his businesses, and whether Kushner has recused himself from anything so far.</p>

<p>Kushner is required to release a financial disclosure form that should give a fuller picture of what assets he has kept. It should be made public in the coming weeks or months.</p>

<p>Also this week, Sen. Jon Tester, D-Mont., <a href="https://www.tester.senate.gov/?p=press_release&amp;id=5094">pressed</a> the White House to continue the Obama-era practice of publishing an annual report on ethics compliance, including details of who was given a waiver from ethics rules.</p>

<p>Tester&#8217;s letter to Trump, sent Tuesday, was prompted <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-the-trump-administration-may-be-skirting-its-own-ethics-rules">by our story</a> describing the hiring of three former lobbyists to work on the White House National Economic Council. The former lobbyists appear to be working on issues on which they previously lobbied, a practice that is supposed to be barred by Trump&#8217;s January executive order on ethics.</p>

             <p class="note related-note"><p>Do you have information about Jared Kushner&#8217;s businesses or other Trump administration ethics issues? Contact me at <a href="mailto:justin@propublica.org">justin@propublica.org</a> or via Signal at 774-826-6240.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5481893.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-09T17:36:29-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Hospitals Waste</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5479644</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/what-hospitals-waste#28687</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/marshall_allen/">Marshall Allen</a>
    
</p>
                                    <!-- START EXPRESSIONENGINE BODY CONTENT -->

  <script src="//connect.facebook.net/en_US/all.js"></script>
    <div id="fb-root"></div>
    <script>
      FB.init({
        appId      : '229862657130557', // App ID
        status     : true, // check login status
        cookie     : true, // enable cookies to allow the server to access the session
        xfbml      : true  // parse XFBML
      });
    </script>

<!-- we can't edit body tag, so use custom bodyclass value in YAML if needed -->
<div id="page-body" class="default">


<header role="banner">
    <h1><a href="https://www.propublica.org">ProPublica</a></h1>
    
<nav>
<ul class="social-links">
<li class="facebook social-widget ss-fb" data-title="What Hospitals Waste" data-img="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_og_image/20170309-what-hospitals-waste-1200x630.jpg" data-txt="The nation&#8217;s health care tab is sky-high. We&#8217;re tracking down the reasons. First stop: A look at all the perfectly good stuff hospitals throw away." data-desc="The nation&#8217;s health care tab is sky-high. We&#8217;re tracking down the reasons. First stop: A look at all the perfectly good stuff hospitals throw away." data-url="https://www.propublica.org/article/what-hospitals-waste/" data-hashtag=""><a href="#">Share on Facebook</a></li>
<li class="twitter social-widget ss-tw" data-txt="What Hospitals Waste" data-url="https://www.propublica.org/article/what-hospitals-waste/" data-hashtag=""><a href="#">Share on Twitter</a></li>
<li class="comment"><a href="#disqus_thread">Comment</a></li>
</ul>
<ul class="donate-links">
<li class="tab"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/site/donate3/">Donate</a></li>
</ul>
</nav>
</header><!-- end header[role="banner"] -->


<main role="main">
<div id="article-top"></div>
<article>

    <header>
<figure>
<div class="lede-img-wrapper">
<span data-picture data-alt >
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/lead-art-warehouse-480*320-1dc9b4.jpg"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/lead-art-warehouse-960*640-1dc9b4.jpg" data-media="(-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/lead-art-warehouse-800*534-1dc9b4.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 30em)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/lead-art-warehouse-1600*1067-1dc9b4.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 30em) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-width: 30em) and (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/lead-art-warehouse-1200*800-1dc9b4.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/lead-art-warehouse-2400*1601-1dc9b4.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-width: 37.5em) and (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<noscript>
<img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/lead-art-warehouse-480*320-1dc9b4.jpg" alt="">
</noscript>
</span>

</div>
<figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>
<div class="title-set">
<div class="titles">

<h1>What Hospitals Waste</h1>
<!-- <h2>The nation&#8217;s health care tab is sky-high. We&#8217;re tracking down the reasons. First stop: A look at all the perfectly good stuff hospitals throw away.</h2> -->
<h2 class="dek">The nation&#8217;s health care tab is sky-high. We&#8217;re tracking down the reasons. First stop: A look at all the perfectly good stuff hospitals throw away.</h2>
<span class="byline">by Marshall Allen, ProPublica</br>
Photos by Tristan Spinski, special to ProPublica</span>
<time class="dateline">March  9, 2017</time>

</div><!-- end .titles -->
</div><!-- end .title-set -->
</header><!-- end article header -->

<div class="wrapper">
<div class="content">
<p class="opening"><span class="lead-in"><span class="dropcap">J</span>ust outside Portland, Maine,</span> there&#8217;s a 15,000-square-foot warehouse that&#8217;s packed with reasons the U.S. health care system costs so much: Shelves climb floor to ceiling, stacked with tubs overflowing with unopened packages of syringes, diabetes supplies and shiny surgical instruments that run hundreds of dollars apiece. There are boxes of IV fluids and bags of ostomy supplies and kits with everything you&#8217;d need to perform an obstetrics surgery.</p>


<aside class="promotion series-promotion">
  <div class="group">
    <a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-propublica-investigate-wasted-health-care-dollars"><span data-picture="" data-alt="">
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/healthcare-waste-300-360*240-837f19.jpg"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/healthcare-waste-300-720*480-837f19.jpg" data-media="(-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<noscript>
<img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/healthcare-waste-300-360*240-837f19.jpg" alt="" />
</noscript>
</span>
</a>
    <h3>Help Us Investigate Wasted Health Care Dollars</h3>
    <p>Experts say the United States might be squandering a quarter of the money spent on health care. That&#8217;s an estimated $765 billion a year. Do you believe you&#8217;ve encountered this waste? <a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-propublica-investigate-wasted-health-care-dollars">Tell us here.</a></p>
  </div>
  <div class="group">
    <h3>Email Updates</h3>
    <p>Sign up to get ProPublica&#8217;s major investigations delivered to your inbox.</p>
    
<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="//propublica.us6.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=ff2018a8e2&amp;id=f74e196955" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate="">
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll">
<div class="mc-field-group">
<label for="mce-EMAIL">Sign up to get ProPublica&#8217;s investigations delivered to your inbox.</label>
<input placeholder="you@example.com" type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL" />
</div>

<!-- UPDATE THIS FOR EACH INVESTIGATION -->
<!--
<div class="mc-field-group hidden">
<input checked type="checkbox" value="16" name="group[15237][16]" id="mce-group[15237]-15237-4">
<label for="mce-group[15237]-15237-4">Advoserve</label>
</div>
-->

<!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;" aria-hidden="true">
<input type="text" name="b_ff2018a8e2_f74e196955" tabindex="-1" value="" />
</div>
<input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button" />
<div id="mce-responses">
<div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
<div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
</div>
  </div>
</form>
</div>
<script src="//s3.amazonaws.com/downloads.mailchimp.com/js/mc-validate.js"></script>
<script>(function($) {window.fnames = new Array(); window.ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';fnames[3]='TWITTER';ftypes[3]='text';}(jQuery));var $mcj = jQuery.noConflict(true);</script>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->

  </div>
</aside>


<p>This, however, isn&#8217;t a story of about the crippling price of medical supplies. This is about the high cost of medical supplies <em>that hospitals throw away.</em></p>

<p>On a recent snowy day the warehouse&#8217;s 65-year-old proprietor, Elizabeth McLellan, gave an indignant accounting: She yanked a urinary catheter out of one bin. It&#8217;s unopened and has an expiration date of July 2018. &#8220;There&#8217;s no reason to get rid of this.&#8221; A box of 30 new feeding bags has an August 2019 expiration date. The same type sells on Amazon.com for $129.</p>

<p>That surgical stapler? It&#8217;s unopened. The same model sells online for $189. And McLellan simply shook her head over a set of a dozen long thin laparoscopic surgery instruments that some hospital discarded. Similar used tools can go for hundreds of dollars.</p>

<p>&#8220;There&#8217;s nothing wrong with these, nothing wrong with any of these,&#8221; she said.</p>

<p>Ten years ago, McLellan, a registered nurse, shocked to see what hospitals were tossing out, began asking them to give her their castoffs instead. In 2009 she launched Partners for World Health, a nonprofit that now has four warehouses throughout Maine. Today, she and hundreds of volunteers collect medical equipment and supplies from a network of hospitals and medical clinics, sort them and eventually ship containers full of them to countries like Greece, Syria and Uganda.</p>

<p>&#8220;This is money.&#8221; McLellan said, extending her arm to the vast array of supplies. &#8220;This is one of the reasons why your health insurance is so expensive.&#8221;</p>

<p>The vexing riddle of how to make health care more affordable has seldom been more front and center on the national stage. President Trump and Republican lawmakers are wrestling with the future of the Affordable Care Act, which has helped millions of people obtain health insurance. But most Americans would rather their legislators focus on bringing down health care costs, according to a recent survey by the Kaiser Family Foundation. Two-thirds of those surveyed said reducing such costs should be the &#8220;top&#8221; health care priority for Trump and the Republican-led Congress.</p>


<figure class="inset left">
    <span data-picture="" data-alt="">
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/elizabeth-mclellan-480*720-a579df.jpg"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/elizabeth-mclellan-960*1439-a579df.jpg" data-media="(-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/elizabeth-mclellan-900*1349-a579df.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/elizabeth-mclellan-1800*2699-a579df.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-width: 37.5em) and (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<noscript>
<img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/elizabeth-mclellan-480*720-a579df.jpg" alt="" />
</noscript>
</span>

    <figcaption>Elizabeth McLellan started Partners for World Health when she worked as a nurse administrator and saw her hospital tossing out useful supplies.</figcaption>
</figure>


<p>Talk to experts and many agree that waste would be a good place to start. In 2012 the National Academy of Medicine estimated the U.S. health care system squandered $765 billion a year, more than the entire budget of the Defense Department. Dr. Mark Smith, who chaired the committee that authored the report, said the waste is &#8220;crowding out&#8221; spending on critical infrastructure needs, like better roads and public transportation. The annual waste, the report estimated, could have paid for the insurance coverage of 150 million American workers &#8212; both the employer and employee contributions.</p>

<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s unconscionable that we&#8217;re not only wasting money in health care but in doing so are sacrificing other important social needs,&#8221; Smith said.</p>

<p>Smith&#8217;s committee blames the obvious villains &#8212; overtreatment, excess administrative costs and high prices &#8212; for most of the fat in the system. Left untallied, however, are the discards that arrive in waves into McLellan&#8217;s warehouses, most of which would otherwise end up in landfills. McLellan estimates the goods her group has right now are worth $20 million. Sure, that&#8217;s a rounding error in the overall waste tab, but it starts being real money if you add up the discards of all the nation&#8217;s medical facilities.</p>

<p>Researchers at the University of California, San Francisco Medical Center, for instance, recently estimated that in a single year the hospital wasted $2.9 million in neurosurgery supplies alone. Nearly $3 million. On wasted supplies. In one department.</p>

<p>Last year Partners sent seven containers overseas, each weighing up to 15,000 pounds and with an estimated value of up to $250,000. One is being sent to Syria this week. It includes an ultrasound machine ($25,000), a dozen trocars ($4,400) and an infant warmer ($3,995).</p>

<p>MedShare, a Georgia-based nonprofit more than 10 times the size of Partners, sent 156 containers of discarded medical supplies to developing countries last year, each one worth as much as $175,000. As lawmakers debate, ProPublica is setting off to document the rarely examined &#8212; and mind-boggling &#8212; ways your health care dollars are frittered away. Our first stop: the world of &#8220;medical surplus.&#8221;</p>


    <div class="nine-up product">
        <h3>A Catalog of Waste</h3>
        <p>The items below were photographed in a Partners for World Health warehouse outside Portland, Maine. It&#8217;s not possible to provide an exact value for each item because health care facilities obtain them through a variety of purchasing arrangements, at varying prices. Some of the items are used, so the value is estimated. ProPublica found the same or similar items online to give an idea of their approximate value.</p>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-10.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>Assorted Surgical Instruments</dt>
                    <dd class="price">$5 and up, approximately</dd>
                    <dd class="description">Grasp objects during a procedure</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-08.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>3M Healthcare Particulate Respirator and Surgical Mask</dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="http://www.bettymills.com/particulate-respirator-/-surgical-mask-cone-headband-(1860)-1860?referer=search">$1.31</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Prevents a health care provider and patient from contaminating each other</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-11.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>OneTouch Verio Glucose Monitors</dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Onetouch-Verio-Glucose-Monitoring-System/dp/B00W0M4AYS">$16.99 each, new</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Measure a patient&#8217;s blood sugar levels</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-07.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>Bard All-Purpose Urethral Catheters <span class="nobreak">(Exp: 7/2019)</span></dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="http://www.garnersupply.com/bard-home-health-div-bard-red-rubber-all-purpose-urethral-catheter-16-fr-16-part-no-9416-57-qty-1-each.html?utm_source=google&amp;utm_medium=cpc&amp;utm_campaign=google&amp;gclid=CJTUmKbKwtICFViBswodT2ALKA">$1.33 each</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Evacuate urine from the bladder</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-15.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>Portex Disposable Inner Cannulas <span class="nobreak">(Exp: 03/21/2021)</span></dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="http://www.medonthego.com/Box-of-Portex-Inner-Cannulas-Trach-Tube-526060-50-mm-Orange-Box20_p_128498.html">About $3 each</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Inserted into a patient&#8217;s tracheotomy tube to guide a catheter into position</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-14.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>AirFlow Manual Resuscitator/Ventilator</dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="https://www.tri-anim.com/adult-airflow-manual-resuscitators-bvm-group-27882-3763.aspx?search=87-AF1000MBN-20">About $26</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Controls breathing in a patient who is having respiratory trouble</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-13.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>Covidien HET Bipolar Forceps</dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="https://www.esutures.com/product/0-in-date/30-covidien-autosuture/336-electrosurgery/46254835-covidien-het-bipolar-forceps-180-1022/">About $299</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Used as part of a system to provide treatment for hemorrhoids</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-16.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>Stryker Formula Egg Bur <span class="nobreak">(Exp: 3/2016)</span></dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="http://www.ebay.com/itm/Stryker-Formula-Egg-Bur-5-5mm-Ref-0375-952-000-Exp-2019-2020-9pcs-/201620971354?hash=item2ef18bdf5a:g:KNMAAOSwyKxXgr0F">$249</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Used for cutting during surgery</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-17.png" />
            <figcaption>
                <dl>
                    <dt>Miltex Hegar Uterine Dilators</dt>
                    <dd class="price"><a href="http://www.medicalresources.com/shopping/proddisplay.asp?catalogid=2249">$40 each, new</a></dd>
                    <dd class="description">Enlarge the opening of the uterus</dd>
                </dl>
            </figcaption>
        </figure>
    </div>


<hr />

<p><span class="lead-in"><span class="dropcap">T</span>here&#8217;s a display case</span> in the Partners headquarters that sums up the heedless wealth of American health care. On one side are medical supplies McLellan brought home from Bangladesh: a yellowed plastic respirator mask, dirty tubing and a bloodstained square of gauze that&#8217;s brown and stiff from being washed and reused over and over again. Above them a sign reads, &#8220;Shared By Thousands.&#8221; On the other side are the same items, sterile and new, the discards of local health care facilities in the U.S.</p>

<p>McLellan once worked as a nurse in Saudi Arabia and her wardrobe reflects her extensive travels in the developing world: velveteen pants from China, a chunky sea rock necklace from Senegal and bangles from Ethiopia. Places that welcome our medical largesse.</p>

<p>At the back of her office, she pushed through a set of swinging double doors that led to her disposable medical supplies warehouse, a room the size of a gymnasium, with 20-foot ceilings and glassy concrete floors.</p>

<p>Donations from throughout Maine, Vermont and Massachusetts come in through a loading dock at the back. McLellan calls it &#8220;golden trash&#8221; and it generally falls into a handful of categories: equipment discarded for upgraded models, supplies tossed after a hospital changed vendors, or materials donated by the families of patients who have died. Other items are past their expiration dates or were swept out by strict infection control procedures, but remain safely usable.</p>

<p>McLellan grabs a bag from a haphazard, 10-foot mound of boxes and bulging sacks waiting to be sorted. Its contents, she says, came from a single room in a hospital&#8217;s intensive care unit. She dumps the bag out onto a table like a kid pouring out a pillowcase full of Halloween candy. The stuff rains down into a pile that&#8217;s three square feet: Handfuls of unopened and unexpired sterile needles, two dozen sterile syringes, packets of alcohol and antiseptic pads, IV tubing; a roll of tape that&#8217;s never been used, a bag of IV solution that expires in September 2018, 14 saline flushes that expire in 2019, an unopened package of suction catheters and a pulse oximeter adapter.</p>


<div class="ad ad-250x300">
  <div id="google-Rt_Sdbr_Non-Mobile-Only300x250">
    <script>googletag.display('google-Rt_Sdbr_Non-Mobile-Only300x250');</script>
  </div>
</div>


<p>&#8220;This is normal,&#8221; she said. &#8220;This is every hospital.&#8221;</p>

<p>McLellan started her nonprofit after watching patient rooms being cleaned out at Maine Medical Center, where she was a nurse administrator. When patients were discharged, hospital staff threw out everything, including unopened supplies. McLellan got permission from the hospital&#8217;s CEO to put out bins to save the discarded items.</p>

<p>A year and a half later, she&#8217;d gathered more than 11,000 pounds of supplies and equipment in her house. Today, Partners has three paid employees &#8212; McLellan is a volunteer &#8212; and an annual budget of $357,000, most of it from individual donations. Hundreds of volunteers pitch in. Similar nonprofits have sprung up around the country.</p>

<p>On a recent afternoon, Donald Madison, 47, Paul Farren, 69, and William Silveira, 85, picked up a used anesthesia machine, an exam table and other items at a Maine Medical Center storage facility and brought them to a different Partners&#8217; warehouse stuffed with medical hardware: a sea of new-looking wheelchairs, a shiny mountain of walkers and canes and neat rows of IV pumps. The biomedical equipment room has ultrasound machines, anesthesia machines, laparoscopic surgery towers and more. Biomedical engineers check out each piece before it is sent on to a country in need.</p>

<!-- 
<figure class="medium">
    <span data-picture data-alt >
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/grid-two-480*718-7ef7fe.jpg"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/grid-two-960*1436-7ef7fe.jpg" data-media="(-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/grid-two-900*1347-7ef7fe.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/grid-two-1800*2693-7ef7fe.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-width: 37.5em) and (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<noscript>
<img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/grid-two-480*718-7ef7fe.jpg" alt="">
</noscript>
</span>

    <figcaption>TKTKTKTKTK TKTKTKTKTK TKTKTKTKTK TKTKTKTKTK TKTKTKTKTK TKTKTKTKTK <span class="credit">(TKTKTKTKTK)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
 -->

<p>Madison, a supervisor at a retail pharmacy, said it&#8217;s easy to get disgusted by the waves of wasted medical goods pouring through the warehouse. He grabbed a $30 walker from the pile. &#8220;We&#8217;ll get 400 more of them this year,&#8221; he said. &#8220;Why do we need everyone on Medicare to get a new walker?&#8221;</p>


<figure class="inset left product">
    <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-02.png" />
    <figcaption>
        <dl>
            <dt>Ethicon Monocryl Undyed Sutures (Exp: 7/2019)</dt>
            <dd class="price"><a href="http://www.hospeq.com/Ethicon-Y266H-MONOCRYL-Suture-CP-1-Size-2-0-p/ety266h.htm">$261</a></dd>
            <dd class="description">Used for tying and sewing during surgery</dd>
        </dl>
    </figcaption>
</figure>


<p>And those pallets of adult diapers stacked high on a shelf? He sells the same type at his pharmacy for $11.99 per package or more. Farren recalled one time they picked up about 100 unopened packages of diapers from the home of a patient who had died. &#8220;It was ridiculous,&#8221; he said.</p>

<p>McLellan is sensitive about the built-in tension of her mission. The hospitals are casting off useful supplies that would otherwise be sent to a landfill. But they are also donating items that are desperately needed in the developing world. &#8220;They are trying to be good stewards in our community and in their world,&#8221; she said.</p>

<p>On the flip side, she can&#8217;t look past the waste. She said she could fill 15 shipping containers now if she had the $25,000 it cost to send each one overseas.</p>

<p>Hospital officials either declined to comment or, sometimes sheepishly, said some of the waste was unavoidable. Elton Cole, the supply chain manager at Stephens Memorial Hospital in western Maine, said some items, such as a torn exam table, must be replaced to meet infection control guidelines. Same goes for those supplies left in patient rooms. At Stephens, he said, the supplies in the room, such as bandages or gloves, are typically included in the room charge and not billed directly to patients.</p>

<p>Health care finance experts say while patients might not see the cost in their bills, the wasted supplies boost a hospital&#8217;s overhead, which in turn makes everyone&#8217;s costs higher.</p>

<p>The waste &#8220;contributes a lot to the cost of health care,&#8221; Cole said. &#8220;It&#8217;s pretty phenomenal the tons of product we&#8217;re shipping out to Elizabeth&#8217;s group.&#8221;</p>


<figure class="inset product">
    <img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/product-03.png" />
    <figcaption>
        <dl>
            <dt>Halyard Powder-Free Exam Gloves</dt>
            <dd class="price"><a href="https://www.zogomedical.com/exam-glove-lavender-nitrile-kc100?gclid=CPDO7q_xx9ICFceFswod_f0Nzw">$16.95, new</a></dd>
            <dd class="description">Protect the patient and the health care provider from contamination</dd>
        </dl>
    </figcaption>
</figure>


<p>Patricia Fallows, who organizes the University of Vermont Medical Center donations to Partners, sent ProPublica a list of the typical shipment. Among the 100 items are a Medline Skin Staple Remover ($100), a box of Carefusion Blood Sets ($100 for 10) and three cases of unexpired Ethicon sutures ($431 per box). (ProPublica is using the list price of the products online, since the prices hospitals and other medical facilities pay vary widely depending on their individual deals with suppliers.) Officials at the medical center said the waste is a tiny percentage of their budget and some of it is unavoidable.</p>

<p>We called the National Rural Health Association in Leawood, Kansas, to see if they could use anything on this list.</p>

<p>&#8220;Oh my gosh!&#8221; said Brock Slabach, the vice president for member services. &#8220;Some of the equipment I know folks would be interested in.&#8221;</p>

<p>Slabach said more than 600 rural hospitals are so strapped financially they risk closure and according to the data, some may be uncomfortably similar to facilities in Algeria and Bangladesh. Wealthier hospitals&#8217; waste could help them stay afloat.</p>

<p>&#8220;Every little bit helps,&#8221; he said. &#8220;None of these things will cure the entire problem altogether. But it would be helpful to meet a need in a community.&#8221;</p>

<p>Unfortunately, quantifying what&#8217;s being squandered is difficult. There is scant research, so it&#8217;s easy for hospitals to say it doesn&#8217;t add up to much.</p>

<p>Dr. Corinna Zygourakis, the chief neurosurgery resident at UCSF, who has studied operating room waste, said hospitals may not like what they&#8217;d find. &#8220;It&#8217;s not nice to say, &#8216;Hey, look at the amount of money we&#8217;re wasting.&#8221;</p>

<p>She decided to study waste after a medical mission trip to Mexico in 2015. At UCSF it was common to set out an array of disposable surgical instruments in the sterile field of the operating room just in case a surgeon needed them. Often the surgeon wouldn&#8217;t even touch the instruments, but they, nevertheless, had to be discarded. In Mexico, they wouldn&#8217;t have been.</p>

<p>Zygourakis and a team of colleagues tracked 58 neurosurgeries at UCSF and tallied the unused supplies that were discarded. In 26 surgeries, all the blood clotting materials weren&#8217;t used, for a total of $3,749. In 16, an expensive tissue adhesive wasn&#8217;t used at a cost of $3,495. Screws were wasted on three cases, totaling $3,144. The items marked as wasted were not billed to patients, and were donated whenever possible, she said.</p>


<figure class="medium">
    <span data-picture="" data-alt="">
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/office-map-480*320-bc03d6.jpg"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/office-map-960*640-bc03d6.jpg" data-media="(-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/office-map-900*600-bc03d6.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em)"></span>
<span data-src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/office-map-1800*1201-bc03d6.jpg" data-media="(min-width: 37.5em) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.3), (min-width: 37.5em) and (min-resolution: 124.8dpi)"></span>
<noscript>
<img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/generated/office-map-480*320-bc03d6.jpg" alt="" />
</noscript>
</span>

    <figcaption>Partners for World Health ships America&#8217;s unwanted medical equipment and supplies to needy countries like Greece, Syria and Uganda.</figcaption>
</figure>


<p>But the study&#8217;s findings, published in Journal of Neurosurgery in 2016, were eye-opening: The public hospital wasted an estimated $968 per neurosurgery case, which amounted to about $2.9 million over the course of a year.</p>

<p>UCSF reviewed all the preference cards for each surgeon, which specify how the operating room should be set up before each operation. The hospital now makes sure the set-up doesn&#8217;t include supplies that aren&#8217;t actually needed, preventing a significant amount of the waste.</p>

<p>In a separate study in the December edition of JAMA Surgery, Zygourakis and her colleagues showed each UCSF surgeon his or her direct costs per procedure in comparison to other surgeons in the institution. Most doctors were unaware of operating-room costs. Then they gave them an incentive: Their departments would get a bonus if they reduced costs by at least 5 percent.</p>

<p>The median surgical supply costs dropped by 6.5 percent in the group of surgeons who participated &#8212; a savings of about $836,000 over one year &#8212; while the control group&#8217;s costs increased by almost 7.5 percent.</p>

<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s really important to make people aware of this,&#8221; Zygourakis said. &#8220;The younger generation of physicians and surgeons do care about these things. We do realize we have limited resources and want to see how we can provide the most and best care to the most number of patients.&#8221;</p>

<p>Back in Maine, McLellan said she would love for the medical community to put her out of business by cutting the waste and passing the savings on to patients. She&#8217;s invited hospital CEOs to visit her warehouses, to see the vast display of wasted health care dollars. So far none have come.</p>

<p>&#8220;I want to go talk to Trump,&#8221; McLellan said. &#8220;Trump wants to figure out how to do this business in a different way, how to be more cost effective. I&#8217;m sure he doesn&#8217;t understand what the waste is. Not this kind of waste. People don&#8217;t get it until they see how much is wasted.&#8221;</p>


<hr />

<div class="author-bio">
  <a href="https://www.propublica.org/site/author/marshall_allen"><img src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/images/marshall-allen-bio-200x200.jpg" alt="Author photo" /></a>
  <p><a href="https://www.propublica.org/site/author/marshall_allen">Marshall Allen</a> is a ProPublica reporter covering health care and patient safety issues.</p>
</div>

<div class="author-bio">
  <p>Design and production by Jillian Kumagai and Rob Weychert.</p>
</div>

<hr />


</div><!-- end .content -->
</div><!-- end .wrapper -->

<footer>
<div id="article-bottom"></div>

<!-- Begin MailChimp Signup Form -->
<div id="mc_embed_signup">
<form action="//propublica.us6.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=ff2018a8e2&amp;id=f74e196955" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
<div id="mc_embed_signup_scroll">
<div class="mc-field-group">
<label for="mce-EMAIL">Sign up to get ProPublica&#8217;s investigations delivered to your inbox.</label>
<input placeholder="you@example.com" type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email" id="mce-EMAIL">
</div>

<!-- UPDATE THIS FOR EACH INVESTIGATION -->
<!--
<div class="mc-field-group hidden">
<input checked type="checkbox" value="16" name="group[15237][16]" id="mce-group[15237]-15237-4">
<label for="mce-group[15237]-15237-4">Advoserve</label>
</div>
-->

<!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
    <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;" aria-hidden="true">
<input type="text" name="b_ff2018a8e2_f74e196955" tabindex="-1" value="">
</div>
<input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button">
<div id="mce-responses">
<div class="response" id="mce-error-response" style="display:none"></div>
<div class="response" id="mce-success-response" style="display:none"></div>
</div>
  </div>
</form>
</div>
<script src='//s3.amazonaws.com/downloads.mailchimp.com/js/mc-validate.js'></script>
<script>(function($) {window.fnames = new Array(); window.ftypes = new Array();fnames[0]='EMAIL';ftypes[0]='email';fnames[3]='TWITTER';ftypes[3]='text';}(jQuery));var $mcj = jQuery.noConflict(true);</script>
<!--End mc_embed_signup-->


    <section id="comments">
<div id="disqus_thread"></div>
<script>
var disqus_shortname = 'propublica';
var disqus_url = 'https://www.propublica.org/article/what-hospitals-waste/';
var disqus_title = 'What Hospitals Waste';
var disqus_identifier = '28687';

/* * * DON'T EDIT BELOW THIS LINE * * */
(function() {
var dsq = document.createElement('script'); dsq.type = 'text/javascript'; dsq.async = true;
dsq.src = '//' + disqus_shortname + '.disqus.com/embed.js';
(document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0] || document.getElementsByTagName('body')[0]).appendChild(dsq);
})();
</script>
<noscript>
<p>Please enable JavaScript to view the <a href="http://disqus.com/?ref_noscript">comments powered by Disqus.</a></p>
</noscript>
<p><a href="http://disqus.com" class="dsq-brlink">Comments powered by <span class="logo-disqus">Disqus</span></a></p>
</section><!-- end #comments -->


</footer>

</article>
</main><!-- end main[role="main"] -->

  <footer role="contentinfo">
  </footer><!-- end footer[role="contentinfo"] --> 

</div><!-- end #page-body -->

<!-- start footer scripts -->

<script src="https://static.propublica.org/projects/medical-waste/assets/js/main.js?2017030981416"></script>



<!-- end footer scripts -->

<!-- END EXPRESSIONENGINE BODY CONTENT -->                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5479644.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-09T08:00:50-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About $765 Billion Is Wasted Each Year on Health Care. Can You Help Us Find It?</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5479338</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-propublica-investigate-wasted-health-care-dollars/#28686</guid>
      <media:content url="http://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/get_involved_primary/healthcare-waste-300.jpg" medium="image"/>
      <media:description type="plain">Tristan Spinski special to ProPublica</media:description>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/marshall_allen/">Marshall Allen</a>
    
</p>
            <img src="/images/ngen/get_involved_primary/healthcare-waste-300.jpg" alt="Tristan Spinski special to ProPublica" />

            <p>Experts say the United States might be squandering a quarter of the money spent on health care. That's an estimated $765 billion a year wasted on things like administrative red tape, high prices and overuse. We are all paying for this waste.</p>

<p>We want to find out where this money is going and we want your help. We are reaching out to people who work in health care and have seen money being blown in ways that could be stopped. We're not talking lost nickels and dimes here &#8212; we want the most outrageous and high-profile cases we can find. Will you please help ProPublica reporter Marshall Allen dig into the problem?</p>
            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5479338.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Health Care</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-09T08:00:45-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theres No Guarantee Trumps Tax Returns Would Reveal Russia Ties</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5479340</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/theres-no-guarantee-trumps-tax-returns-would-reveal-russia-ties/#28688</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">by Allan Sloan, ProPublica, </p>
            <p class="note copublish-note"><p>This story was co-published with <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/why-were-unlikely-to-find-any-russian-connection-in-trumps-tax-returns/2017/03/09/2a52f8c4-0366-11e7-b9fa-ed727b644a0b_story.html?utm_term=.05b70533f677">The Washington Post</a>.</p></p>                        <p>Every week seems to bring yet another revelation about possible relationships between Russia and people close to Donald Trump. Combine that with the fact that this is the height of tax preparation season, and you can see why lots of people seem obsessed with finding a supposed Russian connection in Trump&#8217;s tax returns.</p>

<p>Hence the increased demands for Trump to make his returns public the way presidents and presidential candidates have done since Richard Nixon, but that Trump has refused to do despite initially saying that he would.</p>

<p>However, even if Trump has business ties with Russian oligarchs or the Russian government &#8212; please note the &#8220;if&#8221; because there is nothing suggesting that is the case &#8212; it&#8217;s highly unlikely that evidence of that would show up in his personal tax returns. That&#8217;s the unanimous opinion of three respected tax experts I consulted, none of whom is an apologist for Trump.</p>

<p>A primary reason, they told me, is that Trump does business through hundreds of entities, including partnerships, corporations and LLCs (short for limited liability companies).</p>

<p>If you could read the relevant documents &#8212; IRS Forms 1040 and 8938 and Schedules C, E and S &#8212; you would see that unless Trump has a personal Russian bank account or shows a gain or a loss on the sale of a Russian security or property, financial results of Russian dealings (if they exist) would likely be lumped in with hundreds of other dealings rather than being broken out specifically.</p>

<p>In fact, searching for a Russian connection in Trump&#8217;s returns is a diversion from the real reasons the American public has a stake in seeing them.</p>

<p>We&#8217;ll get to those. But first, let&#8217;s see what the experts have to say.</p>

<p>&#8220;Tax forms don&#8217;t require much specificity,&#8221; said Steve Rosenthal, a senior fellow at the Urban-Brookings Tax Policy Center. Rosenthal, who has helped news organizations including The New York Times and The Washington Post parse Trump tax documents, says that, &#8220;You&#8217;re not going to see an entry that says, &#8216;Loan from Russian oligarch.&#8217;&#8230; Even if you borrowed money directly from the Russian government, you don&#8217;t have to say to whom you paid the interest.&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;Trump&#8217;s income is derived from the business entities &#8212; LLCs, corporations and partnerships &#8212; in which he owns interests,&#8221; says tax lawyer Bob Lord, an associate fellow with the Institute for Policy Studies who was an informal adviser on tax matters to Bernie Sanders&#8217;s campaign.</p>

<p>&#8220;It is possible, albeit unlikely, the tax returns of the business entities in which Trump owns an interest might reveal a relationship with Russia or a Russian oligarch,&#8221; Lord added. &#8220;Because Trump&#8217;s personal tax return will reflect only the income or loss flowing to Trump from those entities, his personal tax return would not be a reliable indicator of whether such a relationship exists.&#8221;</p>

<p>And now, to our third expert: Bob Willens of Robert Willens LLC, who for decades has helped journalists, including me, understand complex tax and accounting issues.</p>

<p>&#8220;I&#8217;m sure that whatever he&#8217;s done &#8212; if he&#8217;s done anything &#8212; is through LLCs. It would likely not show up on his returns,&#8221; Willens said. &#8220;Even if there aren&#8217;t any mentions of Russia on his return, it doesn&#8217;t mean that he doesn&#8217;t have relationships with Russia. Or that he does.&#8221;</p>

<p>If we are highly unlikely to find a Russian connection (should it exist, and again, there is no evidence that one does) in Trump&#8217;s tax returns, why do we have a stake in seeing them?</p>

<p>For the same reason it&#8217;s in our interest to see the tax returns of presidents, vice presidents and candidates for those offices: It&#8217;s important to see what kind of people they are, and to what extent they&#8217;re helping to pay for the country they&#8217;re running or want to run.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s especially important in Trump&#8217;s case, given how he and his family are imposing unprecedented costs on taxpayers for travel and security. The partial Trump tax returns that have surfaced show him paying no federal income tax in past years because of highly inventive and aggressive strategies. (Legal, yes, but shocking just the same.) And he may well not be paying significant federal income tax now.</p>

<p>During the campaign, Trump excoriated hedge-fund and private-equity managers who use the &#8220;carried interest&#8221; loophole to pay only the 23.8 percent capital gains rate on their share of their investors&#8217; long-term profits rather than the 39.6 percent they&#8217;d pay if carried interest were treated as an incentive fee.</p>


<div class="callout">

    <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/for-trumps-rich-appointees-death-may-be-certain-but-taxes-arent">For Trump&#8217;s Rich Appointees, Death May Be Certain But Taxes Aren&#8217;t</a></h2>
<a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/for-trumps-rich-appointees-death-may-be-certain-but-taxes-arent"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/2-170118-kushner-300x200.jpg" /></a>
<p>If Republicans succeed in repealing the estate tax, Rex Tillerson, Gary Cohn, Wilbur Ross, Jared Kushner, Steve Mnuchin, Betsy DeVos and their heirs may be able to defer capital gains taxes forever. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/for-trumps-rich-appointees-death-may-be-certain-but-taxes-arent">Read the story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>Given those attacks &#8212; and given the fact that Trump is proposing to enact major changes in our tax laws &#8212; it seems only right for us to know what Trump&#8217;s tax rate is. If anything.</p>

<p>Based on what the three experts told me and on my own experience, I think the likely reasons Trump won&#8217;t release his tax returns are that he may pay little or no income tax, may make few if any charitable contributions and his return might have entries that aren&#8217;t consistent with his claim to be worth more than $10 billion.</p>

<p>In addition, although his returns are unlikely to show a Russian connection, they may offer hints of how to dig out information that Trump doesn&#8217;t want us to see.</p>

<p>The risk of obsessing about a Russian connection is that if Trump&#8217;s tax returns should surface and Russia&#8217;s not in them, Trump will be able to say, &#8220;See? Russia is fake news, time to move on.&#8221;</p>

<p>So let&#8217;s remember that we should see Trump&#8217;s tax returns for the same reason we got to see Barack Obama&#8217;s or George W. Bush&#8217;s or Bill Clinton&#8217;s: They tell us a lot that it&#8217;s good for us to know about the person running our country.</p>

<p><em>Derek Kravitz contributed research to this report.</em></p>

             <p class="note related-note"><p>Do you have access to information about the Trump administration that should be public? Here&#8217;s how to <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-to-leak-to-propublica">send tips and documents</a> to ProPublica securely.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5479340.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Trump Administration</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-09T08:00:31-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In an Angry and Fearful Nation, an Outbreak of Anti-Semitism</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5475781</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/in-an-angry-and-fearful-nation-an-outbreak-of-anti-semitism/#28685</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/ac_thompson/" title="View A.C. Thompson's other articles">A.C. Thompson</a>


 and <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/ken_schwencke/" title="View Ken Schwencke's other articles">Ken Schwencke</a></p>
                                    <p>In late November, Marna Street, a violist with the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra, was walking to her car after a rehearsal. Street was shocked by what she discovered: Someone had painted a swastika, about 14 inches across, on the trunk of her car.</p>

<p>The vandals, Street said, had probably targeted her vehicle, which was parked in a garage not far from the University of Cincinnati, because she&#8217;d placed a magnet on it indicating that she is Jewish. Street eventually managed scrub off the graffiti. She put the magnet in the glovebox of her car.</p>

<p>&#8220;I had that feeling in the pit of my stomach, like somebody just punched me,&#8221; recalled Street, 68, speaking publicly for the first time. It was, she said, &#8220;a cross between fear and just plain hurt.&#8221;</p>

<p>Working with a coalition of organizations, ProPublica late last year launched &#8220;Documenting Hate,&#8221; an attempt to gather evidence of hate crimes and episodes of bigotry from a divided America. The account from Cincinnati is one of the anti-Semitic incidents the project has chronicled. But there are scores more.</p>

<p>Indeed, &#8220;Documenting Hate&#8221; recorded more than 330 reports of anti-Semitic incidents during a three-month span from early November to early February. The accounts &#8212; our list is by no means comprehensive &#8212; come via personal submissions, police documents and news articles. The majority, though not all, have been authenticated through either news reports, interviews or other evidence, like photos.</p>

<p>The incidents have taken place in big cities and small towns, along the country&#8217;s liberal coasts and in deep red states. Some of the episodes &#8212; swastikas and threatening messages spray-painted at schools and colleges around the nation &#8212; have been worrisome, though relatively minor. Others have been more serious, such as the 65 bomb threats targeting Jewish organizations across the country during the period we examined (<a href="http://projects.propublica.org/graphics/jcc-bomb-threats">there have been nearly 70 more since then</a>). In many cases, the culprits singled out specific individuals for abuse, defacing their homes and autos with swastikas and menacing comments.</p>


<div class="callout">

    <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/jcc-bomb-threats">Map: Bomb Threats to Jewish Community Centers and Organizations</a></h2>
<a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/jcc-bomb-threats"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170301-jcc-map-300x200.jpg" /></a>
<p>A timeline of bomb threats against Jewish Community Centers and other organizations <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/jcc-bomb-threats">See the graphic.</a></p>

</div>


<p>President Trump, after weeks of criticism for being slow to condemn the incidents, last week called them &#8220;horrible&#8221; and &#8220;painful&#8221; and &#8220;a very sad reminder of the work that still must be done to root out hate and prejudice and evil.&#8221;</p>

<p>The remarks, however, came after a number of confounding comments about the issue. During a Feb. 16 news conference, Trump castigated Jake Turx, a reporter for Ami, a Jewish magazine, for asking what the government was doing to address the increase in anti-Semitic events. Trump accused Turx of lying about the question he wanted to ask, and instructed him to sit down. And without citing any evidence, Trump has wondered whether some of the recent anti-Semitic incidents were carried out by liberals, or Jews themselves, intent on discrediting him.</p>

<p>&#8220;There&#8217;s a push on the left to conflate anti-Semitism with Trump, while at the same time criticizing him for having Jared Kushner, who wears his Jewishness as proudly as anyone, as his most trusted confidant and in the highest echelons of the White House staff,&#8221; said Joe Borelli, a Trump supporter who represents Staten Island on the New York city council, according to Breitbart News. &#8220;It is mind-boggling.&#8221;</p>

<p>The White House would not comment for the record when asked whether President Trump had in any way contributed to the threats and violence.</p>

<p>On a national level, data on hate crimes and bias incidents is spotty at best. The FBI admits the information it collects is incomplete &#8212; many police departments don&#8217;t participate in the hate crimes tracking program &#8212; and the bureau has yet to release statistics on 2016 and 2017. As a result, determining with authority whether anti-Semitic events are rising or declining is difficult. </p>

<p>There is little question, however, that the incidents have generated genuine concern. In a rare show of unity, all 100 U.S. senators this week issued a public letter urging the Department of Justice, FBI and Department of Homeland Security to protect Jewish institutions and prosecute those responsible for terrorizing them. In New York, Gov. Andrew Cuomo recently announced a $25 million grant to better protect day care and community centers from threats.</p>

<p>The available data does support the idea of an uptick. After years of decline, anti-Semitic crimes began trending upward in 2015, according to FBI data. Experts say that increase seems to have accelerated in recent months, as Trump&#8217;s unique brand of nativist populism has helped to pull more extreme right-wing groups, some of them avowedly racist, closer to the political mainstream. On Twitter, openly anti-Semitic figures have built vast networks of supporters and cultivated large audiences, while the Daily Stormer, a neo-Nazi website geared towards millennials, <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/in-an-ugly-election-result-hate-surges-online">has seen its traffic grow</a> to roughly a half a million unique visitors per month. In New York City, the police department said anti-Semitic hate crimes nearly doubled in the first two months of 2017 as compared to the same period last year.</p>

<p>&#8220;One of the constituencies Trump mobilized was the KKK-style anti-Semitic extreme right,&#8221; said Lawrence Rosenthal, a scholar of fascist history and director of the Center for Right-Wing Studies at the University of California, Berkeley. These groups &#8220;had been absolutely on the fringe of American politics for at least my lifetime &#8212; and I am getting old.&#8221;</p>

<p>Oren Segal, who tracks anti-Semitic incidents in his role as director of the Anti-Defamation League&#8217;s Center on Extremism, concurs. &#8220;The anti-Semites think they have a champion in the highest office,&#8221; said Segal, who believes that &#8220;divisive rhetoric&#8221; aired during last fall&#8217;s presidential campaign has emboldened racists and inspired them to strike out at their perceived enemies in the Jewish community.</p>

<p>&#8220;We have seen a significant uptick in the reports we&#8217;ve received, certainly starting around the election in November and continuing through the first two months of 2017,&#8221; Segal told ProPublica.</p>

<p>Amid the larger national debate about any responsibility Trump may bear for racist and anti-Semitic behavior, the accounts emerging from the &#8220;Documenting Hate&#8221; database offer a chance to appreciate the very personal experiences of violation and fear.</p>

<p>We identified:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Incidents at colleges and universities, like the man who wandered the <a href="http://www.gainesville.com/news/20170126/swastika-wearer-draws-uf-protests-has-hate-symbol-stolen">University of Florida&#8217;s campus in Gainesville wearing a swastika armband</a>.</p></li>

<li><p>Incidents at K-12 schools, including swastikas painted on almost any surface you could imagine &#8212; <a href="http://www.palmcoastobserver.com/photo-gallery/families-say-young-boys-hands-were-marked-swastikas-older-boy-imagine-school-bus">including students&#8217; hands</a>.</p></li>

<li><p>Incidents at government buildings, most of which were libraries, though one involved the words &#8220;Heil Hitler&#8221; and &#8220;Trump&#8221; <a href="http://www.nydailynews.com/new-york/brooklyn/cops-find-anti-semitic-graffiti-nyc-wastewater-plant-article-1.2905406">scrawled inside of a Brooklyn wastewater treatment plant</a>.</p></li>

<li><p>Incidents at private homes and businesses, including <a href="http://kval.com/news/local/several-swastika-signs-found-graffitied-around-whiteaker-neighborhood">swastika graffiti and propaganda</a> on businesses in Eugene, Oregon.</p></li>

<li><p>And incidents at public parks, mostly graffiti, though one enterprising vandal dug a <a href="https://www.longislandpress.com/2016/12/24/20-foot-swastika-dug-into-levittown-field-cops-say/">20-foot by 20-foot swastika into the grass</a> at a park in Levittown, New York.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>ProPublica&#8217;s review, which did not involve incidents occurring online, where anti-Semitic trolling and abuse have become widespread, uncovered many episodes which had never before been reported by the media or investigated by police.</p>

<p>Our tally is almost surely an undercount. It consists of incidents covered in media reports, as well as accounts gathered by the Southern Poverty Law Center and a coalition of news organizations including ProPublica, Univision News, Buzzfeed News and The New York Times Opinion section.</p>

<p>The reports we examined generally fall into two categories. Most appear to have been committed by angry individuals who aren&#8217;t affiliated with any organized group. They are often teens or adolescents who defame Jews &#8212; and other minority groups &#8212; through graffiti or verbal taunting. In some cases, the Nazi symbol was specifically aimed at non-Jews.</p>

<p>A smaller number were orchestrated by extremist political groups, such as the New Order, an outgrowth of the long-dormant American Nazi Party founded by George Lincoln Rockwell, and the Atomwaffen Division, a new, youthful fascist group. A handful of cases involved a saboteur who remotely hijacked computer printers at Stanford and other colleges, programming them to spit out page after page of neo-Nazi propaganda.</p>

<p>Some experts tracking this wave of incidents said it was crucial to situate them within a wider historical context.</p>

<p>&#8220;Generally, we&#8217;ve seen a remarkable decline in anti-Semitism over the past 40 years,&#8221; noted Jonathan Sarna, a history professor at Brandeis University and one of the foremost chroniclers of Jewish-American life. &#8220;In the 1950s, we didn&#8217;t just have bomb threats &#8212; we had bombings. Synagogues in the south were bombed.&#8221;</p>

<p>Sarna added: &#8220;It&#8217;s important to be vigilant and concerned. But it&#8217;s also important to not to overreact.&#8221;</p>

<p>Across the nation, Jews were directly harassed with hateful imagery and messages in dozens of instances we examined.</p>

<p>During Hanukkah last year, vandals desecrated a large home-made menorah that stood in the front yard of a home in Chandler, Arizona, <a href="http://www.azcentral.com/story/news/local/chandler-breaking/2016/12/30/vandals-turn-chandler-menorah-into-swastika/96011114/">twisting the sacred symbol into a swastika</a>. Days after the presidential election, New York State Sen. Brad Hoylman found <a href="http://nypost.com/2016/11/16/jewish-and-openly-gay-senator-finds-swastika-etched-outside-home/">a swastika carved into the elevator door</a> in his Manhattan apartment building and received a flyer in the mail saying that Jews would be &#8220;punished&#8221; for failing to convert to Christianity.</p>

<p>Not everyone who has encountered Nazi imagery is Jewish &#8212; gays, lesbians, African Americans and others have also been targeted.</p>

<p>Consider the story of Karen Schaeffer, who found a swastika and the word &#8220;SCUM&#8221; drawn on her front door in mid-November.</p>

<p>&#8220;I was pretty scared,&#8221; said Schaeffer, who lives in Wyandotte, Michigan, a small blue-collar town outside of Detroit. &#8220;I&#8217;m not even Jewish, but I am a pretty loud-mouthed liberal woman in a town that doesn&#8217;t always appreciate that.&#8221;</p>

<p>She has an idea about what drew the attention of the anti-Semites: a campaign sign in her window for Bernie Sanders, the Vermont senator who unsuccessfully ran against Hillary Clinton in the Democratic presidential primary.</p>

<p>Police came to Schaeffer&#8217;s house to investigate, but made no arrests.</p>

<p>In Cincinnati, Street, who is the principal violist emeritus with the symphony and a music teacher, said the graffiti on her car left her &#8220;feeling very vulnerable.&#8221; Her father and grandmother fled Nazi Germany for the safety of the U.S. in the 1940s.</p>

<p>Several weeks after Street&#8217;s car was defaced, schools in her city began getting hit with anti-Semitic graffiti.</p>

<p>First, someone <a href="http://www.wcpo.com/news/local-news/hamilton-county/cincinnati/clifton/hebrew-union-college-sign-vandalized-with-swastika">painted a large white swastika</a> on a sign at Cincinnati&#8217;s Hebrew Union College-Jewish Institute of Religion, the largest seminary for Reform Judaism in North America.</p>

<p>When the incident happened in early January, it was another psychic blow for Street. She worried about her friends who work at the college, and tried to understand the acts of ugliness taking place in her city. The crimes, she said, &#8220;are not huge, but compounded they are very frightening.&#8221;</p>

<p>Across the nation, similar graffiti appeared on the campuses of at more than 35 other colleges during the three months examined by ProPublica.</p>

<p>Late on the night of Jan. 21, a mask-wearing vandal equipped with a spray can <a href="http://www.wlwt.com/article/withrow-high-school-vandalized-with-swastikas-racial-slurs/8627606">defaced Withrow University High School</a>, a public school on Cincinnati&#8217;s east side, painting &#8220;Trump&#8221; and swastikas all over the campus. The vandal, who tagged signs, sidewalks and buildings, also painted anti-gay and anti-black slurs.</p>

<p>Dozens of other schools were also tagged with anti-Semitic graffiti during the same time period.</p>

<p>At a high school in Newton, Massachusetts, somebody wrote <a href="http://newton.wickedlocal.com/news/20170126/newton-police-investigated-more-than-two-dozen-hate-incidents-in-schools-in-2016">&#8220;Burn the Jews,&#8221; &#8220;white power,&#8221; and &#8220;Trump!!!&#8221;</a> on a bathroom stall. At Wilbur Cross High School in New Haven, Connecticut<a href="http://www.newhavenindependent.org/index.php/archives/entry/wilbur_cross_swastikas">, red swastikas were spray-painted</a> all over the athletic complex. In Murfreesboro, Tennessee, <a href="http://www.dnj.com/story/news/2017/02/08/blackman-high-expels-2-girls-swastika/97657830/">two teenage girls were expelled</a> from Blackman High School for drawing a swastika in a bathroom stall.</p>

<p>&#8220;Some people will say that the swastika vandalism is just being done by a bunch of kids and dismiss it as irrelevant. I think it&#8217;s the opposite. The fact that young kids are doing this is potentially the scariest part of it,&#8221; said Segal of the Anti-Defamation League.</p>

<p>On college campuses, much of the new anti-Semitism has been coming from organized groups of extremists out to intimidate or recruit new members.</p>

<p>At the University of Washington, in Seattle, a pro-Trump student group calling itself the &#8220;UW Wall Building Association&#8221; flirted with Nazism in a public Facebook post suggesting that undocumented immigrants should be sent to &#8220;concentration camps.&#8221;</p>

<p>Neo-Nazis also crisscrossed the university campus at night, pasting up stark black-and-white posters threatening violence and uploading videos of their exploits to YouTube. One poster, featuring the death&#8217;s head, or Totenkopf insignia, used by the SS during World War II, promised to &#8220;Drive out the sodomites and degenerates of Seattle.&#8221; Another poster encouraged students to &#8220;join your local Nazis&#8221; and visit the website IronMarch.com, a fascist web hang-out that encourages people to exterminate Jews and start a &#8220;race war now.&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;People are just shocked. We can&#8217;t believe this is happening,&#8221; said a graduate student who requested anonymity for fear of being harassed.</p>

<p>When the student saw the posters, she said she felt physically ill. &#8220;I called my mom and was sobbing. I was so upset. My ancestors were slaughtered by the Nazis,&#8221; said the student, who is Jewish.</p>

<p>The neo-fascist organization did not reply to a request for an interview about its activities.</p>


<div class="callout">

    <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/hatecrimes">Documenting Hate</a></h2>
<a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/hatecrimes"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170117-documenting-hate-300x200.jpg" /></a>
<p>Hate crimes and bias incidents are a national problem, but there&#8217;s no reliable data on their nature or prevalence. We&#8217;re collecting reports to create a national database for use by journalists and civil-rights organizations. <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/hatecrimes">See the project.</a></p>

 <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/i-cover-hate-i-didnt-expect-it-at-my-familys-jewish-cemetery">I Cover Hate. I Didn&#8217;t Expect It at My Family&#8217;s Jewish Cemetery.</a></h2>
    <p>The vandalizing of a Jewish graveyard in St. Louis becomes a very personal entry in our &#8220;Documenting Hate&#8221; database. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/i-cover-hate-i-didnt-expect-it-at-my-familys-jewish-cemetery">Read the story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>White nationalist groups including Identity Evropa, led by a California man convicted of attacking an Arab cab driver at gunpoint, and True Cascadia, which aims to promote &#8220;White ethnic consciousness in the Pacific Northwest,&#8221; are also propagandizing at the school.</p>

<p>Segal has tracked 112 instances of white supremacist groups posting flyers on college campuses since September 2016.</p>

<p>Over the past several months, synagogues and other Jewish institutions have come under sustained harassment.</p>

<p>In December, somebody repeatedly hurled rocks through the windows of Temple Menorah-Keneseth Chai, a historic synagogue in Philadelphia. On the opposite side of the country, in Las Vegas, a young man in jeans and a pull-over sweatshirt scratched a swastika into a black marble column during Shabbat services at Chabad of Southern Nevada.</p>

<p>In other states, Christian churches ministering to gays and lesbians or Latinos have also been tagged with swastikas.</p>

<p>But it is the array of <a href="http://projects.propublica.org/graphics/jcc-bomb-threats">bomb threats directed at Jewish community centers</a> that has captured the most media attention and generated the most concern. Federal authorities on March 3 charged Juan Thompson, an erratic former journalist who once wrote for the Intercept website, with making threats to a small number of JCCs as well as other Jewish institutions.</p>

<p>But the figures responsible for the scores of threats to other JCCs remain at large. On March 7, another 17 locations of Jewish institutions in the U.S. received bomb threats.</p>

<p>Some faith leaders are urging President Trump to issue a stronger public condemnation of anti-Semitism before the problem worsens. &#8220;We need him to say very forcefully, &#8216;This is not acceptable&#8217; &#8212; and to follow up with action,&#8221; said Rabbi Steven Fox, chief executive of the Central Conference of American Rabbis, the nation&#8217;s most prominent rabbinical body.</p>

<p>Fox said Jewish community leaders have requested a meeting with the White House to discuss the surge in anti-Semitic activity, but, so far, have not been granted an audience with Trump or his advisors.</p>

<p>Within his denomination, Reform Judaism, &#8220;there is great concern about this uptick in hate crimes, this increase in hate speech,&#8221; Fox told ProPublica. &#8220;In the last two years we&#8217;ve seen this real hatred for <em>anybody</em> that&#8217;s different &#8212; hatred for Muslims, hatred for the LGBTQ community. We see it as a deeply troubling trend, not just in America, but in the world.&#8221;</p>            <p class="note related-note"><p>Read more of our coverage in the <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/hatecrimes">Documenting Hate</a> project.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5475781.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-08T17:36:48-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trump Invites Bids to Build Wall, Cites Importance of Aesthetics</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5475157</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-invites-bids-to-build-wall-cites-importance-of-aesthetics/#28684</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/t_christian_miller/">T. Christian Miller</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>President Donald Trump built his campaign on the promise of a wall across the U.S.-Mexico border. Just a month after his inauguration, the Department of Homeland Security announced plans to begin construction.</p>

<p>And last Friday, the department took a step to make sure it will look good.</p>

<p>In a little-noticed <a href="https://www.fbo.gov/spg/DHS/USCS/FPSB/2017-JC-RT-0001/listing.html">update</a>, the department now says it wants a wall that will be &#8220;nominally 30 feet tall,&#8221; and, importantly, that bids will be judged on &#8220;aesthetics,&#8221; as well.</p>

<p>The new language, perhaps coincidental but likely not, appears to be a bureaucratic translation of Trump&#8217;s oft-repeated promise to build a &#8220;<a href="https://www.revealnews.org/article/how-trump-has-described-his-wall/">beautiful</a>&#8221; wall from <a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-37243269">30 to 55 feet</a> high.</p>

<p>Of course, the federal government does not typically focus on beauty in building its walls, fences and barriers. Procurement officers prefer to evaluate bids on concrete things such as price or a company&#8217;s past performance &#8212; or, for that matter, concrete itself. As a contract requirement, appearances usually only figure into high-end projects (think of the Vietnam Veterans Memorial).</p>

<p>But the Trump administration&#8217;s apparent demand for a wall with style is only one of the oddities that has arisen in planning for the massive project, estimated to cost as much <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trump-immigration-wall-exclusive-idUSKBN15O2ZN">as $21.6 billion</a> and cross hundreds of miles.</p>

<p>The rush for raising the wall has veteran contracting officers comparing the process to the rebuilding of Iraq and Afghanistan, multibillion-dollar efforts widely considered failures because of poor planning.</p>

<p>&#8220;This isn&#8217;t normal,&#8221; said Steven L. Schooner, a professor of government contracting at George Washington University. &#8220;This is shoot first, aim later.&#8221;</p>

<p>A CBP spokesman said the agency was &#8220;not in a position&#8221; to conduct an interview for this story.</p>

<p>The initial request, released with fanfare on Feb. 24, was not for building the actual wall, but for a prototype of a &#8220;total wall solution.&#8221;</p>

<p>The real bidding specifications &#8212; where the government would lay out details about the size, shape and construction of the wall &#8212; have yet to be announced. It&#8217;s not clear when they will be.</p>

<p>In another bidding <a href="https://www.fbo.gov/notices/8d3da7a86af51e252d019f2e13b08378">document</a> posted last week, the department&#8217;s &#8220;Procurement Innovation Lab&#8221; acknowledged that erecting the wall was going to be complex business.</p>

<p>Lab officials asked for help from industry to map out a comprehensive plan. America&#8217;s current 2,000-mile long border with Mexico is defended by a patchwork of physical and natural barriers, supplemented by the presence of U.S. Customs and Border Patrol agents.</p>

<p>&#8220;This strategy will need to accommodate the entire Southwest Border, which has a quite diverse range of terrain, foliage, population, wildlife, and other features,&#8221; explained the notice, known formally as a request for information.</p>

<p>The document raised an unusual question: How should the government pay for the wall?</p>

<p>The answer is usually straightforward. Under the U.S. Constitution, Congress appropriates funding for government projects.</p>

<p>In this case, however, Trump has vowed to make Mexico foot the bill, a proposition the Mexican government has vigorously rejected. Trump has responded by seeking cost savings. The Washington Post <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/to-fund-border-wall-trump-administration-weighs-cuts-to-coast-guard-airport-security/2017/03/07/ba4a8e5c-036f-11e7-ad5b-d22680e18d10_story.html?utm_term=.840573d6d61b">reported</a> Tuesday that White House officials have suggested raiding the budgets of the Coast Guard, the Transportation Security Agency and the Federal Emergency Management Agency to find money for the wall.</p>


<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/former-border-czar-gives-real-facts-about-immigration">Former &#8216;Border Czar&#8217; Gives Real Facts About Immigration</a></h2>
     <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/former-border-czar-gives-real-facts-about-immigration"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170213-immigration-qa-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>Alan Bersin says a border wall won&#8217;t address the real challenges confronting the U.S. border enforcement system: hopelessly understaffed immigration courts and lawlessness and poverty in Central America. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/former-border-czar-gives-real-facts-about-immigration"> Read the story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>Perhaps reflecting the uncertainty, Customs officials asked interested parties for their own ideas, in the form of five-page white papers with &#8220;models for financing, constructing and maintaining the wall.&#8221;</p>

<p>Another question: Will building the wall require &#8220;major deviations from federal law or regulation&#8221;?</p>

<p>More than 500 companies have expressed interest in the project. They include the usual cast of giant construction firms involved in federal projects, such as Tutor Perini Corp, Fluor Corp, and KBR, Inc., a former subsidiary of Halliburton once known as Kellogg, Brown &amp; Root.</p>

<p>But the list also includes more than a hundred smaller minority and veteran-owned firms, who receive special consideration under government contracting laws. Eleven percent of the companies are owned by Latinos.</p>

<p>Also among the interested parties: private security contractors, whose presence will almost certainly be necessary to protect the companies building the wall from protesters, vandals and thieves.</p>

<p>In war zones and New Orleans after Hurricane Katrina, such companies raised troubling questions about the use of force against civilians, including the murder of Iraqi and Afghan citizens. They also raised the price of some projects by as much as 25 percent.</p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5475157.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Trump Administration</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-08T15:19:27-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Here Are More Than 400 Officials Trump Has Quietly Deployed Across the Government</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5475158</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/beachhead#28682</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/al_shaw/" title="View Al Shaw's other articles">Al Shaw</a>


, <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/justin_elliott/" title="View Justin Elliott's other articles">Justin Elliott</a>


 and <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/derek_kravitz/" title="View Derek Kravitz's other articles">Derek Kravitz</a></p>
                                    <p>ProPublica has obtained a list of more than 400 people hired by the Trump administration to fill key roles across the federal government. 
</p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5475158.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-08T14:45:06-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meet the Hundreds of Officials Trump Has Quietly Installed Across the Government</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5475159</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/meet-hundreds-of-officials-trump-has-quietly-installed-across-government/#28683</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/justin_elliott/" title="View Justin Elliott's other articles">Justin Elliott</a>


, <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/derek_kravitz/" title="View Derek Kravitz's other articles">Derek Kravitz</a>


 and <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/al_shaw/" title="View Al Shaw's other articles">Al Shaw</a></p>
                                    <p>A Trump campaign aide who argues that Democrats committed &#8220;ethnic cleansing&#8221; in a plot to &#8220;liquidate&#8221; the white working class. A former reality show contestant whose study of societal collapse inspired him to invent a bow-and-arrow-<em>cum</em>-survivalist multi-tool. A pair of healthcare industry lobbyists. A lobbyist for defense contractors. An &#8220;evangelist&#8221; and lobbyist for Palantir, the Silicon Valley company with close ties to intelligence agencies. And a New Hampshire Trump supporter who has only recently graduated from high school.</p>

<p>These are some of the people the Trump administration has hired for positions across the federal government, according to documents received by ProPublica through public-records requests.</p>

<p>While President Trump has <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2017/02/25/politics/donald-trump-cabinet-vacancies/">not moved</a> to fill <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/politics/trump-administration-appointee-tracker/database/">many jobs</a> that require Senate confirmation, he has quietly installed hundreds of officials to serve as his eyes and ears at every major federal agency, from the Pentagon to the Department of Interior.</p>

<p>Unlike appointees exposed to the scrutiny of the Senate, members of these so-called &#8220;<a href="http://www.politico.com/blogs/donald-trump-administration/2017/01/beachhead-teams-agenda-inauguration-day-233774">beachhead teams</a>&#8221; have operated largely in the shadows, with the White House declining to publicly reveal their identities.</p>

<p>While some names have previously dribbled out in the press, <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/beachhead">we are publishing a list of more than 400 hires</a>, providing the most complete accounting so far of who Trump has brought into the federal government.</p>

<p>The White House <a href="http://www.politico.com/blogs/donald-trump-administration/2017/01/beachhead-teams-agenda-inauguration-day-233774">said</a> in January that around 520 staffers were being hired for the beachhead teams.</p>

<p>The list we obtained includes obscure campaign staffers, contributors to Breitbart and others who have embraced conspiracy theories, as well as dozens of Washington insiders who could be reasonably characterized as part of the &#8220;swamp&#8221; Trump pledged to drain.</p>

<p>The list is striking for how many former lobbyists it contains: We found at least 36, spanning industries from health insurance and pharmaceuticals to construction, energy and finance. Many of them lobbied in the same areas that are regulated by the agencies they have now joined.</p>


<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/beachhead">Here Are More Than 400 Officials Trump Has Quietly Deployed Across the Government</a></h2>
     <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/beachhead"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170308-beachhead-graphic-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>ProPublica has obtained a list of more than 400 people hired by the Trump administration to fill key roles across the federal government. <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/graphics/beachhead"> Read the story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>That figure is almost certainly an undercount since we only included those who formally registered as lobbyists, a process <a href="https://sunlightfoundation.com/2016/04/19/what-is-shadow-lobbying-how-influence-peddlers-shape-policy-in-the-dark/">increasingly avoided</a> by many in Washington.</p>

<p>During the campaign, Trump said he would have &#8220;<a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-before-would-have-no-problem-banning-lobbyists-trump-now-youre-hired">no problem</a>&#8221; banning lobbyists from his administration. But they have nonetheless ended up in senior roles, aided by Trump&#8217;s <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-the-trump-administration-may-be-skirting-its-own-ethics-rules">weakening of Obama-era ethics</a> rules that <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2015/12/barack-obama-revolving-door-lobbying-217042">modestly limited</a> lobbyists&#8217; role in government.</p>

<p>The White House didn&#8217;t respond to requests for comment.</p>

<p>There are many former congressional staffers, several top officials from the George W. Bush administration, and even a handful of holdovers from the Obama administration. The list also includes at least eight staffers drawn from the Heritage Foundation, a conservative think tank that <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2016/11/trump-transition-heritage-foundation-231722">forged close ties</a>&nbsp;to the new administration during the transition.</p>

<p>Much about the role of the beachhead teams at various federal agencies is unclear. But close observers of the early weeks of the Trump administration believe they have taken on considerable influence in the absence of high-level political appointees.</p>

<p>&#8220;If the public and Senate is in the dark about a team created without a Senate confirmation process, no one will be permitted to shed light on who is hopelessly conflicted or who is obviously unqualified &#8212; and who is both,&#8221; said <a href="http://cepr.net/about-us/staff/jeff-hauser-executive-director-of-the-revolving-door-project">Jeff Hauser</a>, director of the Revolving Door Project at the Center for Economic and Policy Research.</p>

<p>The beachhead team members are <a href="https://www.chcoc.gov/content/temporary-transition-schedule-c-authority-and-temporary-transition-senior-executive-service">temporary</a> employees serving for stints of four to eight months, but many are expected to move into permanent jobs. The Trump administration&#8217;s model is based on <a href="http://nbcpolitics.nbcnews.com/_news/2012/11/19/15264192-inside-the-romney-readiness-project-the-ambitious-plans-for-an-unrealized-administration?lite">plans</a> developed but never used by the unsuccessful presidential campaign of Mitt Romney.</p>

<p>&#8220;The beachhead teams involve people with considerable authority over the federal government,&#8221; said Max Stier, the CEO of the Partnership for Public Service, a nonpartisan group that <a href="http://presidentialtransition.org/ready-to-govern/index.php">advises</a> presidential candidates on smooth transitions. &#8220;We need clarity about what they&#8217;re doing and what their role is going to be.&#8221;</p>

<p>The Obama administration also hired temporary staffers after the inauguration. But Trump has brought in many more, Stier said.</p>

<p>The new list of names was provided to us by the Office of Personnel Management, the government&#8217;s human resources agency. We received additional names from other federal agencies in response to Freedom of Information Act requests. At least a few people on the list have changed agencies or left the administration, including, for example, the young Department of Housing and Urban Development staffer who was <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/02/16/us/politics/shermichael-singleton-housing-urban-development.html">fired</a> after his anti-Trump writings during the campaign came to light.</p>

<p>Here is a run-down of some of the Trump hires.</p>

<h2>The Breitbart wing</h2>

<p><strong>Curtis Ellis</strong> was a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160414050424/http://www.wnd.com/author/cellis/?archive=true">columnist</a> for WorldNetDaily, a website best known for its <a href="http://www.wnd.com/2011/04/286329/">enthusiastic</a> <a href="http://talkingpointsmemo.com/dc/birther-czar-joseph-farah-i-ve-been-talking-to-donald-trump-quite-a-bit">embrace</a> of the false notion that President Obama was born outside the United States. A column headlined the &#8220;The Radical Left&#8217;s Ethnic Cleansing of America&#8221; won Ellis an <a href="http://www.mediaite.com/online/trump-advisor-hillary-and-obama-want-ethnic-cleansing-of-white-working-people/">admiring interview</a> with Steve Bannon, now Trump&#8217;s top aide. He is a longtime <a href="http://www.breitbart.com/radio/2016/08/10/curtis-ellis-tpp-is-about-redistributing-the-wealth-of-america-to-the-rest-of-the-world/">critic</a> of trade deals such as the Trans-Pacific Partnership.<p>

<p>Ellis was hired Jan. 20 as a special assistant to the secretary at the Labor Department. Asked about his role in a brief phone interview Tuesday, he said: &#8220;Nothing I can tell you.&#8221;</p>

<p><strong>Jon Perdue</strong>, a self-described guerrilla warfare expert and fellow at a little-known security <a href="http://www.securefreesociety.org/about-sfs/sfs-team/">think tank</a>, wrote a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/War-All-People-Radicalism-Terrorism/dp/1597977047">book</a> called &#8220;The War of All the People: The Nexus of Latin American Radicalism and Middle Eastern Terrorism.&#8221; He is also a onetime <a href="http://www.breitbart.com/national-security/2010/07/08/chavezs-alliance-with-iran-and-how-to-stop-him/">contributor</a> to Breitbart.</p>

<p>Perdue was featured on CNBC&#8217;s reality series &#8220;Make Me a Millionaire Inventor&#8221; for his invention, the Packbow, which Perdue came up with while <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Packbow">studying</a> &#8220;collapsed societies, and what people who lived in those societies came up with to either defend themselves or to survive.&#8221; It&#8217;s a bow and arrow that <a href="http://packbow.com/">doubles as</a> a compass, tent pole, walking stick, spearfishing rig, and water purification tablet receptacle.</p>

<p>Perdue was hired as a special assistant at the Treasury Department. The agency didn&#8217;t immediately respond to a request for comment.</p>

<p><strong>John Jaggers</strong> ran the Trump campaign in Maryland and Virginia, where he made headlines for endorsing the conspiracy theory that Hillary Clinton was &#8220;<a href="https://thinkprogress.org/trump-operative-clinton-will-die-because-wool-coat-d28684385641#.mhkwyal20">very, very sick and they&#8217;re covering it up</a>.&#8221; As he put it last August: &#8220;The woman who seeks to be the first female president of the United States wears a wool coat at every single thing. Have you ever stopped to wonder why? It&#8217;s a big deal, folks.&#8221;</p>

<p>Jaggers was hired Jan. 20 as senior adviser at the General Services Administration, which oversees <a href="https://www.gsa.gov/portal/category/101606">tens of billions of dollars</a> of government procurement every year. But records show he left the job on March 3. He declined to comment.</p>

<h2>Swamp denizens, including health care lobbyists hired by HHS Secretary Tom Price</h2>

<p><strong>Alexandra Campau</strong>, hired at the department of Health and Human Services, was formerly <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/lobby/lobbyist.php?id=Y0000048211L&amp;year=2014">a lobbyist</a> in Washington for the law firm Cozen O&#8217;Connor. According to disclosure records, her firm&#8217;s clients included a licensee of insurance giant Blue Cross Blue Shield, and Fresenius Medical Care, a German company that specializes in medical supplies for renal dialysis.</p>

<p><strong>Timothy Clark</strong>, a senior adviser to HHS Secretary Tom Price, ran his own political consulting firm in California. His&nbsp;<a href="http://clarkstrategygroup.com/current-and-past-clients/">past clients</a>&nbsp;included PhRMA, the powerful trade group that represents the pharmaceutical industry.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/keagan-lenihan-071b511/?locale=de_DE">Keagan Lenihan</a></strong>, also a senior adviser to Price, was a director of government relations at McKesson Specialty Health, a firm that supports independent health providers. Disclosure <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/lobby/lobbyist.php?id=Y0000046788L&amp;year=2016">records</a> show Lenihan directly lobbied HHS. For Lenihan, the new post represents a return trip through the revolving door between government and the private sector, and a reunion with an old boss. Before registering as a lobbyist, she was a senior legislative assistant for Price, when the now-HHS secretary was in Congress.</p>

<p>Asked about the three HHS staffers, an agency spokeswoman said: &#8220;We are not confirming or commenting on personnel at this time.&#8221;</p>

<p><strong>Justin Mikolay</strong>, hired at the Department of Defense, was previously a registered lobbyist for Palantir. His title at the tech firm was &#8220;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/justin-mikolay-375bb02/">evangelist</a>.&#8221; Mikolay lobbied for the &#8220;procurement/deployment of the Palantir Government software platform&#8221; throughout intelligence and defense agencies, according to disclosure&nbsp;<a href="https://soprweb.senate.gov/index.cfm?event=getFilingDetails&amp;filingID=B1AA2EAD-09CE-4157-9747-7DEDA5B89E34&amp;filingTypeID=69">records</a>.</p>

<p>Mikolay was a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/justin-mikolay-375bb02/">speechwriter</a>&nbsp;to Secretary of Defense Leon Panetta between 2011 and 2013, according to his LinkedIn profile. Mikolay also previously served as a&nbsp;<a href="http://theeverybodyletter.com/2014/07/thanks-general-mattis-1/">speechwriter</a>&nbsp;for current Secretary of Defense James Mattis. He declined to comment.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://wexlerwalker.com/team_member/chad-wolf/">Chad Wolf</a></strong>, a Bush-era Transportation Security Administration official turned lobbyist, is currently serving as an adviser to the TSA at the Department of Homeland Security. His clients have included defense and homeland security contractors.</p>

<p>Reached Tuesday, Wolf declined to comment. George Rogers, CEO of Wolf&#8217;s lobbying firm, Wexler Walker, told ProPublica that Wolf is currently on unpaid leave.</p>

<p>As we&#8217;ve previously reported, lobbyists for the <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-watered-down-ethics-rules-let-lobbyist-help-run-agency-he-lobbied">construction industry</a> trade association and financial services firm <a href="https://www.facebook.com/notes/propublica/trump-admin-hired-another-lobbyist-to-work-at-an-agency-whose-regulations-he-onc/10155123953299445">TransAmerica</a> are on the team at the Department of Labor.</p>

<h2>Trump campaign vets &#8212; including very young ones</h2>

<p>The list also includes what appear to be dozens of former Trump campaign staffers, including several who graduated from college last year. One, Danny Tiso at the Department of Labor, graduated from high school in 2015, according to his LinkedIn <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/danny-tiso-961512a8/">profile</a>. He worked for the Trump campaign in New Hampshire.</p>

<p>Seth Harris, who was on the first Obama-Biden transition team and later became a top Labor Department official, said it&#8217;s not uncommon to bring in campaign staff to agencies &#8212; &#8220;as long as there are senior political people to direct the junior people.&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;This is how you incorporate the people who are your strongest supporters into the government,&#8221; he said. &#8220;There are plenty of junior jobs in the government that these people can do &#8212; public-affairs jobs, special assistant jobs.&#8221;</p>

<p><em>Reporting was contributed by Robert Faturechi, Jesse Eisinger, Alison Gregor, Jessica Huseman, Lauren Kirchner, Alec MacGillis, Clifford Michel, T. Christian Miller, Charles Ornstein, Andrew Revkin, Marcelo Rochabrun, Lisa Song and Annie Waldman.</em></p>

             <p class="note related-note"><p>If you have any information about members of the Trump beachhead teams or their roles in the agencies, contact us at <a href="mailto:beachhead@propublica.org">beachhead@propublica.org</a> or via Signal at 774-826-6240. Here is a guide for <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-to-leak-to-propublica">how to leak to ProPublica</a>.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5475159.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Trump Administration</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-08T14:44:26-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rules Frozen by Trump Could Melt Away Without a Trace</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5473108</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/rules-frozen-by-trump-could-melt-away-without-a-trace/#28681</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/jesse_eisinger/">Jesse Eisinger</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>Ridding day care centers of fluorescent lightbulbs with toxic PCBs. Requiring a backup engineer on freight trains to avoid crashes. Restricting drones from flying over people.</p>

<p>Federal agencies were preparing these rules and dozens more when Donald Trump was elected. In one of his first acts, the president <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/01/24/implementation-regulatory-freeze">quietly froze them</a>. That isn&#8217;t unusual. Presidents Clinton, Bush and Obama signed similar orders.</p>

<p>Unlike in previous administrations, however, this time the proposed rules are long shots to be finished and enacted. Because of &#8220;the very clear signals of an anti-regulatory mandate from the president,&#8221; they are less likely to be implemented than in prior eras, according to Sally Katzen, a New York University law professor and former deputy director for management at the Office of Management and Budget. Instead, they may vanish with little or no announcement or explanation. Already, they have disappeared from the main federal website that lists rules in the works.</p>

<p>Five federal agencies contacted by ProPublica said they are reviewing regulations but declined to address specifically the pending rules that were put on hold. A spokesman for the Health Resources and Services Administration said his agency is pursuing &#8220;efforts to reduce regulatory burden.&#8221; The White House did not respond to a request for comment.</p>

<p>While the media and the public focus on the Russia scandal or who has the ear of the president, the Trump administration and the Republican-controlled Congress are conducting a broad assault on regulations. Trump, making regulatory rollback a centerpiece of his administration, <a href="http://www.npr.org/2016/08/08/488816816/donald-trump-looks-to-turn-the-page-on-bad-week-with-economic-speech">contends </a>onerous rules stifle American businesses and the economy. Steve Bannon, his chief strategist, promised supporters a &#8220;<a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/top-wh-strategist-vows-a-daily-fight-for-deconstruction-of-the-administrative-state/2017/02/23/03f6b8da-f9ea-11e6-bf01-d47f8cf9b643_story.html?utm_term=.7f1e5a26fa3d">deconstruction of the administrative state</a>.&#8221; On Monday, The New York Times <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/05/us/politics/trump-deregulation-guns-wall-st-climate.html">surveyed the sweeping efforts</a> to roll back environmental rules, restrictions on Wall Street, and other limitations on businesses of every stripe.</p>

<p>Finalized rules cannot be easily rescinded. Doing so often requires some congressional action. And agencies typically must explain why they are canceling a rule. Groups that object sometimes sue to preserve the regulations.</p>

<p>But dozens of rules are pending and those may be easier to kill. After previous administrations&#8217; freezes, agencies examined proposed rules and went forward with the vast majority, according to administrative law experts. This time may be different. A few days after his freeze, Trump signed another executive order on Jan. 30, ordering that agencies cut <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/01/30/presidential-executive-order-reducing-regulation-and-controlling">two old regulations for each new one</a>. Given that edict, federal agencies, like the Department of Transportation or the Environmental Protection Agency, may resist finalizing pending rules.</p>

<p>Regulations often undergo review for years before they take effect. Typically, after a law is passed, the appropriate agency comes up with proposed rules for implementing it, and puts them out for public comment. Supporters and opponents (often corporations or their representatives) weigh in. The agency then edits the rules and sends them to the Office of Information and Regulatory Affairs, a body within the Office of Management and Budget. There, the office conducts an economic analysis to make sure the costs don&#8217;t outweigh the benefits. Finally, if the new regulations clear all the hurdles, they are published in the Federal Register. After 60 or 90 days, they become effective.</p>

<p>At least 25 rules were waiting on the OIRA runway for final approval in the waning days of the Obama administration. Some had gone through the entire process and merely required being sent to the Federal Register. (A separate group of regulations were at the Federal Register but had not become effective. These are on hold as well.)</p>

<p>Among the pending rules was a Department of Transportation <a href="https://www.fra.dot.gov/eLib/Details/L17369">initiative calling for</a> all railroad operations to have at least two crew members. Proponents say the rule could minimize the risk of a repeat of the 2013 Canadian train accident in which a derailed, unattended locomotive became a burning missile hurtling through a small Canadian town called Lac-M&#233;gantic, killing 47 people and spilling 6 million liters of crude oil. The railroad industry has objected to the new restriction, contending the rule is <a href="https://www.mercatus.org/system/files/McLaughlin-FRA-Crew-Size-Rule-v1.pdf">too costly and unlikely to minimize accidents</a>.</p>

<p>Another rule would require that fluorescent lights in daycares and schools contain no PCBs, which can become toxic when burned. Still others cover everything from grain elevator performance to disclosures about foods that have been bioengineered.</p>

<p>Trump&#8217;s two-for-one edict already faces problems. It stipulates that the incremental cost of new regulations in 2017 must be zero: In other words, that discarding two regulations must save as much money as the new regulation costs. The trouble with this approach is that regulations typically entail large upfront investments, but little in the way of ongoing outlays. For instance, if the government requires retrofitting of certain plants with safer machines, that&#8217;s expensive at first. But once manufacturers have complied, the ongoing cost is minimal. Therefore, to find enough savings to offset a new regulation might mean cutting many more than two old ones.</p>


<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-the-trump-administration-may-be-skirting-its-own-ethics-rules">How the Trump Administration May Be Skirting Its Own Ethics Rules</a></h2>
     <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-the-trump-administration-may-be-skirting-its-own-ethics-rules"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170303-lobbyists-trump-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>The hiring of three former lobbyists to work in the White House raises questions about how the Trump administration is enforcing the president&#8217;s executive order on ethics. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-the-trump-administration-may-be-skirting-its-own-ethics-rules">Read the story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>Perhaps more significantly, scholars argue that the Trump order is against the law. &#8220;Agencies do not simply regulate for the sake of regulation &#8212; each regulation is aimed at implementing a specific provision of a statute passed by Congress,&#8221; Columbia Law School&#8217;s Michael Burger and Jessica Wentz <a href="http://blogs.law.columbia.edu/climatechange/2017/02/01/trumps-executive-order-on-regulatory-costs-is-not-only-arbitrary-it-is-also-against-the-law/">wrote recently</a>. Indeed, liberal groups Public Citizen, the National Resources Defense and the Communications Workers of American <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2017/02/trump-sued-2-for-1-regulations-234788">filed a lawsuit</a> to block the Trump executive order, contending it is arbitrary.</p>

<p>But there&#8217;s little legal recourse for resurrecting proposed rules, which might be shelved without any public notice. If agencies do so, it&#8217;s unclear if they have to explain why. Liberal interest groups argue that ditching pending rules without a legitimate justification might not stand up to a court challenge, though they concede it&#8217;s uncharted territory. They say rules that have undergone public comments and other scrutiny may also be protected under the prohibitions against arbitrary regulatory decisions.</p>

<p>&#8220;We believe it is illegal to kill a final rule without good reason, not just that Donald Trump doesn&#8217;t like rules,&#8221; said Rena Steinzor, a law professor at the University of Maryland and former president of <a href="http://www.progressivereform.org/">Center for Progressive Reform</a>, a think tank. &#8220;That&#8217;s not good enough.&#8221;</p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5473108.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Trump Administration</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-08T08:00:54-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>These For-Profit Schools Are Like a Prison</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5472526</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/these-for-profit-schools-are-like-a-prison/#28680</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">by Sarah Carr, Francesca Berardi, Zo&#235; Kirsch and Stephen Smiley, The Teacher Project,</p>
            <p class="note copublish-note"><p>This story was co-published with Slate.</p></p>                        <p>Teenagers at Paramount Academy sometimes came home with mysterious injuries.</p>

<p>An alternative school for sixth- through 12th-graders with behavioral or academic problems, Paramount occupied a low-slung, brick and concrete building on a dead-end road in hard-luck Reading, Pennsylvania, a city whose streets are littered with signs advertising bail bondsmen, pay-day lenders, and pawn shops. Camelot Education, the for-profit company that ran Paramount under a contract with the Reading school district, maintained a set of strict protocols: No jewelry, book bags, or using the water fountain or bathroom without permission. Just as it still does at dozens of schools, the company deployed a small platoon of &#8220;behavioral specialists&#8221; and &#8220;team leaders&#8221;: typically large men whose job was partly to enforce the rules.</p>

<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system">Listen to This Story</a></h2>
     <iframe width="100%" height="200" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/311230679&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;visual=true"></iframe>
    <p>Hear a narrated version of this story. <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/app/apple-store/id1138892702?mt=8">Download the Audm app</a> for your iPhone to listen to more titles.

</div>


<p>Over six months in 2013 and 2014, about a half-dozen parents, students and community members at Paramount Academy &#8212; billed as a &#8220;therapeutic&#8221; day program &#8212; complained of abusive behavior by the school&#8217;s staff. One mother heard that staff restrained students by &#8220;excessive force&#8221; and bruised the arms of a female student, according to email exchanges between Camelot and the district. Another mother, Sharon Pacharis, said she visited the school to complain about manhandling and was told, &#8220;That&#8217;s just what we do.&#8221; Camelot&#8217;s own written reports to the district documented one incident in which a teenager was scratched and another in which a bathroom wall was damaged. Both resulted from &#8220;holds&#8221; &#8212; likely a reference to Camelot&#8217;s protocol for restraining students during a physical encounter.</p>

<p>Camelot tended to blame the students in its weekly reports to the district, calling them &#8220;out of control&#8221;; school officials referred several to police. It was, after all, a place partly for students whom the district had deemed too disruptive for a traditional school setting.</p>

<p>But an incident on April 24, 2014, abruptly shifted the focus to Camelot&#8217;s staff.</p>

<p>Ismael Seals, a behavioral specialist, walked into a classroom with several loud and boisterous students and commanded them to &#8220;shut the fuck up,&#8221; decreeing that the next one who talked would get body-slammed through the door, according to a subsequent criminal complaint. Moments later, Seals fulfilled his promise. After 17-year-old Corey Mack asked and received permission from his teacher, Teresa Bivens, to get up to sharpen his pencil, Seals pushed him repeatedly against a door and then shoved him into the hall, where a school surveillance camera recorded most of the rest of the incident. Seals, 6 feet 4 inches tall and 280 pounds, lifted Mack, 5 feet 8 inches tall and about 160 pounds, by his shirt and swung him into the wall headfirst, later pinning him to the ground as other staff members arrived, according to court documents.</p>

<p>Mack later showed a string of bruises and scratches on his back to a program director at a center for children with behavioral and mental health challenges. The program director called a juvenile probation official, who contacted the police.</p>

<p>Reached by telephone last fall, Corey Mack struggled to remember the details of his altercation with Seals, including what he had said just before the behavioral specialist shoved him, and the precise sequence of events. But he was clear on the essential point: &#8220;He beat me up,&#8221; Mack said.</p>

<hr />

<p>The Seals incident is the best-documented example of staff-on-student violence at facilities run by Camelot, a company dogged by allegations of similar abuses. Thirteen Camelot students have alleged in interviews or documents that they were shoved, beaten, or thrown &#8212; assaults almost always referred to as &#8220;slamming&#8221; &#8212; by Camelot staff members, usually for the sin of talking back, in separate incidents that span 10 years and three states. (Six of the students <a href="http://www.nola.com/news/index.ssf/2009/06/schwarz.html">were interviewed</a> in 2009 in New Orleans.) Two additional students, and five Camelot staff members, say they have personally witnessed beatings or physical aggression by staff.</p>

<p>The abuse allegedly occurred in Camelot programs in Reading; Lancaster; Philadelphia; New Orleans; and Pensacola, Florida. Jandy Rivera, for instance, a former teacher at Camelot-run Phoenix Academy in Lancaster, Pennsylvania, says that on multiple occasions staff members, including administrators, &#8220;baited kids so they could hit kids.&#8221; For the most part, staffers who allegedly assaulted students have faced no criminal charges or internal discipline; some have even been promoted.</p>

<p>The Florida Department of Children and Families, which investigates reports of child abuse, is looking into an incident last week at Camelot Academy in Pensacola in which a behavioral specialist, while breaking up a fight between students, allegedly knocked a 13-year-old to the ground, causing a bloody abrasion and bruising near the teenager&#8217;s eye. The youth posted a graphic photo of his swollen face on Facebook. &#8220;I do not like this way of disciplining kids,&#8217;&#8217; said his mother, Pauline Ball. &#8220;You can give him a permanent injury.&#8221; Camelot said the specialist &#8220;had to intervene to protect other students,&#8221; and that the injuries were an accident: &#8220;The staff member and student tripped over each other&#8217;s feet and both fell.&#8221;</p>


<div class="graphic-promo-vertical">
    <figure>
        <img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_630/20170308-pensacola-inline.jpg" />
        <figcaption>This 13-year-old student at Camelot Academy in Pensacola, Florida, says his face was bruised when a staff member knocked him to the ground. Camelot says it was an accident. (Courtesy of Pauline Ball)</figcaption>
    </figure>
</div>


<p>Despite such allegations, Camelot has continued to expand. It contracts with traditional school districts to run about 40 schools across the country &#8212; schools that serve kids who have gotten into trouble, have emotional or behavioral issues, or have fallen far behind academically. In 2015, Camelot reported more than $77 million in revenue, more than a third from contracts with the school districts of Philadelphia, Houston, and Chicago. The company also maintains a large presence in some heavily Hispanic old factory towns of Pennsylvania.</p>

<p>About half a million students in the United States attend alternative schools, which are publicly funded but often managed by private, for-profit companies such as Camelot. Camelot&#8217;s story illustrates the risk that <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2009-12-15/online-colleges-surge-with-marketing-to-military">for-profit schools</a>, which are <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2017/02/03/us/politics/betsy-devos-nominee-education-secretary.html?_r=0">favored by the Trump administration and new Education Secretary Betsy DeVos</a>, may put earnings ahead of student welfare. It also exposes the dismal educational options available to some students that traditional high schools don&#8217;t want to serve, because they are disruptive, severely disabled, years behind in school, or have criminal backgrounds.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3482701-Camelot.html">In a 17-page response</a> to written questions, Camelot and its chief executive, Todd Bock, denied any claims of systemic abuse across its programs and said it provides effective and supportive services to thousands of the country&#8217;s most challenging and needy students. The company cited a student survey that found 23 percent of its students were homeless or had been homeless; 78 percent did not have a father living in their household; and 45 percent said violence in the school they attended before Camelot impeded their success. The company also maintained that it has a long record of academic success, and that it does not place profits over its students&#8217; well-being. It cited a 2010 study by the Mathematica Policy Research organization which found that students at a couple of Camelot-run programs in Philadelphia accumulated more credits and were more likely to graduate than their counterparts in competing programs. While student and staff confidentiality prevented the company from going into details, it said, &#8220;immediate action is taken in the very rare instance&#8221; of allegations of physical abuse. In regard to student safety, the company said the incidents in Pennsylvania, Pensacola and New Orleans &#8220;were handled with the utmost diligence and care.&#8221;</p>

<p>Camelot also questioned why some teachers and former teachers &#8212; who are mandatory reporters of suspected child abuse &#8212; would wait months, or years, to express their concerns. &#8220;With the exception of an isolated incident in Reading, PA in which we immediately investigated and terminated multiple employees, Camelot has had no founded child abuse cases or lawsuits involving our students over the last decade,&#8221; the statement read. &#8220;Your narrative is formulated using fewer than 10 incidents from the almost 5,940,000 daily interactions over a period of 10 years.&#8221; (A daily interaction is one student going to a Camelot school for one day.) Indeed, very little is known about the vast majority of the daily interactions across Camelot&#8217;s schools, partly because they face almost no scrutiny, at every level. School-district officials, desperate to farm out the students most likely to depress their test scores and graduation rates, have repeatedly failed to investigate allegations of mistreatment at Camelot schools.</p>

<p>Moreover, state officials in Pennsylvania have designed the accountability system in a way that obscures the academic results of the state&#8217;s alternative programs. Test scores of thousands of alternative students are never tagged to a school, instead counting only toward the district&#8217;s performance, making it virtually impossible to gauge and compare the quality of individual schools. In 2013, the Philadelphia-based Education Law Center filed a <a href="http://www.elc-pa.org/cases/doj-aedy-complaint-8713/">statewide complaint</a> alleging that the Pennsylvania Department of Education fails to adequately monitor its alternative schools, which the center says too often have subpar, insufficient academic programs. The complaint is pending.</p>

<p>Add it all up, skeptics say, and the Camelot experience starts to resemble the nation&#8217;s incarceration system: racially biased, isolated, punitive, unnecessarily violent and designed, above all else, to maintain obedience and control.</p>

<p>That&#8217;s how Camelot&#8217;s Phoenix Academy felt to Jose Muriel. There, he argued with a staff member, who held him against a door and then pushed him to the ground, bruising his arm, the Spanish-speaking Muriel said through an interpreter. Camelot denied that he was restrained or mistreated. After the incident, Muriel said, he saw a therapist, and skipped school for weeks, before finally graduating.</p>

<p>&#8220;That place was like a prison,&#8221; he said.</p>

<hr />

<p>After Ismael Seals&#8217; assault on Corey Mack, a cover-up began almost immediately. In a detailed write-up of the incident, Seals described Mack as the instigator. But the surveillance footage of the hallway contradicted key details in Seals&#8217; account, according to court documents.</p>

<p>Seals wrote in his report that he led Mack from the room using a technique he described as a &#8220;one arm upper escort.&#8221; According to court documents, the video showed him pulling Mack from the classroom by his shirt before pushing him against a wall. Seals also wrote that Mack became aggressive and threatening, swinging his hands wildly at one point. The video showed that the student remained silent, with his hands at his sides &#8212; except for when Seals picked him up and threw him headfirst against a wall. Finally, Seals reported that his glasses were knocked off by Mack during the tussle while the video showed Seals&#8217; glasses falling off as he threw Mack toward the wall, according to court documents.</p>

<p>Teresa Bivens, the teacher who gave Mack permission to sharpen his pencil, initially told police that Mack had been disruptive and caused the fight. She also wrote an internal school report implicating him. But four days after her initial police interview, Bivens confessed to authorities that she had lied at the urging of unnamed &#8220;higher-ups&#8221; who wanted to cover up the incident. Bivens also reported that she had conspired with Seals and a &#8220;supervisor&#8221; about how to write the reports to put the blame on Mack, not Seals. At the time, Camelot administrators denied pressuring Bivens to lie, and prosecutors said they did not have enough evidence to charge more senior employees of Camelot. Camelot provided a different version of events in its response for this article, claiming the company &#8220;immediately investigated&#8221; and reported the incident to authorities before firing Seals and Bivens.</p>

<p>Bivens pleaded guilty to conspiracy and making a false statement to authorities and was sentenced to two years of probation. Seals pleaded guilty to assault, conspiracy and making a false statement; he served 17 days in prison. His is the only case we found in which a Camelot staff member has been convicted of beating a student.</p>

<p>In a tearful interview, Seals told us that he deeply regretted what had happened. He said he had been drawn to working with troubled students largely because of his own tough background: He spent some of his boyhood in foster care and group homes. Seals recalled fondly the staff-student bonding events that Camelot sponsored, including a Thanksgiving dinner and a basketball game. Part of his job at Camelot was to &#8220;de-escalate&#8221; potential conflicts, he said. &#8220;It worked to some extent.&#8221;</p>

<p>He declined to comment on the assault &#8212; on the advice of a lawyer, he said &#8212; but offered an apology: &#8220;I realize I made a mistake and got to be accountable for it,&#8221; he said. &#8220;I really miss those kids.&#8221;</p>

<p>A moment later, he added, &#8220;Man, I messed up.&#8221;</p>

<hr />

<p>Before there was Camelot, there was the Brown Schools, a for-profit company that ran treatment centers for young people with severe emotional and behavioral needs. In some cases, parents signed their children up for Brown facilities; in other cases, school or juvenile-justice personnel referred them to the programs. Over 15 years, five children and teenagers died in Brown&#8217;s care. One was a 9-year-old boy who died of a heart attack after being held face down by employees. Another time, a 17-year-old choked on his own vomit after three Brown staffers allegedly pinned him to the ground. Ironically, the 17-year-old victim&#8217;s father, attorney Charles Moody, had represented Brown in an earlier restraint-related death at one of its facilities. &#8220;They certainly did not train and/or hire particularly qualified people,&#8221; Moody said in an interview.</p>

<p>John Harcourt served as chief executive officer of Brown Schools from 1995 to 1999. In 2002, after his non-compete agreement expired, he acquired the alternative school company that became Camelot. In a 2009 letter to a Philadelphia city councilman, a Camelot official wrote that, while allegations regarding Brown Schools&#8217; treatment of children &#8220;may have basis in fact,&#8221; they related to the period after Harcourt left Brown. Harcourt remained chief executive of Camelot Schools until 2011. </p>

<p>Camelot would employ other former leaders of Brown, which effectively shut down in 2005. Todd Bock, now the president and chief executive officer of Camelot, was director for public education at Brown Schools. We identified eight other Camelot employees, including two vice presidents and the leader of business development, who previously worked at Brown.</p>

<p>Camelot said it isn&#8217;t an outgrowth of Brown. &#8220;While it is a fact that ... current Camelot employees worked for the Brown Schools, one organization has nothing to do with the other,&#8221; it said in its statement.</p>

<p>Still, the association with Brown has at times dogged Camelot&#8217;s pursuit of new contracts.</p>

<p>Current Philadelphia Mayor Jim Kenney asked for a reconsideration of Camelot&#8217;s contracts there when he served as a city councilman eight years ago, citing Brown Schools. Responding to Kenney, the Philadelphia School District compiled a five-page memo, based largely on paperwork submitted by Camelot itself. &#8220;While the allegations about Brown Schools and its affiliates may have basis in fact,&#8221; it concluded, &#8220;Camelot Schools is not a corporate or legal successor of Brown Schools.&#8221;</p>

<p>Camelot took in nearly $10 million this year from its Philadelphia schools. Through a spokesperson, Kenney declined to comment, referring all questions on the company&#8217;s performance to the school district.</p>

<p>In Millville, New Jersey, the school board <a href="http://www.thedailyjournal.com/story/news/2016/06/21/millville-school-system-bringing-company-alternative-education-camelot/86138602/">voted last year</a> to hire Camelot. Kim Carty, a school-board member who opposed the hiring, expressed concern at the time about the company&#8217;s connection to Brown.</p>

<p>Financial considerations helped sway the board. Camelot promised to run the Millville alternative school for $8,000 per pupil, compared to the $15,000 per pupil the school district spent to run it on its own. &#8220;As a mom and taxpayer, I question how a for-profit company can promise such a large cost savings while also making a profit for their investors,&#8221; Carty said in an interview. &#8220;I worry that we are failing the kids who need us most by making their education someone's profit.&#8221;</p>

<p>In a letter to District Superintendent David Gentile after the school board hired Camelot, Bock wrote that his company felt &#8220;gratified to be able to save the school district a substantial amount of money compared to what you currently spend on alternative education.&#8221; But he devoted most of the letter to expressing his &#8220;enormous disappointment&#8221; that &#8220;the fictitious Camelot-Brown relationship is back in the Google search,&#8221; referring to a <a href="http://www.thedailyjournal.com/story/news/2016/06/21/millville-school-system-bringing-company-alternative-education-camelot/86138602/">local news report</a> that mentioned the alleged Brown tie. He asked the superintendent to share with board members his &#8220;extreme disappointment in the scurrilous attack on our reputation.&#8221;</p>

<hr />

<p>Camelot and Brown certainly have one thing in common: They have both profited from the urgency felt by parents and public schools to find a place for troubled youth. But they filled different niches: While Brown specialized in residential treatment centers for children with emotional and behavioral disabilities, Camelot Education offers nonresidential programs and enrolls a broader range of students. A focus on serving kids whom school districts don&#8217;t want is a shrewd business strategy in an era when test scores, graduation rates and other data-based outcomes matter greatly &#8212; and are frequently tied to funding &#8212; giving school districts incentive to shed the hardest-to-educate students from their rolls.</p>

<p>Public school districts typically contract with Camelot to run one of three types of programs: &#8220;transitional schools&#8221; for kids with behavior issues; &#8220;therapeutic programs&#8221; for those with special behavioral and emotional needs; and &#8220;accelerated programs&#8221; for students who have fallen far behind. Some of their sites, particularly accelerated programs like Phoenix Academy in Lancaster, combine students from all three categories as well as other populations &#8212; pretty much any type of student the district doesn&#8217;t believe it can adequately serve, or doesn&#8217;t want to. In August, <a href="http://www.pennlive.com/news/2016/08/lancaster_refugee_school.html">a federal judge ruled</a> that the Lancaster, Pennsylvania, school district, which was funneling some newly arrived refugees to Phoenix, had to allow them to attend the main district high school. The school district maintains that its support for refugee students is appropriate.</p>

<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system">&#8216;Alternative&#8217; Education: Using Charter Schools to Hide Dropouts and Game the System</a></h2>
     <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170221-alt-schools-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>School officials nationwide dodge accountability ratings by steering low achievers to alternative programs. In Orlando, Florida, the nation&#8217;s tenth-largest district, thousands of students who leave alternative charters run by a for-profit company aren&#8217;t counted as dropouts.<a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system"> Read the story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>Most Camelot students share two characteristics. They are nearly all poor. And they are overwhelmingly peopleof color. In Lancaster, for instance, Phoenix Academy last year enrolled a significantly higher share of Hispanic students, and those with special needs, than the district as a whole. The school district says the population at Phoenix this year more closely resembles the district&#8217;s overall demographics. In Pensacola, Florida, black students comprise about two-thirds of the Camelot school&#8217;s enrollment, compared to a third of overall school-district enrollment. Of the close to 900 students who attended Camelot schools in Chicago last school year, zero were white.</p>

<p>Some students are reassigned to Camelot because they committed serious disciplinary infractions at prior schools, such as possessing drugs or fighting. In other cases, the reasons are more nebulous. In interviews, several families described feeling pressured by school-district officials to attend Camelot-run schools simply because their children were far behind academically, couldn&#8217;t speak English fluently, or had special needs the district didn&#8217;t want to meet. One mother said a district official in Reading simply told her, &#8220;We can&#8217;t deal with him anymore.&#8221;</p>

<p>The private-equity firm Riverside has owned Camelot since 2011. A <a href="https://www.riversidecompany.com/Portfolio/Portfolio_Companies/Camelot_Education_-_Company_Profile.aspx">promotional video</a> that Riverside created for Camelot praises the company&#8217;s benefits to taxpayers and students. It notes that Camelot spends an average of $12,000 per child in its alternative school programs, compared to $20,000 spent by a traditional school district. Without the company&#8217;s distinctive approach, the video contends, students risked &#8220;becoming a statistic.&#8221;</p>

<hr />

<p>In the Camelot curriculum, structure and discipline reign above all else. &#8220;The staff, their job is to make sure we don&#8217;t fall out of order,&#8221; said Jamire Warner, a 22-year-old who attended two Camelot schools in Philadelphia. &#8220;That&#8217;s what they call protocol. Being there is like being detained.&#8221; Warner, who said he was sent to Camelot after beating up a classmate, found the structure overwhelming, but the academics less so. &#8220;The education was pretty basic,&#8221; he said, noting that a typical class might involve filling out a single worksheet. &#8220;They dumbed it down at Camelot.&#8221;</p>

<p>At most Camelot schools, staff members search students arriving each day. Students can bring virtually no personal belongings with them apart from their clothes; that prohibition can make it difficult for girls to bring enough sanitary napkins and tampons. In the hallways, most students are required to walk with their hands behind their backs. At the Lancaster school district&#8217;s request, Camelot allowed students to walk with their hands in front of them at Phoenix Academy, since the school was not created for students with discipline problems.</p>

<p>Behavioral specialists are supposed to not only enforce the rules but also act as counselors to students, and calm them down as needed. Former students remember some of them as aggressive and bullying; others were trusted mentors and role models. Carolyn Murphy, who taught math at Phoenix between 2013 and 2015 recalls &#8220;behavioral specialists that [the students] really developed relationships with &#8230; It was a very well run environment. Violence was not really something I ever experienced there.&#8221;</p>

<p>Camelot creates a stratified social hierarchy that affords students at the top special privileges, such as eating lunch with the principal, walking down the hall without keeping their hands behind their backs, and leaving campus for field trips. &#8220;We have a unique ability to create a positive school environment, and we do that by manipulating the peer group,&#8221; Bock said in the promotional video created by Riverside. &#8220;We&#8217;re going to take that negative leader and turn them into a positive leader.&#8221;</p>

<p>At Phoenix Academy, the favored students can become &#8220;firebirds,&#8221; allowing them to don black uniform shirts rather than the green shirts worn by their classmates. Consistently exemplary behavior on the part of a firebird can lead to an &#8220;executive&#8221; designation &#8212; along with a gray shirt. When two reporters visited Phoenix last month, about two-thirds of the students were wearing green shirts, and most of the rest black shirts; only two students wore gray shirts.</p>

<p>The privileges have different names at different Camelot schools; at Camelot Academy in Pensacola, the more highly-regarded students are known as &#8216;Tigers&#8217; and can wear &#8220;tiger shirts&#8221; and hang out in the &#8220;tiger shark room,&#8221; according to a former student, Ladaryl Purifoy.</p>

<p>As a well-ranked student, &#8220;you would get to go to the bathroom, and get water if you were thirsty,&#8221; Warner said. He earned executive status, but then lost it for an offense that he can&#8217;t recall.</p>

<p>Teenagers were often rewarded with &#8220;tiger&#8221; or &#8220;executive&#8221; designations for reasons unrelated to academic performance. One former Camelot student said he gained &#8220;executive&#8221; status partly because of his willingness to serve as a student tour guide when visitors came to the school, particularly school-board members and journalists. The student, who did not want to be identified because he might re-enroll at the school, said its executive director would tell him what to say, what not to say, and also asked him to instruct teachers to put &#8220;academic things&#8221; on their walls before the visitors arrived. &#8220;I would have to say that the failure ratio is really low, when it&#8217;s really not,&#8221; he said. &#8220;I would say that students are supported to the best of their abilities, when really they&#8217;re not.&#8221;</p>

<p>When the executive director no longer needed him as a tour leader, she removed the student&#8217;s title. &#8220;Now that I lost my executive rating, no teachers will help me,&#8221; he said. &#8220;When I&#8217;m helping your school, you love me. But when I need you, where are you?&#8221;</p>

<p>While all of the students interviewed for this piece said they bonded with at least one Camelot staff member, most of them also said that other behavioral specialists and team leaders behaved like bullies, in word and deed. &#8220;They would say very offensive things like, &#8216;You guys aren&#8217;t going to be nothing in life,&#8217;&#8221; said Jose Muriel, the Phoenix Academy graduate. &#8220;They would curse at you directly and in general.&#8221;</p>

<p>Muriel and other former students and teachers said that the verbal baiting sometimes had a discriminatory element. One former teacher recalled that white staff members called black students &#8220;boy,&#8221; for instance. One student said some staff would tell the Hispanic teenagers that they planned to vote for Trump to rid the country of Spanish speakers.</p>

<p>A current Camelot student, 18, lamented that one behavioral specialist routinely referred to him as a &#8220;retard.&#8221; The student, who has attended the same Camelot school since the sixth grade, asked not to be identified by name since he fears retaliation. A more sympathetic staff member advised the teen to &#8220;pay them no mind.&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;He tells me, &#8216;They say that to make you mad so you will drop out and won&#8217;t be nothing,&#8221; the student said. When staff members bully him now, the student buries his head in his arms on his desk and tries as hard as he can to tune them out.</p>

<p>Asked about staff bullying students, Camelot said it has &#8220;no such evidence.&#8221; Camelot has a student government organization, and every student is taught a grievance process &#8220;to register complaints with campus leadership,&#8221; it said.</p>

<p>Some Camelot students appreciated the school&#8217;s tough-love approach. Serge Jules, a 23-year-old former student at Camelot Excel Academy South in Philadelphia, has positive memories of the two years he spent there. &#8220;Teachers cared about students and their personal issues,&#8221; he said. Staff physically restrained the students at times, and sometimes engaged in physical fights with the kids. But they &#8220;were just doing their jobs,&#8221; he added, noting that &#8220;it was the students&#8217; fault.&#8221;</p>

<p>Ja&#8217;mirca Delacruz attended Excel Academy at the same time as Jules; she shares much of his affection for Camelot. &#8220;Teachers care more than in regular schools,&#8221; she said. &#8220;They helped me out.&#8221; She also witnessed students being physically restrained, which she described as similar to getting arrested: Staff members grabbed students&#8217; arms and pinned them behind their backs. But Delacruz thought that for the most part the physical restraints were done the &#8220;right way.&#8221;</p>

<p>Camelot held detailed orientation sessions for parents and students, she said. &#8220;The main thing for me is, give the kids a complete heads up of what will happen to them if they get out of control,&#8221; she said. &#8220;&#8230; If you can&#8217;t handle it, you don&#8217;t belong there, and it becomes hell.&#8221;</p>

<hr />

<p>There&#8217;s nothing in the written policies of Camelot schools that mentions slamming, but there is something called &#8220;handle with care.&#8221; This protocol calls for staff members to use a series of de-escalation strategies on disruptive students, starting with nonverbal cues, such as eye contact, and moving on to verbal redirection. If the students fail to respond to the less intrusive efforts, the staff member is supposed to pin children&#8217;s hands behind their backs, lead them over to a wall, and ease them into a seated posture. Camelot parents typically sign consent forms allowing school staff to physically restrain their children as a last resort.</p>

<p>&#8220;You&#8217;re only supposed to go to that last step if the student is posing a danger, and you never go directly to that,&#8221; said Jandy Rivera, who taught at Phoenix Academy between 2011 and 2013. But that&#8217;s not what happened in practice. &#8220;On various occasions they would just bang the kid, bang the kid, bang the kid,&#8221; Rivera said, jerking her body back and forth. &#8220;The men had this militaristic mentality that you could shove kids around and talk to them however you wanted.&#8221; Once, a Camelot school administrator baited a physically slight student into a fight in Rivera&#8217;s classroom, she said. The incident ended with the administrator yanking the student from his desk, shoving him up against a door and throwing him into a wall.</p>

<p>Rivera <a href="http://lancasteronline.com/insider/lawsuit-expert-calls-pace-at-phoenix-academy-totally-inappropriate-for/article_d2f46406-65a8-11e6-9633-8fb21f36b89b.html">testified about the violence</a> last summer as part of the federal court case related to the assignment of international refugee students to Phoenix Academy. She also expressed her concerns more than once to her Camelot supervisor, she said. Camelot said Rivera &#8220;never talked with her supervisor or registered a complaint about any situation involving incidents to which she testified&#8221; in the lawsuit.</p>

<p>The incidents at Camelot tended to follow a similar pattern, according to multiple accounts from students and staff members. Nonacademic staff members (usually the behavioral specialists and team leaders but sometimes higher-level employees) were permitted by administrators and school leaders to manhandle students as a form of intimidation &#8212; whether the teenagers had acted out or not. They preyed most often on students who had the least recourse to complain: social pariahs whose parents were disengaged or unable to advocate effectively, because they didn&#8217;t speak English, for instance.</p>

<p>School leaders condoned the abuse and in some cases even encouraged it, according to Jandy Rivera and others. Staff routinely picked on the Hispanic students and the quiet students. &#8220;The people they would help would be the cool kids who were always trying to pick a fight,&#8221; said former Phoenix student Luis Colon.</p>

<p>The cases weren&#8217;t always clear-cut, however. And unlike the incident in Reading, they weren&#8217;t often captured on video, witnessed by multiple people, or even reported to authorities.</p>

<p>Colon emigrated from Puerto Rico with his mother when he was 9, following the death of his father. They went first to Buffalo, where his grandmother lived, and then to Lancaster, a small city bustling with Hispanic immigrants, where sidewalk signs advertise cheap flan.</p>

<p>Before attending Phoenix, Colon spent two years at Buerhle School, another Camelot program in Lancaster that serves students with disciplinary issues. &#8220;I wasn&#8217;t always quiet,&#8221; he said. &#8220;I&#8217;m not going to lie to you. &#8230; Sometimes I got into altercations just like everybody.&#8221;</p>

<p>A native Spanish speaker, Colon also struggled academically in public schools. Phoenix, however, offered an accelerated high school program in which he could earn his credits in 2 1/2 years. &#8220;It seemed like a great opportunity,&#8221; he said.</p>

<p>Colon quickly discovered that despite its many structures and routines, the school <a href="http://lancasteronline.com/insider/lawsuit-expert-calls-pace-at-phoenix-academy-totally-inappropriate-for/article_d2f46406-65a8-11e6-9633-8fb21f36b89b.html">lacked appropriate academic support</a> such as enough English-language tutoring. &#8220;If I asked for help, they would say, &#8216;Ask one of your classmates to help you,&#8217;&#8221; Colon said.</p>

<p>Colon never finished high school at Phoenix. But the reason, he said, had nothing to do with the instruction.</p>

<p>One day, after he had been at Phoenix for a couple of years, Colon alleges that a Camelot team leader, Adam Cobb, goaded him into a fight when they were alone in a classroom. Cobb denied Colon&#8217;s assertions in an email statement and a phone conversation.</p>

<p>According to Colon, Cobb screamed, &#8220;Come on, hit me, tough guy, now that we&#8217;re alone,&#8221; his face so close in that Colon said he could feel the spit. Cobb, who stands 6 foot 5 and wears size 18 shoes, then pushed him into a desk. Colon tried, futilely, to fight back. Cobb quickly got his arms around Colon and lifted, jamming him so hard into the ceiling that Colon's head dislodged a tile. When Colon finally broke free, he ran away, escaping through one of the school&#8217;s back doors. His shirt came off in the tussle, so he left it behind and tried to run home bare-chested. Cobb caught up to him, however, and, according to Colon, pleaded with the teenager not to tell anyone about the incident. &#8220;He asked me to leave it alone, which I never should have,&#8221; Colon said.</p>

<p>By Cobb&#8217;s account, none of that happened. &#8220;I understand how to utilize &#8216;handle with care&#8217; and I practice it precisely at the rare occasions that a student is a threat to themselves or others,&#8221; he wrote. &#8220;I have never shoved a student through a desk, or raised anyone up into the ceiling tiles and run out of the building.&#8221;</p>

<p>In an interview, Cobb said there were &#8220;a handful&#8221; of instances when he had to physically escort Colon out of a classroom &#8212; which he did by placing two hands on one arm (one hand between the elbow and shoulder, and the second between the elbow and the wrist). He described it as a &#8220;simple escort&#8221; and said he would then counsel Colon verbally. Cobb said part of his role was to make &#8220;a big deal out of something small so something big didn&#8217;t occur&#8221; and that he looks at the students under his supervision &#8220;as if they are my own.&#8221;</p>

<p>Colon said he didn&#8217;t report the incident to authorities because he feared school officials and the police would take Cobb&#8217;s side, and that he, not Cobb, would get in trouble.</p>

<p>Colon eventually told his mother. She complained to a Camelot official, according to her son and a person familiar with the situation. The school took no action, Colon said. He suspects that school officials found it convenient to brush her off because she only spoke Spanish. &#8220;A lot of the parents didn&#8217;t speak English, which is part of the reason they got away with it,&#8221; Colon said.</p>

<p>Cobb said he never met Colon&#8217;s mother, or heard any mention of her complaints. &#8220;I&#8217;ve seen his mother zero times,&#8221; he said.</p>

<p>Three other people who have worked at or attended the school say they witnessed Cobb being inappropriately physically aggressive with students on other occasions. Two more people said he verbally crossed the line. Cobb defended his job performance and said at least one of those people worked on a different floor and wasn&#8217;t in a position to know.</p>

<p>Camelot said it has no record of a student or parent complaining about Cobb. It described him as &#8220;an outstanding staff member who has gone above and beyond in caring for the needs of the children in his care.&#8221; Cobb was eventually promoted to director of operations at another Camelot-run school in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania.</p>

<p>Rachel Raytik, who worked as a teacher and academic coordinator at Phoenix Academy between 2010 and 2014, described it as a &quot;tough, tough, volatile environment. Some students do need to be restrained.&quot; While Cobb meant well, she said, he had a temper and would escalate situations rather than calm students down.</p>

<p>Told of Raytik&#8217;s comments, Cobb said, &#8220;A temper has never been my issue.&#8221;</p>

<p>Ultimately it was Camelot's responsibility to provide more support to staff or remove them if necessary, Raytik said. To add resources or hire more qualified people would cost money that Camelot didn&#8217;t want to spend. &#8220;They run themselves like a company, not a school,&#8221; she said.</p>

<hr />

<p>Altercations between Camelot staff and students rarely end up in court. More often the cases disappear &#8212; whether because of the student&#8217;s or family&#8217;s reluctance to pursue them; a lack of witnesses; the accusers&#8217; checkered backgrounds; superficial investigations by the police; school districts&#8217; hesitancy to get involved; or some combination of all five.</p>

<p>Three different students accused Jamal Tillery of assault in 2011 while he worked as director of operations at Camelot Academy in Pensacola, Florida, according to police records. Tillery denies the claims in all three cases, and none went far in the legal system. Getting to the bottom of the 6-year-old incidents isn&#8217;t simple. The Pensacola police reports contain several redactions, and parts of them are confusing. In all three cases, officers appear to have taken Tillery&#8217;s word over the students&#8217; &#8212; at least at first.</p>

<p>In the first incident, a 13-year-old student, who weighed 90 pounds at the time, claimed that Tillery grabbed him, threw him to the ground, and spit in his face. The 13-year-old fled to a Walmart store, where an employee helped him contact police. A police officer dropped the investigation because he said he could see no visible injuries on the boy&#8217;s body and because Tillery denied the 13-year-old&#8217;s account. The officer reported interviewing no one else apart from Tillery and the teenager in his 23-minute investigation.</p>

<p>Nine days after allegedly assaulting the 13-year-old, Tillery had a physical altercation with a student. When 16-year-old Ladaryl Purifoy refused to sit down, Tillery spit in his face and threw him across several chairs, according to Purifoy&#8217;s family. Purifoy&#8217;s mother called police from the hospital the evening of the incident, reporting that her son had been beaten up at Camelot. But police officers did not document her concerns until nine months later, when Younbloski Purifoy called a second time to complain. Even then, police only spent 10 minutes investigating her allegations, according to their report, which noted that staff members blamed Purifoy for instigating the fight with Tillery.</p>

<p>Eight months after the incident with Ladaryl Purifoy, 17-year-old Jeremiah Jones argued with Tillery after refusing to hand over his cellphone. Jones said Tillery and another staff member pulled him into the Tiger Shark room and punched him repeatedly on the face and body. At one point, the second staff member held the student&#8217;s arms behind his back while Tillery allegedly punched and kicked the teenager in the face, striking him with a trashcan.</p>

<p>In separate interviews, Jones&#8217; mother, Stephanie Henderson, and his great-aunt, Annie Brown, said the teenager came home that day with bruises all over his face. The school had sent Jones home on the bus as usual, without notifying them that anything had happened, they said. The mother and aunt went the next day to Camelot Academy, where, they recalled, the director informed them that Tillery had been suspended, and would be removed from his position. That same day, Jones, his mother, and his great-aunt approached the police. The police heard them out, but the women, like Younbloski Purifoy, said their concerns weren&#8217;t taken seriously. If it had &#8220;been any other school and a parent complained of abuse by a staff member they would have done something,&#8221; said Brown.</p>

<p>Both women say they never talked with police or Camelot officials again, despite several attempts to reconnect with the school director on the phone and in person. Two weeks after the alleged beating of Jones,&#160;<a href="http://inweekly.net/wordpress/?p=8255">authorities arrested and charged Tillery</a>&#160;and his colleague with battery. But for unknown reasons, they didn&#8217;t move forward with the case.&#160;In a statement about the case against Tillery&#8217;s colleague, the Office of the State Attorney cited &#8220;insufficient evidence to prove this case beyond reasonable doubt.&#8221; Asked for more information, a spokeswoman for the office responded that the files were destroyed a year after the case was closed &#8212; a procedure she described as routine.</p>

<p>Jones left Camelot Academy immediately after the alleged incident. His mother enrolled him in a GED program where, she said, he struggled to work independently and eventually quit. Several months after clashing with Tillery, Jones was arrested for aggravated assault and armed robbery. He was convicted, and is currently in prison in Bonifay, Florida, his mother said.</p>

<p>In an email, Tillery said he had never seen the police reports for the incidents involving the 13-year-old or Ladaryl Purifoy. He added that &#8220;any allegations regarding me assaulting or abusing either of these students are false and untrue.&#8221; In the case of Jeremiah Jones, Tillery said that &#8220;Camelot completed an internal investigation and found it to be unfounded.&#8221; More importantly, he added, the police &#8220;reviewed my case and dismissed the allegations.&#8221; He said Jones had actually assaulted him.</p>

<p>While student privacy prevented the company from discussing the specifics of the incidents involving Tillery, he &#8220;was cleared of any and all charges,&#8221; Camelot said.</p>

<p>Pensacola&#8217;s school district stayed out of the Tillery cases. It let Camelot investigate and address them, said Vickie Mathis, the director of alternative education for the district. &#8220;They are Camelot employees,&#8221; she said. &#8220;We expected Camelot to do the investigation and come to a finding and take action if there was a finding of wrongdoing.&#8221; Mathis recalled &#8212; mistakenly &#8212; that Camelot reported Tillery had been fired.</p>

<p>In two other cities, Reading, Pennsylvania and New Orleans, school officials cut ties with Camelot as abuse allegations emerged. In New Orleans, six students, a youth advocate, two judges, and a former Camelot staffer all described <a href="http://www.nola.com/news/index.ssf/2009/06/schwarz.html">episodes of &#8220;slamming&#8221; at a Camelot-run school to The Times-Picayune</a> in 2009. Camelot&#8217;s statement said these claims were &#8220;unfair.&#8221; Paul Vallas, the superintendent of the Recovery School District, which oversaw the school, dropped Camelot and brought management in-house. But Vallas, who had previously worked with Camelot as chief executive of the Philadelphia schools, said his decision had nothing to do with the abuse reports and everything to do with finances: He thought the school district could run the school more cheaply than Camelot could. &#8220;They&#8217;ve done a pretty good job, all things considered,&#8221; Vallas said, when asked at the time about the company&#8217;s record in New Orleans.</p>

<p>In August 2014, days after charges were brought against Seals and Bivens in connection with the assault on Corey Mack, Reading school officials issued a statement saying they were &#8220;appalled&#8221; by the behavior of the two staff members at Paramount Academy and were reviewing the district&#8217;s relationship with Camelot. Just a week later, they entered into a termination agreement with Camelot. The contract stipulated that both parties would &#8220;release a mutually agreeable joint statement to the press&#8221; that would cast neither party in &#8220;a negative light.&#8221; Camelot said in its statement that the district&#8217;s discontinuing of the contract had nothing to do with the beating of Corey Mack. And district officials declined to comment for this article.</p>

<hr />

<p>In most middle- and upper-income communities, parents provide an informal yet crucial form of accountability for schools &#8212; protesting, and even suing over, mistreatment of their children. But this safety net is largely missing in the Camelot schools, where parents lack the knowledge, confidence, resources or language skills to complain. Those who have come forward say that few people in positions of power, including school officials, lawyers and police officers, take them seriously &#8212; if they listen at all.</p>

<p>For Younbloski Purifoy, Ladaryl&#8217;s mother, seeking justice for her son has become a personal crusade. Since Jamal Tillery allegedly assaulted Ladaryl in 2011, Purifoy has complained to police, lawyers, the NAACP, Pensacola&#8217;s mayor, the U.S. Department of Justice, and the Florida Commission on Ethics, among other places. So far, all of her efforts have been in vain.</p>

<p>Ladaryl Purifoy&#8217;s uncle, Tony Neal, retrieved his injured nephew from Camelot Academy that February afternoon six years ago. The school bus driver had refused to transport the injured teenager, insisting that Purifoy should go straight to the hospital instead. So school officials called Neal to pick him up.</p>

<p>When the uncle arrived, he spoke with Tillery, who told him that staff had had to &#8220;restrain&#8221; Purifoy to stop him from fighting. Neal says Tillery encouraged them to leave before the police arrived, stating that he didn&#8217;t want Purifoy to get in trouble. In hindsight, Neal wishes he had overcome his instinctive fear of police and stayed at the school to advocate for his nephew.</p>

<p>School officials &#8220;think that they can get away with this because they think that nobody cares about these kids, that nobody loves them,&#8221; Neal said.</p>

<hr />

<p>Unlike teenagers with academic or emotional problems from wealthy families, students who felt mistreated or unhappy at Camelot had few other options. If they couldn&#8217;t stand it, they dropped out, and entered adulthood without high school diplomas and, in some cases, bleak futures. In the unforgiving mathematics of the American economy, no degree usually equals a low-wage job, or unemployment.</p>

<p>Luis Colon tried going back to Camelot for a short time. But he felt anxious, his grades started to slip, and he didn&#8217;t want to be there anymore. Colon wasn&#8217;t scared that Cobb or other staff would do him real harm, but that he would retaliate and face harsh legal consequences. &#8220;I didn&#8217;t want the teachers to keep touching me because then I would do something stupid,&#8221; he said.</p>

<p>So Colon dropped out. He lives with his mother and is the main breadwinner for her, his girlfriend and his girlfriend&#8217;s 8-year-old child. One fall afternoon, he reflected on his hopes for the future while sitting in his mother&#8217;s living room, just down the street from Phoenix Academy. Colon said he has a full-time job at a warehouse that processes everything from furniture to clothing and shoes; he operates the lift machine. He hopes to become a mechanic someday. He has also completed an online Bible school program. But he regrets that he didn&#8217;t enroll at a more traditional high school. &#8220;That should never have happened in a school,&#8221; he said. &#8220;They are supposed to be like your second parents, watching you.&#8221;</p>

<p>In Reading, Pennsylvania, Corey Mack, now 20, dropped out after the beating. He said he simply didn&#8217;t feel like attending school, even with Seals gone. When we visited Reading on two separate occasions, Mack was sleeping on his grandmother&#8217;s couch. He has a young child with an ex-girlfriend and works occasional odd jobs, including helping friends move, according to his mother.</p>

<p>Since 2014, when Mack left the Camelot school, he has been arrested half a dozen times, with convictions for brawling, harassment, and public drunkenness. He is currently in prison as a result of a physical altercation with his brother, according to their mother.</p>

<p>Mack believes he would have stayed in school and graduated if not for the body slamming that day. &#8220;It&#8217;s too late now,&#8221; he said.</p>

<p>Nearly three years later, his mother, Sharon Pacharis, remains incensed about the incident &#8212; and its effect on her son. &#8220;They knew kids had behavior issues and they tried to use that as an excuse,&#8221; she says. The school&#8217;s mentality was: &#8220;I guess their parents aren&#8217;t going to beat the crap out of them, so we&#8217;re going to beat the crap out of them.&#8221;</p>

<p>Ladaryl Purifoy stayed home for a few weeks after the altercation with Tillery in Pensacola. He tried to start over at a new school, but he still suffered from pain in his shoulder as a result of the alleged assault, according to his mother. He also had recurring nightmares that people were chasing him, trying to beat him. Purifoy never finished high school &#8212; a direct consequence, he said, of the trauma he endured at Camelot. Charges of unarmed burglary and theft are pending against him.</p>

<p>Camelot placed Tillery on leave during its investigation of the allegations against him. He now serves as executive director of Camelot&#8217;s Excel Academy of Southwest, in Chicago, far from Pensacola. &#8220;Despite the fact that the allegations against him were determined to be unfounded,&#8221; a Camelot spokesman said, &#8220;the negative experience hurt him personally, and we agreed to have him work in another community.&#8221;</p>

             <p class="note related-note"><p>The Teacher Project is an education reporting fellowship based at Columbia Journalism School dedicated to covering the issues facing families and teachers. ProPublica reporter Heather Vogell contributed to this article.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5472526.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-08T06:00:36-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>For New York Families in Custody Fights, a Black Hole of Oversight</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5467918</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/for-new-york-families-in-custody-fights-a-black-hole-of-oversight/#28669</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/joaquin_sapien/">Joaquin Sapien</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>When Anna Frank lost custody of her 9-year-old son, she blamed her husband and the judge who decided the case in his favor.</p>

<p>She also faulted Barbara Burkhard, a psychologist appointed to evaluate the family and advise the court on the matter. According to Frank, Burkhard concluded &#8212; after meeting Frank once and without interviewing her son &#8212; that their claims of abuse were invented and that Frank had poisoned her child against his father.</p>

<p>Frank ultimately regained custody of her son, based partly on testimony from other psychologists who disputed Burkhard&#8217;s contentions. But before she did, she sought sanctions against Burkhard from the agency that oversees licensed psychologists in New York.</p>

<p>Frank&#8217;s densely detailed, 12-page complaint to the Office of Professional Discipline was never investigated, let alone acted upon.</p>

<p>&#8220;Due to our inability to access records or discuss the services rendered with this psychologist, we are unable to investigate this matter or to initiate disciplinary action based upon your complaint,&#8221; a letter from the office, from the spring of 2012, explained. &#8220;I am sorry we cannot be of more assistance to you.&#8221;</p>

<p>The office&#8217;s response was typical, a ProPublica examination shows.</p>

<p>Though psychologists who appear in New York&#8217;s Family and Matrimonial Courts help shape decisions of grave consequence &#8212; from custody to child protection to juvenile delinquency &#8212; their work is subject to little or no professional oversight, purportedly because the confidentiality of such proceedings makes them hard to penetrate even for regulators.</p>

<p>Several lawyers who have represented parents in such court cases say they and their clients have received similar responses when they&#8217;ve tried to pursue complaints against court-appointed psychologists with OPD.</p>

<p>&#8220;They rely upon a bureaucratic Catch-22 to avoid having to take a hard look at misconduct and take their responsibility of oversight seriously,&#8221; said Timothy Tippins, who wrote a 2016 article for the New York Law Journal on inadequate oversight of such evaluators. &#8220;You can&#8217;t make this bureaucratic bullshit up.&#8221;</p>

<p>Pace University law professor Merril Sobie, a former chair of the New York State Bar Association&#8217;s Committee on Children and the Law, has pressed OPD on what recourse exists for families who challenge the competence or objectivity of the psychologists in their cases. The agency has provided few answers.</p>

<p>&#8220;It&#8217;s a black hole,&#8221; Sobie said.</p>

<p>When ProPublica asked OPD several months ago to explain why it did not investigate complaints against psychologists working in family and matrimonial courts, officials responded with little more than a description of the office&#8217;s mandate and staffing. They declined requests for interviews.</p>

<p>This month, when we pressed again, the office &#8212; an arm of the New York Department of Education &#8212; issued a short statement indicating it was seeking more authority to gather information in such investigations:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;The State Education Department investigates every complaint that alleges conduct constituting professional misconduct through its Office of Professional Discipline,&#8221; the statement said. &#8220;The Department&#8217;s ability to investigate court-appointed psychologists can be hampered because the records necessary to pursue such an investigation are, by law, private and open to inspection only upon permission of the Family Court. To help eliminate this potential obstacle to a thorough investigation, the Department is discussing with the New York State Legislature amendments to the law that would give our professional conduct officers greater access to court records. We will continue to pursue such an amendment this legislative session.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

<p>Without intervention by OPD, there&#8217;s virtually no place to take complaints against court evaluators.</p>

<p>Since 2008, New York City&#8217;s Appellate Court has had a committee that certifies the just over 200 psychologists and psychiatrists who get court appointments and can adjudicate complaints against them. Through June 2015, it had received 10 complaints and issued two admonitions.</p>

<p>But while the committee can bar problem practitioners from testifying in court, it has no authority over psychologists&#8217; licenses. Moreover, court systems elsewhere in the state haven&#8217;t set up such committees, partly out of fear that certification requirements might dissuade qualified professionals from taking appointments in regions where practitioners are difficult to find.</p>

<p>&#8220;They didn&#8217;t want to put things in the way of getting people to do this work,&#8221; said Jacqueline Silbermann, a former top New York Matrimonial Court judge who was involved in setting up the city&#8217;s certification committee and pushed courts outside the city to do the same. &#8220;The bottom line is they didn&#8217;t.&#8221;</p>

<p>That leaves OPD, whose investigators are tasked with responding to complaints not only about the state&#8217;s nearly 14,000 licensed psychologists, but nearly 50 other kinds of professionals, from dentists to massage therapists.</p>

<p>The agency, also known as the Office of the Professions, has come under fire before for its weak enforcement. A <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/weak-oversight-lets-dangerous-nurses-work-in-new-york">2016 ProPublica investigation</a> found it had not implemented criminal background checks for nurses that are routine in other states and often took years to administer discipline. Critics say it is also impeded by its unusual structure. As part of the Department of Education, OPD comes under the state&#8217;s Board of Regents, whose primary responsibility is to oversee the state&#8217;s vast public education system, and needs board approval to impose its stiffest sanctions.</p>

<p>But in the case of Family and Matrimonial Court psychologists, OPD&#8217;s oversight is not so much flawed as it is absent entirely.</p>

<p>Since 1994, according to a review by ProPublica, only one evaluator who is today approved for court work in New York City has been disciplined by the state, and it is unclear whether that action had anything to do with work he may have done for the courts. Since Family and Matrimonial Court evaluators elsewhere in the state aren&#8217;t certified, it&#8217;s impossible to know if any have been disciplined.</p>

<p>At a 2012 public hearing, Nancy Erickson, one of the attorneys who represented Frank, called OPD&#8217;s approach to overseeing psychologists one of the court system&#8217;s most troubling aspects.</p>

<p>&#8220;This refusal of OPD means that psychologists who are incompetent or even corrupt can continue to make money by doing custody evaluations that could end up misleading the courts and harming children and their families,&#8221; she said.</p>

<hr>

<p>The tumultuous saga of the Frank family provides as good a window as any into court evaluators&#8217; pivotal role in custody cases.</p>

<p>Anna Frank had filed for divorce in 2007 in Suffolk County Supreme Court, which handles matrimonial matters. She says her husband of 16 years, Michael Frank, was prone to screaming fits and physical aggression. Police records show she called local officers to complain of physical abuse several times as the marriage unraveled. Each parent had had the other arrested over domestic disputes. Their young son allegedly bore witness to their violent fights and later said he, too, suffered abuse at the hands of his father.</p>

<p>Michael Frank denies ever abusing either his wife or son, and insists the police reports were based on false allegations.</p>

<p>Anna Frank, though, did get a one-year order of protection against her husband and sought to dissolve the marriage. The Franks then came before Suffolk County Supreme Court Judge Andrew Crecca, with Anna seeking custody of her son, child support, and what she deemed her share of the family&#8217;s finances and Michael, the primary breadwinner, seeking to protect his assets and gain full custody of his son himself.</p>

<p>To sort through the competing accusations, the judge appointed Barbara Burkhard. Burkhard&#8217;s company, Child and Family Psychological Services, P.C., had provided therapeutic services to children since 1999 under a contract with Suffolk County&#8217;s Department of Social Services. (Burkhard did not respond to repeated emails and phone messages regarding this story.)</p>

<p>In the Frank case, Burkhard started out in 2008 functioning as what&#8217;s known as the Franks&#8217; &#8220;parenting coordinator,&#8221; where she would oversee transfers of the child by his warring parents.</p>

<p>Then Judge Crecca took the somewhat unusual step of appointing Burkhard to complete a forensic psychological evaluation of the family. Normally these roles are kept separate in order to avoid preconceived notions on the part of the evaluator.</p>

<p>In January 2009, Burkhard was part of a chaotic dispute involving the Franks. Anna was supposed to drop her son off at Burkhard&#8217;s office so he could be picked up by Michael. But he refused to get out of her car. Burkhard tried to speak with the boy in the car. He was crying, yelling, telling her he did not want to go. He said his father had abused him, sexually and physically. When the boy&#8217;s father arrived, he, too, tried to talk to him in the car. In a terror, the boy got out of the car and darted across a busy street. With some coaxing from Burkhard&#8217;s staff, the boy came back and embraced his mother, insisting he go home with her. The police arrived and questioned everyone at the scene and the boy went home with his mother.</p>

<p>Based on what she saw, Burkhard recommended in a &#8220;preliminary report&#8221; that the boy be removed from his mother&#8217;s care immediately. She determined that what the boy needed most was more time with his father, outside of his mother&#8217;s sphere of influence. She recommended that Michael Frank receive temporary, sole custody while the divorce proceedings progressed. The judge followed her recommendation.</p>

<p>Anna Frank felt the actions were unfounded and unfair and that the court had essentially awarded sole custody to her husband based on a single episode. Burkhard never interviewed her, or her son, and now, in Anna Frank&#8217;s view, the psychologist was putting him in harm&#8217;s way.</p>


<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/dysfunction-disorder-nyc-family-court-flawed-mental-health-reports">Dysfunction Disorder</a></h2>
     <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/dysfunction-disorder-nyc-family-court-flawed-mental-health-reports"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170117-nyc-family-court-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>NYC paid millions for flawed mental health reports. Family court judges relied on them routinely. Parents and children lived with the consequences. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/dysfunction-disorder-nyc-family-court-flawed-mental-health-reports"> Read the story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>And according to court records, the boy did suffer. His behavior and state of mind deteriorated after that. Usually a strong student, his grades began to decline. Rather than completing assignments, he&#8217;d scrawl all over them that he wanted to see his mother. He complained to teachers and social workers that his father had beaten him with a belt and locked him in a basement. His behavior grew increasingly erratic. He tried to run away. He broke windows. He urinated and defecated around the house. Social workers with Child Protective Services became a regular presence at the boy&#8217;s home, but their reports echoed Burkhard&#8217;s belief that Anna Frank was encouraging the boy to make false allegations of abuse.</p>

<p>Burkhard, in report after report, told the court the boy had become &#8220;enmeshed&#8221; with his mother, potentially succumbing to something akin to what&#8217;s known as &#8220;Parental Alienation Syndrome.&#8221; Burkhard&#8217;s reports suggested his mother may have convinced him to make up abuse allegations, in order to heighten her chances of winning custody.</p>

<p>Burkhard had the boy evaluated by more mental health professionals, and Judge Crecca decided the boy should be removed from both parents and live at a residential treatment center called Little Flower, in Wading River, about 30 minutes from where the Franks lived. He first came to the home in December 2009.</p>

<p>Over the next few years, Frank said she spent every penny she had battling her husband in court to get her son back. She lost her job as a school psychologist after Child Protective Services filed a neglect charge against her &#8212; deeming her responsible for her boy&#8217;s fear of his father. The school, she said, decided she couldn&#8217;t work with children with such a charge pending against her.</p>

<p>&#8220;They tried to strip me of everything I cared about,&#8221; Frank said, in a recent interview. &#8220;It was devastating.&#8221;</p>

<p>She said she supported herself by taking jobs in retail, making a meager $10 an hour after growing accustomed to an $80,000 annual salary.</p>

<p>She said Little Flower came to believe her son was telling the truth about his father all along and helped her regain custody.</p>

<p>In January 2010, Little Flower delivered a report to the court stating that the boy&#8217;s relationship with his father remained deeply strained and that his psychiatrist was concerned about the boy&#8217;s tales of abuse. </p>

<p>Anna Frank said staff from the home agreed to testify on her behalf, urging the judge to believe the boy. Again, Burkhard weighed in, recommending that if the boy were to leave Little Flower, he should move back in with his father. The home&#8217;s staff disagreed. They told the judge if the boy wasn&#8217;t going to move in with his mother, he&#8217;d be better off in foster care, Anna Frank said.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Michael Frank consented to a settlement that granted custody of the boy to his mother.</p>

<p>In an interview, Michael Frank said he never &#8220;abused his son or her, never, never, never.&#8221; He said his wife lied in a number of ways: The police reports were false, and Little Flower never took her side. And he claimed Anna lost her job not because of the neglect charges, but because she &#8220;stopped showing up to work.&#8221;</p>

<p>He said he was the &#8220;stable parent.&#8221; He said his wife had &#8220;brainwashed&#8221; their son. He repeatedly cited the fact that she is a trained psychologist, which, as he put it, &#8220;gave her plenty of knowledge on how to manipulate young kids. And that&#8217;s exactly what she did.&#8221;</p>

<p>But by the end, he said he had little choice but to &#8220;give up.&#8221; He said his son was clearly suffering and their relationship felt irrevocably fractured.</p>

<p>He said Burkhard had handled the case professionally.</p>

<p>&#8220;There was no rush to judgment,&#8221; he said.</p>

<p>Robert Gallo, one of several court-appointed attorneys who wound up representing Anna Frank over the five-year court battle, told ProPublica that the case, taken as a whole, reflects a dire need for outside oversight:</p>

<p>&#8220;I don&#8217;t want to sound like I am bashing Burkhard,&#8221; he said. &#8220;In that case, I thought she was wrong. But I&#8217;ve had others where I thought she was right. Take her out of the mix, and a different psychologist may have just looked at the same facts and got a whole different view. Which is why there should be some oversight and some real clear rules. I don&#8217;t think anybody is doing that today.&#8221;</p>

<hr>

<p>Anna Frank sure tried.</p>

<p>During the custody battle, she was determined to hold Burkhard accountable for the assessment that helped lead to the loss of her child. She complained to OPD in April 2011.</p>

<p>The agency&#8217;s investigators are charged with ensuring &#8220;public protection&#8221; from &#8220;professional misconduct&#8221; across a variety of licensed professions. When it comes to psychologists, their complaint process is no different for practitioners doing evaluations for Family Court than for matters such as fraudulent billing or disclosing private medical information that might come up in private practices.</p>

<p>In cases in which OPD&#8217;s investigators substantiate complaints, the agency can issue administrative warnings for minor violations or &#8212; in more serious cases, which are reviewed by a violations committee &#8212; fine or censure licensees.</p>

<p>The committee can also refer cases to the state Board of Regents, which can refer the most egregious cases to the state attorney general for criminal prosecution. The board can also revoke a professional&#8217;s license.</p>

<p>Complaints against psychologists are relatively rare and discipline is even rarer. In 2015, for example, 88 complaints were filed against psychologists statewide and OPD issued one warning, two violation decisions, and four regent actions.</p>

<p>But to Erickson, Frank&#8217;s lawyer, OPD&#8217;s professed unwillingness to even look into complaints about the subset of practitioners acting as court evaluators is particularly problematic.</p>

<p>Erickson brought Frank&#8217;s case and several others like it to the state bar association&#8217;s Children and Family Law committee, then run by Merril Sobie, in April 2011. OPD seemed to have &#8220;a policy against investigating complaints that arise out of a court proceeding,&#8221; Erickson told the committee.</p>


<div class="graphic-promo">
    <figure>
        <img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_630/20170307-nancy-erickson-inline.jpg" />
        <figcaption>Nancy Erickson, an attorney who helped Anna Frank with her case (Chad Batka for ProPublica)</figcaption>
    </figure>
</div>


<p>She pointed out that complainants had few good options other than OPD. The American Psychological Association, for example, publishes non-mandatory guidelines for forensic evaluations and looks into complaints about practitioners, but has little enforcement power. A &#8220;psychologist can simply drop his or her membership,&#8221; Erickson said.</p>

<p>Sobie was struck by what he described as OPD&#8217;s &#8220;hands-off&#8221; policy and decided the committee should pursue an explanation for it.</p>

<p>ProPublica obtained Sobie&#8217;s subsequent correspondence with OPD and its director, George Ding.</p>

<p>In his first letter, dated December 2011, Sobie described the problems his committee saw in OPD&#8217;s handling of complaints about evaluators.</p>

<p>He said complainants were often told to address their concerns to the judge presiding over their custody case, when the judge &#8220;would in all likelihood advise the litigant to file a complaint with OPD, the APA, or another office,&#8221; Sobie wrote. OPD also advised litigants to write to the court &#8220;to release their reports and relevant records&#8221; so that it could begin an investigation, a step Sobie said would risk stirring up the &#8220;hornet&#8217;s nest&#8221; by demanding the presence of their ex-spouse after a grueling custody battle.</p>

<p>&#8220;The Committee believes that this policy may place many children in danger; unfortunately, no matter how many valid complaints are filed against a court-ordered custody evaluator OPD will not investigate,&#8221; Sobie wrote. &#8220;An incompetent (or unethical) evaluator could continue to harm children.&#8221;</p>

<p>Sobie closed the letter by offering to help Ding develop a better approach. &#8220;We would happily assist you in improving procedures to better protect New York&#8217;s children,&#8221; he said. </p>

<p>Then he waited. And waited.</p>

<p>The New Year came and went. He sent the same letter again in late January 2012.</p>

<p>&#8220;We would appreciate the courtesy of a reply,&#8221; he wrote.</p>

<p>Still, nothing.</p>

<p>&#8220;I was not happy,&#8221; he said, recalling his dismay in an interview. &#8220;I didn&#8217;t think they were fulfilling their responsibility. I didn&#8217;t think that was the appropriate way to respond to the state bar association. And they wouldn&#8217;t put a goddamn thing in writing.&#8221;</p>

<p>The following month, in February 2012, Erickson brought another complaint filed with OPD to Sobie&#8217;s committee&#8217;s attention.</p>

<p>In this instance, the psychologist &#8212; a highly active forensic evaluator based in Brooklyn named N.G. Berrill &#8212; was not even appointed by the court. He was retained directly by a man who sought to halt his ex-wife&#8217;s unsupervised visits with their children.</p>

<p>According to the complaint, Berrill never contacted the mother and never attempted to question the statements the ex-husband made about himself. And yet he concluded the mother&#8217;s relationship with the kids had a potentially damaging effect. Berrill wrote a letter to the court recommending that her visitations with her children be supervised by state social workers from then on. The woman wound up losing custody.</p>

<p>Asked about the Family Court case by ProPublica, Berrill declined to respond to the allegations in the complaint and said in an email he did not want his work &#8220;discussed&#8221; in this article.</p>

<p>When an investigator with OPD wrote back to the complainant, the responses struck her as bizarre.</p>

<p>The letter said that since the woman herself was &#8220;not the parent who requested the report from Dr. Berrill&#8221; and since the office could not &#8220;interview the children or obtain copies of the necessary records without the consent of the father, this office could not adequately conduct an investigation.&#8221;</p>

<p>It also noted that Berrill disclosed the fact that he never spoke to the woman and &#8220;the court recognized that fact.&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;It is based on this that the decision was made to close your file.&#8221;</p>

<p>Sobie, more alarmed than ever, wrote to Ding again in May 2012.</p>

<p>&#8220;It has come to our attention OPD&#8217;s policies are perhaps more seriously flawed than we thought,&#8221; he said, laying out the details of the complaint.</p>

<p>&#8220;The response from OPD is frankly incomprehensible,&#8221; he said. &#8220;When we wrote our December 1, 2011 letter, we thought OPD took a &#8216;hands off&#8217; policy only when the licensee was appointed by a court; the current example indicates that even a licensee who is not court appointed will not be investigated.&#8221;</p>

<p>Ding never wrote back.</p>

<p>After weeks of prodding, Sobie said he finally got a phone call from him.</p>

<p>&#8220;Essentially he said they can&#8217;t get involved if it&#8217;s a court ordered forensic because of confidentiality,&#8221; Sobie said. &#8220;I said &#8216;You are a state agency charged with enforcing professional discipline, I don&#8217;t see how you couldn&#8217;t do this. Don&#8217;t you have subpoena power? I find it very difficult to believe that a judge upon motion of a state agency who is charged with that responsibility would deny the motion. Did you ever do that?&#8217; And of course, they never did that.&#8221;</p>

<p>Ding did not respond to questions about Sobie&#8217;s version of their back-and-forth.</p>

<p>In 2012, Sobie&#8217;s tenure as chair of the Children and Law Committee came to a close. The committee subsequently lost some of its interest in evaluators.</p>

<p>Erickson said she continued to hear from mothers who felt OPD had unjustly dismissed their complaints.</p>

<p>In one such case, a woman was told by an OPD investigator that it found no &#8220;evidence sufficient to support taking action against the subject&#8221; but then explained that &#8220;a request for the official documents and the evaluation was denied by Family Court.&#8221;</p>

<p>Once again, OPD had apparently closed an investigation without getting the records it would need to even start it.</p>

<p>That case was featured in Tippins&#8217; law journal article, titled &#8220;Custody Evaluators: Where&#8217;s the Oversight?&#8221;</p>

<p>Tippins, a veteran attorney who has become the go-to expert in how to effectively challenge their work, has written extensively on the topic of oversight. In the article, he declared the OPD&#8217;s professed unwillingness or inability to investigate Family Court evaluators to be &#8220;as dangerous as it is derelict.&#8221;</p>

<p>&#8220;Evaluations are often flawed by bias, methodological deficiency, or both,&#8221; he wrote. &#8220;While many evaluators strive to present reliable expertise, incompetent or unethical evaluators are hardly strangers to the courts.&#8221;</p>

<p>He went on to explain that thorough cross examination of evaluators is rare and that cases are often settled on the basis of their work, making outside oversight an absolute imperative.</p>

<p>In his view, OPD provides nothing of the kind.</p>

<p>&#8220;If the subject were not so serious, this rigmarole would be worthy of Abbott &amp; Costello,&#8221; he wrote.</p>

<p>In his response to Tippins, Ding asserted that his office &#8220;investigates every complaint which alleges conduct constituting professional misconduct.&#8221;</p>

<p>Ding said he could not supply evidence of the office taking action against a court-appointed evaluator because its data &#8220;is not maintained in a manner that is based on the information that you are seeking.&#8221;</p>

<p>Tippins&#8217; article helped reinvigorate the bar association committee&#8217;s interest.</p>

<p>Ding accepted an invitation to their annual meeting last December.</p>

<p>Finally, Sobie and Erickson thought they might get some answers.</p>

<p>But Ding didn&#8217;t show up.</p>

<p>He apologized, saying he got the date wrong, and called in by phone, answering questions for an hour.</p>

<p>According to people who attended the meeting, he stuck to his claim that his office can&#8217;t investigate Family or Matrimonial Court cases because it can&#8217;t access essential records. Asked if he ever went to court to ask for records, he said he&#8217;d done so only once. Someone at the committee meeting noted that Ding could go to the state Attorney General&#8217;s office to seek a subpoena. According to those present, Ding said he assumed the attorney general had other priorities.</p>

<p>OPD disputes this version of events, but would not supply details as to what happened.</p>

<p>Ding did call the current head of the Children and Law Committee to complain that someone on the committee had described the meeting to ProPublica. He said it put him in &#8220;a very bad position&#8221; with the Attorney General&#8217;s office.</p>

<p>Sobie said the meeting left him certain of one thing:</p>

<p>&#8220;There is no professional oversight.&#8221;</p>            <p class="note related-note"><p><strong>Help us investigate:</strong> If you have experience with or information about the role of psychologists in Family and Matrimonial Courts, email <a href="mailto:Joaquin.Sapien@propublica.org">Joaquin.Sapien@propublica.org</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Related stories:</strong> For more coverage, read ProPublica&#8217;s previous reporting on <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/dysfunction-disorder-nyc-family-court-flawed-mental-health-reports">mental health evaluators</a>.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5467918.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-07T12:12:46-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Florida to Examine Whether Alternative Charter Schools Underreport Dropouts</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5461772</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/florida-to-examine-whether-alternative-charter-schools-underreport-dropouts/#28668</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/heather_vogell/">Heather Vogell</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>Florida&#8217;s Department of Education is expanding an inquiry into how schools classify students who leave without graduating, in response to a <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system">ProPublica report</a> that the state may have thousands more dropouts than it acknowledges.</p>

<p>Also in reaction to the ProPublica article, the school board chairman in Orlando is asking the district superintendent for a formal report regarding concerns that low-achieving students have been pressured to transfer from traditional to alternative high schools.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s &#8220;one allegation we take very, very seriously,&#8221; chairman Bill Sublette said. &#8220;If that&#8217;s going on, that&#8217;s intolerable. ... That cannot happen.&#8221;</p>

<p>Fifteen students at schools run by for-profit Accelerated Learning Solutions (ALS) in Orlando&#8217;s district said that, because of their academic performance, they had been denied admission to regular public high schools or told they had to transfer from them to alternative programs, according to our Feb. 21 article, which was co-published by USA Today. Some were pulled from class for surprise assemblies where ALS representatives gave a pitch to attend their schools.</p>

<p>Several traditional schools improved their graduation rates by dispatching students unlikely to earn diplomas on time to ALS schools, the article reported. Enrollment in alternative schools in Orlando&#8217;s district, Orange County, has tripled in recent years, swelling to 3,900 in 2014. District officials say transfers for academic reasons are voluntary.</p>

<p>ProPublica also found that these alternative schools could be significantly undercounting dropouts by coding students who leave as withdrawing to enter adult education, such as GED classes. State rules don&#8217;t label withdrawals for adult education as dropping out.</p>

<p>ALS ran seven of the 10 high schools statewide with the most withdrawals to adult education in 2015, including the top five. Company officials couldn&#8217;t say where these students actually went &#8212; or if they took any GED classes. If all such withdrawals from ALS schools in Florida were counted as dropouts, the number of times that students quit statewide in 2015 would increase by at least 5 percent. Last week, Orange County&#8217;s school board voted unanimously to renew its contract with one ALS school, Sunshine High, which had the most withdrawals for adult education in the state in 2015.</p>

<p>The state education department, which was already reviewing graduation-rate data, will broaden its examination in light of ProPublica&#8217;s findings, a department spokeswoman wrote in an email. The state board of education will consider the matter at its March 22 meeting.</p>

<p>Linda Stewart, a Democratic state senator representing part of Orlando, expressed dismay in a recent interview about the apparent underreporting of dropouts.</p>

<p>&#8220;This little play of numbers, it needs to be stopped,&#8221; Stewart said. &#8220;They need to play by the same rule book that everybody else plays by.&#8221; She said she would ask the state Department of Education to look into the questions concerning data collection and see if lawmakers could help with a &#8220;corrective measure.&#8221;</p>

<p>Last month, when ProPublica asked Orange County officials about traditional schools pressuring low-achieving students to transfer to alternative schools against their wishes, they denied it was happening.</p>

<p>Once the article was published, though, people stepped forward to say the issue had been simmering within the district for years. At the school board meeting last week, and in comments to ProPublica afterwards, board member Christine Moore said a &#8220;handful&#8221; of Hispanic parents had complained a couple of years ago about pressure to transfer to alternative schools run by a for-profit company. Moore said she had ALS &#8220;investigated,&#8221; and told district staff to speak with personnel at traditional high schools to make sure they were not pressuring students to transfer. She said she would like to see a checklist developed for such counseling sessions, to make sure families understand all of their options.</p>

<p>&#8220;My only concern is to make sure the parents and the students are counseled with all of the options and that they are given the choice,&#8221; Moore said.</p>

<p>Moore said that the investigation she spurred had corrected the problems. &#8220;There were systems put in place to be sure that every child had the opportunity to go into the setting that best met their needs,&#8221; she said. &#8220;And so to me, this has already been answered and addressed and it had been taken care of.&#8221;</p>

<p>A former middle school math teacher, Eric Schwalbach, said that former students of his who were struggling in high school told him they were encouraged to attend the charters. At the board meeting, he offered to provide the students&#8217; names and suggested that members &#8220;go to Sunshine personally and say &#8216;Hey, how did you end up here? Did somebody encourage you to leave?&#8217;&#8221;</p>

<p>He showed ProPublica copies of emails he sent to several school board members, Superintendent Barbara Jenkins and Florida Education Commissioner Pam Stewart last year that accused Orange County schools of improving their state ratings by exiling low achievers to alternative schools.</p>


<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system">&#8216;Alternative&#8217; Education: Using Charter Schools to Hide Dropouts and Game the System</a></h2>
     <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170221-alt-schools-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>School officials nationwide dodge accountability ratings by steering low achievers to alternative programs. In Orlando, Florida, the nation&#8217;s tenth-largest district, thousands of students who leave alternative charters run by a for-profit company aren&#8217;t counted as dropouts.<a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/alternative-education-using-charter-schools-hide-dropouts-and-game-system"> Read the story.</a></p>

    <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/devos-education-nominees-code-words-for-creationism-offshoot-raise-concerns">DeVos&#8217; Code Words for Creationism Offshoot Raise Concerns About &#8216;Junk Science&#8217;</a></h2>
    <p>Betsy DeVos, President Trump&#8217;s pick as secretary of education, has funded groups that champion &#8220;intelligent design,&#8221; a sophisticated outgrowth of creationism.<a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/devos-education-nominees-code-words-for-creationism-offshoot-raise-concerns"> Read the story.</a></p>
</div>


<p>&#8220;We can no longer just move 2000 (sic) kids that OCPS failed to meet their needs out of our low income high schools to subpar charter schools ...,&#8221; he wrote in a May 20, 2016, email to Jenkins, &#8220;to make our school grades look better on paper.&#8221;</p>

<p>And in <a href="http://www.fitzforschools.com/single-post/2016/06/24/DataDriven-Transparency">a blog post</a> last June that was emailed around last week, Matthew Fitzpatrick &#8212; a former district high school assistant principal &#8212; outlined how regular district schools could be improving test scores by pushing low achievers towards alternative schools like those ALS runs.</p>

<p>&#8220;Now, understand, many students are not finding success in traditional high schools, and they need a change of venue,&#8221; Fitzpatrick&#8217;s blog post said, &#8220;but we shouldn&#8217;t brag about the great success and progress we are making if all we did was get rid of our lowest students.&#8221;</p>

<p>Sublette, the board chairman, said he initially asked Jenkins to investigate students&#8217; claims in the ProPublica article that school staff pressured them to leave. Jenkins responded that she had already investigated the concerns, Sublette said, and found them without merit. Still, he said, he asked Jenkins to detail at the next school board meeting what steps she took.</p>

<p>Orange County parents also expressed concerns about the alternative schools at the board meeting. &#8220;Children who are not succeeding in a traditional school setting need more help, not less,&#8221; said one, Heather Mellet. &#8220;The answer is not to push these high-risk children further into the shadows.&#8221;</p>

<p>Mellet also asked Moore and a second board member, Pam Gould, to recuse themselves from the vote because they had accepted campaign donations from ALS. Moore has received $1,250 in contributions from ALS, its lobbying firm, and a lawyer who works for the firm. She said the donations didn&#8217;t influence her vote. &#8220;You go to a fundraiser and the lobbyist hands you checks,&#8221; she said. &#8220;We get contributions from lots of people.&#8221; Gould has received $2,000 from the same sources. Gould said the contributions were transparent and did not constitute a conflict of interest under Florida law. The school board&#8217;s attorney said at the meeting that neither member needed to recuse herself.</p>

<p>Sublette defended the quality of the ALS schools. &#8220;I&#8217;m proud of these schools and I&#8217;m not even hesitant about renewing this charter&#8221; with Sunshine, he said.</p>

<p>District personnel have said that shifting students to alternative charter schools doesn&#8217;t burnish the district&#8217;s overall numbers. Students who leave without diplomas count against the district&#8217;s graduation rate, even if they aren&#8217;t considered dropouts. The district&#8217;s overall graduation rate was 81.3 percent in 2016.</p>

<p>But that&#8217;s not the number district leaders use when boasting of Orange County&#8217;s academic prowess: Instead, they often prefer the higher graduation rate for traditional schools &#8212; which excludes charters like the ALS schools.</p>

<p>Sublette and Jenkins touted that rate in last year&#8217;s <a href="https://www.ocps.net/sb/Documents/2015-16/2016%20State%20of%20the%20Schools_FINAL.pdf">state of the schools address</a>, which is typically aimed at the business community as well as the general public.</p>

<p>&#8220;[T]he accomplishment we&#8217;re proudest of, and the one our community, our teachers, our parents and our hard working students deserve all the credit for, is our graduation rate,&#8221; Sublette said during the May presentation. &#8220;Over the past 15 years the graduation rate at our 19 traditional high schools has risen from 49 percent to 90 percent today!&#8221;</p>

<p>When Jenkins recently filmed a <a href="https://soy.aasa.org/video_player.php?vid=undefined&amp;vid_source=https://aasa-awards-storage.s3.amazonaws.com/soy/intro_videos/2016/1475184803f.mp4">short video</a> as one of four finalists to become the national Superintendent of the Year, she, too, cited only the traditional schools&#8217; rate: &#8220;The graduation rate among our traditional high schools is at an all-time high, at 89.6 percent,&#8221; said Jenkins, who was named Florida&#8217;s superintendent of the year last November.</p>

<p>Company representatives did not speak at the board meeting. &#8220;We are grateful for the School Boards support and recognition of our work and successes and remain committed to providing the highest quality of programming,&#8221; ALS President Angela Whitford-Narine said in an email.</p>

<p>At the request of Sunshine&#8217;s principal, one graduate, Charles Jackson, addressed the school board. Jackson&#8217;s comments suggested that, as with the students in the ProPublica article, his departure from a traditional high school may not have been entirely voluntary.</p>

<p>&#8220;It was the last chance for me,&#8221; he said. &#8220;I got moved on to this school, I got moved on to the next school, but I had to look within myself and have the support of special teachers and my mother and my family.&#8221;</p>

<p>Jackson added that he felt welcome at Sunshine.</p>

<p>&#8220;Just because my regular school didn&#8217;t want me,&#8221; he said, &#8220;Sunshine took me in.&#8221;</p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5461772.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-06T12:00:47-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How the Trump Administration May Be Skirting Its Own Ethics Rules</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5449874</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/how-the-trump-administration-may-be-skirting-its-own-ethics-rules/#28666</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">


            by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/site/author/justin_elliott/">Justin Elliott</a>
    
</p>
                                    <p>The Trump administration appears to be either ignoring or exempting top staffers from its own watered-down ethics rules.</p>

<p>As we have detailed, President Trump in January issued an order <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-watered-down-ethics-rules-let-lobbyist-help-run-agency-he-lobbied">weakening</a> Obama-era ethics policies, allowing lobbyists to work at agencies they had sought to influence. The Trump <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/01/28/executive-order-ethics-commitments-executive-branch-appointees">order</a> did limit what lobbyists could do once they entered government, banning them from directly handling issues on which they had lobbied.</p>

<p>But the administration may not be even following that.</p>

<p>We&#8217;ve found three hires announced this week who, in fact, are working on the same issues on which they were registered lobbyists while in the private sector.</p>

<p>Consider <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/02/27/white-house-national-economic-council-director-announces-senior-staff">Shahira Knight</a>, President Trump&#8217;s special assistant for tax and retirement policy.</p>

<p><a href="http://disclosures.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2016/Q1/300799320.xml">Lobbying</a> <a href="http://disclosures.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2015/Q4/300778250.xml">disclosures</a> show that Knight lobbied the government on a host of retirement and tax issues for financial services giant Fidelity. In one case, she lobbied against a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/04/07/your-money/new-rules-for-retirement-accounts-financial-advisers.html?_r=0">regulation</a> requiring financial professionals to act in the best interests of their clients when it comes to retirement accounts such as 401(k)s. The regulation is strongly supported by consumer advocates and strongly <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3478191-Fidelity-on-Fiduciary-Rule.html#document/p2">opposed</a> by Fidelity. Retirement savers lose <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3467046-Cea-Coi-Report-Final.html#document/p3">billions of dollars</a> a year because of conflicts of interest in the industry, the Obama administration estimated.</p>

<p>The Trump executive <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/01/28/executive-order-ethics-commitments-executive-branch-appointees">order</a> says former lobbyists like Knight cannot work in the &#8220;specific issue area&#8221; in which they lobbied, though that phrase is not defined.</p>

<p>Given that Knight lobbied on tax and retirement issues and is now working as Trump&#8217;s assistant on tax and retirement issues, how can she be in compliance with the ethics policy?</p>

<p>It&#8217;s not at all clear.</p>

<p>One possibility is that the Trump administration has issued waivers exempting Knight and the other lobbyists they&#8217;ve hired from the new rules.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, there&#8217;s no way for the public to know if this has been done. In a little-noticed action, Trump killed the Obama-era <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3478663-2015-Ethics-Pledge-Assessment-Report-EO-13490.html">requirement</a> that the Office of Government Ethics publish an annual report disclosing such waivers. Trump&#8217;s order also removed the requirement to provide a <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3458515-Obama-ethics-order-2009.html#document/p3">public interest justification</a> for waivers.</p>

<p>That means Trump can exempt an official from the lobbying limits at any time, for any reason, with no public disclosure.</p>

<p>Critics of the administration&#8217;s approach to conflicts of interest said it is impossible to know whether the rules are being ignored or rendered irrelevant by the officials implementing them.</p>

<p>&#8220;I very much suspect that Trump&#8217;s ethics executive order either is not understood within the administration and not enforced, or the White House counsel is single-handedly interpreting the restrictions of the executive order so narrowly that they are next to meaningless,&#8221; said Craig Holman of the watchdog group Public Citizen.</p>

<p>The White House didn&#8217;t respond to a request for comment about whether any waivers have been issued or the how the ethics policy is being enforced.</p>

<p>Asked about Knight, White House spokeswoman Lindsay Walters said in a statement:</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;Shahira Knight has been working with the Office of White House Counsel since before she joined the White House staff to ensure she is in compliance with all rules and regulations.&#8221;</p></blockquote>


<div class="callout">

     <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-before-would-have-no-problem-banning-lobbyists-trump-now-youre-hired">Trump Then: &#8216;I Would Have No Problem&#8217; Banning Lobbyists. Trump Now: You&#8217;re Hired!</a></h2>
     <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-before-would-have-no-problem-banning-lobbyists-trump-now-youre-hired"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_lead_ngen/20170214-trump-lobbyists-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>Donald Trump suggested during the campaign that he would ban lobbyists from his administration. Now they&#8217;re working at the very agencies they sought to influence.<a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-before-would-have-no-problem-banning-lobbyists-trump-now-youre-hired"> Read the story.</a></p>

    <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-watered-down-ethics-rules-let-lobbyist-help-run-agency-he-lobbied">Trump&#8217;s Watered-Down Ethics Rules Let a Lobbyist Help Run an Agency He Lobbied</a></h2>
    <p>President Trump&#8217;s executive order on ethics also cites a section of the law that doesn&#8217;t exist.<a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-watered-down-ethics-rules-let-lobbyist-help-run-agency-he-lobbied"> Read the story.</a></p>
</div>


<p>Walters wouldn&#8217;t provide any further details.</p>

<p>The two other lobbyists hired this week, whose names were first <a href="https://theintercept.com/2017/02/28/donald-trumps-economic-policy-team-is-stacked-with-lobbyists-and-conflicts-of-interest/">flagged</a> by The Intercept, are Michael Catanzaro and George David Banks. They, like Knight, were <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2017/02/27/white-house-national-economic-council-director-announces-senior-staff">named</a> to National Economic Council Director Gary Cohn&#8217;s senior staff.</p>

<p>Just a few months ago Catanzaro was <a href="http://disclosures.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2016/Q4/300851249.xml">lobbying</a> on fuel standards and greenhouse gas regulations for the &#8203;American Fuel and Petrochemical Manufacturers. He is now special assistant to the president for domestic energy and environmental policy.</p>

<p>As for Banks, disclosure records state he <a href="http://disclosures.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2015/Q4/300776513.xml">recently</a> <a href="http://disclosures.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2016/Q1/300790548.xml">lobbied</a> on environmental issues for a business group. He is now special assistant to the president for international energy and environment.</p>

<p>In an interview, Banks told ProPublica that he had signed an ethics pledge but no one from the White House Counsel&#8217;s office has contacted him about any restrictions on his job or the fact that he was a registered lobbyist.</p>

<p>&#8220;I haven&#8217;t had a conversation about it yet,&#8221; he said. He has not received a waiver.</p>

<p>Banks also said that he was mistakenly registered as a lobbyist due to an error by his office manager. His former <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Council_for_Capital_Formation">employer</a>, the American Council for Capital Formation, said in a statement that Banks &#8220;did not meet the legal threshold for registering with Congress as a lobbyist&#8221; and it is seeking to correct the filings.</p>

<p>That distinction matters because the Trump ethics policy applies only to officials who were registered lobbyists.</p>

<p>The law requires a lobbyist to register based on a complicated <a href="https://www.senate.gov/legislative/Lobbying/Lobby_Disclosure_Act/3_Definitions.htm">test</a> including spending more than 20 percent of his or her time lobbying. In recent years there has been a well-documented <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/news/2016/08/number-of-registered-lobbyists-plunges-as-spending-declines-yet-again/">decline</a> in the ranks of registered lobbyists, who must report details of their work publicly, and a rise in so-called <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/politics/articles/2017-01-30/trump-s-ethics-order-seen-as-potential-boost-for-shadow-lobbying">shadow lobbying</a> by people who do not meet the registration requirements.</p>

<p>The White House spokeswoman said that Knight and Catanzaro &#8220;have been working with the Office of White House Counsel since before they joined the White House staff to ensure they are in compliance with all rules and regulations,&#8221; but declined to provide any details.</p>

<p>There are multiple signs the Trump administration is not aggressively policing ethics issues beyond its handling of the rules on lobbyists. In January, Trump&#8217;s team cancelled a previously scheduled ethics and leadership training course for White House appointees, <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2017/03/trump-ethics-white-house-235586">Politico reported</a>.&#160;The White House Counsel&#8217;s office also <a href="http://www.latimes.com/politics/washington/la-na-essential-washington-updates-no-penalties-for-kellyanne-conway-for-1488409192-htmlstory.html">gave a pass</a> to Trump aide Kellyanne Conway for violating ethics rules by urging Americans to buy Ivanka Trump&#8217;s clothing line.</p>

<p>During the Obama administration, the White House posted copies of ethics waivers on its <a href="https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/21stcenturygov/tools/ethics-waivers">website</a>. Obama issued a handful to former lobbyists during his eight years in office.</p>

<p>The current White House website still has a <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/disclosures/ethics-pledge-waivers">page</a> for ethics waivers, but it is empty. It states: &#8220;Ethics pledge waivers will be published as they become available.&#8221;</p>

             <p class="note related-note"><p>Do you have information about ethics issues or lobbyists in the Trump administration? Contact me at <a href="mailto:justin@propublica.org">justin@propublica.org</a> or via Signal at 774-826-6240.</p></p>            <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5449874.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject>Trump Administration</dc:subject>
      <dc:date>2017-03-03T16:00:18-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Despite Federal Law, Some Rural Hospitals Still Turn Away Women in Labor</title>
      <link>http://tracking.feedpress.it/link/9499/5447442</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.propublica.org/article/despite-federal-law-some-rural-hospitals-still-turn-away-women-in-labor/#28665</guid>
      <description><![CDATA[
            <p class="byline">by Julie Lasson, for ProPublica,</p>
            <p class="note copublish-note"><p>This story was co-published with the Louisville Courier-Journal.</p></p>                        <p>The young woman&#8217;s water broke late one morning in August 2014, as she stood in the bathroom of her home in rural Kentucky.</p>

<p>Her mother rushed her to the emergency room at Jewish Hospital Shelbyville. She signed a slip at the front desk, listing her chief complaint as &#8220;labor.&#8221;</p>

<p>But Jewish Hospital had closed its obstetrics department eight years earlier. &#8220;We don&#8217;t deliver babies here,&#8221; the nurse told the woman over the phone, not realizing that she was calling from inside the emergency room, a government <a href="http://www.hospitalinspections.org/report/8426">inspection</a> found.</p>

<p>With no help offered, the woman and her mother went to a nearby gas station and called 911. An ambulance took her to a hospital 24 miles away, where she delivered a baby girl via C-section.</p>

<p>Under the federal Emergency Medical Treatment and Labor Act, or EMTALA, every U.S. hospital with an emergency room has a duty to treat patients who arrive in labor, caring for them at least until the delivery of the placenta after a baby is born.</p>

<p>But 30 years after EMTALA was passed, hospitals &#8212; particularly those in rural areas without obstetrics units &#8212; are still turning away women in labor.</p>

<p>A review of federal inspection reports shows that at least 20 rural hospitals around the country have been found in violation of EMTALA over the last five years &#8212; including Jewish Hospital Shelbyville. In several cases, women suffered serious complications after being turned away, or were misdiagnosed at facilities that lacked specialists in obstetrics.</p>

<p>A hospital in Willows, California, was <a href="http://www.hospitalinspections.org/report/6531">cited and fined</a> in October 2013 for not recognizing that 29-year-old Martha Guzman had preeclampsia, a dangerous pregnancy complication. Guzman suffered seizures later that night and was rushed to a different hospital, where she delivered a stillborn boy. She died the next day.</p>

<p>Some ERs not only denied treatment to women in labor, they also would not help them transfer elsewhere, records show. A woman turned away by <a href="http://www.hospitalinspections.org/report/6552">Monroe County Hospital</a> in Forsyth, Georgia, ended up calling 911 from outside the dialysis center across the street. Another woman, told there were no staff gynecologists at a <a href="http://www.hospitalinspections.org/report/6646">Hartford, Kentucky</a> hospital, called an ambulance from a grocery store parking lot.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s unknown how much such lapses contribute to the nation&#8217;s burgeoning rates of maternal mortality and serious pregnancy-related complications, but inadequate care and misdiagnoses clearly play some role, experts say.</p>


<div class="callout">

    <h2 class="pp-int-hed"><a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-propublica-and-npr-investigate-maternal-mortality">Help Us Investigate Maternal Health</a></h2>
    <a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-propublica-and-npr-investigate-maternal-mortality"><img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/get_involved_primary/20170210-maternal-mortality-300x200.jpg"/></a>
    <p>Do you know someone who died or nearly died in pregnancy, childbirth, or within a year after delivery?<a href="https://www.propublica.org/getinvolved/item/help-propublica-and-npr-investigate-maternal-mortality"> Please tell us your story.</a></p>

</div>


<p>EMTALA was passed primarily to ensure that emergency rooms couldn't refuse patients because they couldn't pay for services. Prompted by a catastrophic case in which a pregnant woman was turned away from two California hospitals that believed she had no insurance, the provisions outlined in EMTALA specific to labor reflected that a growing number of hospitals, especially in rural areas, had begun eliminating obstetrics departments because of high costs and a lack of doctors.</p>

<p>EMTALA has not reversed this trend. &#8220;The availability of OB services in rural areas has steadily declined since the beginning of EMTALA in 1985,&#8221; notes Dr. Todd Taylor, a longtime emergency room physician and EMTALA compliance consultant.</p>

<p>A <a href="http://www.norc.org/Research/Projects/Pages/declining-access-to-hospital-based-obstetric-services-in-rural-areas.aspx">study</a> by The Walsh Center for Rural Health Analysis shows the portion of non-metropolitan counties without hospital-based obstetric services grew from 24 percent in 1985 to 44 percent in 2002, pointing to EMTALA as one reason why. Another <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1475-6773.12441/full">study</a> by the University of Minnesota Rural Health Research Center found that 7 percent of hospitals in nine states with large rural populations closed their obstetrics units between 2010 and 2014.</p>

<p>An official at the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services said that the agency does not track whether hospitals drop obstetric services or if the number of EMTALA violations at hospitals without such services has grown.</p>

<p>The EMTALA violation at Jewish Hospital Shelbyville prompted CMS to cite the hospital for placing patients in &#8220;immediate jeopardy,&#8221; warning that if it did not swiftly fix the problems in its emergency room, it could lose Medicare funding.</p>

<p>&#8220;This was an existential threat,&#8221; said Dr. Peter Hasselbacher, who conducts research and writes about state health policy for his web site, the Kentucky Health Policy Institute. Government health programs cover over 75 percent of Jewish Hospital&#8217;s patients, he added.</p>

<p>The hospital, which is part of KentuckyOne Health, the state&#8217;s largest health system, says it has made the required changes.</p>

<p>&#8220;We are fully capable of dealing with obstetric emergencies at Jewish Hospital Shelbyville Emergency Department,&#8221; said Barbara Mackovic, Jewish Hospital Shelbyville&#8217;s senior manager of media relations. She said the hospital has the equipment and the board-certified personnel it needs to handle such cases and educates its employees on the law.</p>

<p>The hospital&#8217;s commitment to handling emergency deliveries hasn&#8217;t been tested, however. Since the case in August 2014, it has not delivered a baby, Mackovic said.</p>

<p>Dealing with emergency deliveries tests rural hospitals in several ways, experts say. These cases create tough decisions for all practitioners, but especially those who see a lower volume of patients and have less experience.</p>

<p>Active labor can be hard to diagnose unless it is obvious, and the process can take hours, said Dr. Shailey Prasad, an associate professor at the Department of Family Medicine and Community Health at the University of Minnesota. Doctors in rural communities who perform few deliveries should use simulations to maintain their skills so they&#8217;re ready when emergencies arise, he said.</p>

<p>Pregnant women in rural areas face a host of risk factors, including inadequate prenatal care, higher rates of tobacco and alcohol use during pregnancy, and fewer choices of providers and health care plans, according to the <a href="https://ruralhealth.und.edu/pdf/hart.pdf">Center for Rural Health at the University of North Dakota</a>. <a href="http://www.acog.org/Resources-And-Publications/Committee-Opinions/Committee-on-Health-Care-for-Underserved-Women/Health-Disparities-in-Rural-Women">The American Congress of Obstetricians and Gynecologists</a> says rural women experience slightly higher rates of hospitalizations due to complicated pregnancies.</p>

<p>Jennifer Boomer Trammell lives in remote Alpine, Texas (population 6,000). Last year, when she was pregnant with her second child, she saw the first obstetrician/gynecologist to come to town, but also traveled eight hours to Dallas for prenatal examinations starting at the 30-week mark of her pregnancy. She had severe complications during the delivery of her first child, now three and a half years old; the baby had to be medevaced to a hospital with a neonatal intensive care unit.</p>

<p>&#8220;It opened my eyes to how naive I was to give birth in a place like this,&#8221; she said. &#8220;I&#8217;m hyper-aware of how dangerous it could be.&#8221;</p>


<div class="graphic-promo">
    <figure>
        <img src="https://www.propublica.org/images/ngen/gypsy_image_630/20170303-jennifer-boomer-inline.jpg" />
        <figcaption>Jennifer, Neil and Abbott Trammell in Marfa, Texas. Abbott was medevaced to a hospital with a neonatal ICU after his delivery. (Jordann Tomasek, courtesy of Jennifer Boomer Trammell)</figcaption>
    </figure>
</div>


<p>She stayed in Dallas three weeks before the birth of her second child and six weeks afterwards. &#8220;I just don&#8217;t want to take that risk,&#8221; she said back in July, when she was making arrangements.</p>

<p>Some rural hospitals singled out for EMTALA violations have since made concerted efforts to change their approach. Harlan County Health in Alma, Nebraska, was <a href="http://www.hospitalinspections.org/report/6740">cited</a> for an incident in 2011 when an emergency department staffer told the boyfriend of a woman in labor that the hospital didn&#8217;t do deliveries and didn&#8217;t have a maternity ward, prompting the couple to leave.</p>

<p>The hospital itself reported the problem and, in response to the citation, hired a consultant to update its policies, gave the staff a half day of training on EMTALA, and purchased new equipment to be more prepared for emergencies, said Manuela Wolf, now Harlan&#8217;s CEO. The hospital also has a telemedicine system that allows practitioners elsewhere to guide hospital staff members through deliveries via live stream. Harlan has delivered four babies since the incident.</p>

<p>But not all facilities have followed suit, even if staffers are well aware of EMTALA&#8217;s requirements.</p>

<p>Government inspectors <a href="http://www.hospitalinspections.org/report/10523">cited</a> East Texas Medical Center Carthage in Carthage, Texas, for a July 2012 incident in which a staffer told a woman in labor that the hospital didn&#8217;t have obstetric services or an obstetrician, and didn&#8217;t know where ambulances were stationed to transfer her elsewhere. She and her husband tried to drive themselves to another hospital, but their car broke down, the inspection report said. An ambulance took them to the facility, where she delivered by C-section, but the baby died shortly thereafter.</p>

<p>As part of their investigation, inspectors turned up an email from one Carthage staff member to another, noting this was not the first time the medical center had turned away an emergency delivery.</p>

<p>&#8220;That very scenario is why we have the EMTALA law, and this,&#8221; the staff member wrote, referring to the July 2012 case, &#8220;was an EMTALA violation.&#8221;</p>

<p>Officials at East Texas Medical Center Carthage did not respond to questions about these incidents.</p>

<p>Experts say hospitals need to do a better job of upholding their obligations to women in labor, even if they&#8217;ve closed their obstetric units.</p>

<p>&#8220;It is hard to understand the legal requirements in an emergency room and many physicians have a mental block when it comes to the law,&#8221; said Dr. Larry Weiss, a physician, lawyer and University of Maryland professor of emergency medicine. &#8220;But ignorance of the law is no excuse.&#8221;</p>

<p><strong>Correction, March 3, 2017:</strong> <em>This article erroneously said Jennifer Boomer Trammell had complications so severe during the delivery of her first child that she was medevaced to a hospital with a neonatal intensive care unit. It was actually her child that was medevaced to the intensive care unit.</em></p>                        <img src="http://feedpress.me/9499/5447442.gif" height="1" width="1"/>]]></description>
      <dc:subject/>
      <dc:date>2017-03-03T06:00:38-05:00</dc:date>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
